Turn 39 Results - 2489 - Part 2

As rocks go, the one you've been taken to in central Middenland is far from the most impressive you've seen. It barely manages to stand taller than you, which is a low bar to clear in the first place, and you have to squint to see the faint remains of ancient carvings that have barely withstood millennia of wind and rain. You can find ones like it just about everywhere on the continent if you bother to look, and the only reason this one stands out is that it in despite of a moderate amount of ambient magical energies that have soaked into everything else around you, the stone is completely empty of magical energies. Stone might have a high capacity for absorbing magical energy, but given enough time any stone exposed to the elements would eventually accumulate as much earthbound energy as everything around it. But this one is, you expect, sending its magic to a nearby Waystone. "So," you say. "This is one of the Belthani tributaries." "Yes, Lady Magister," Magister Tochter Grunfeld says. "As typical a specimen as I could find." Cadaeth begins to examine the vegetation growing around it, and Baba Niedzwenka purses her lips as she looks the stone up and down. "Hm. Curious, but if I came across it I wouldn't stop to prod at it unless I was very bored." "That's probably why they're still around," you observe. "They're just rocks. For mundane purposes they're not large enough to bother bringing tools to quarry them, and for magical purposes there's nothing to work with, and if for some reason you want magically neutral stone you can get as much as you need from any mine or quarry. There's not even anything to corrupt like there are with Waystones, the magical inflow is through the natural tendency of earthbound energies to seek equilibrium. If you broke the outflow somehow they'd just become normal rocks and eventually become no more filled with magical energy than any other rock." "Can you observe the flow of energies?" Tochter asks curiously. You shake your head. "Not this far north, it took me a week of meditation to spot a Waystone-sized leyline in Reikland. Maybe if there were any in, say, southern Tilea or Estalia the background magic might be low enough for me to be able to spot it..." You consider further, then shake your head. "No, then there'd be less magic flowing to spot. By the mechanics of the tributary, the amount flowing out will never be higher than the background magic level I'd be trying to spot it through." "Perhaps you could spot the channel itself," Zlata says from somewhere behind you. "The channel might not be a distinct piece of magic," Cadaeth says. "The Waystones are already absorbing magic, if you release magic into the earth deep enough the magic will be pulled towards it as it diffuses. It doesn't take long before there's basically a magical rivulet that carves out a magically conducive channel using nothing but the absorbed ambient energies." "I take it that's how the Lornalim work?" She only hesitates for a moment before answering. "Only once their roots grow deep enough, otherwise the magic just 'floats' back up to the soil." She places her palm against the dirt at the base of the tributary. "And the depth required is significantly deeper than this stone goes." "Which way is the Waystone from here?" "Remind me to organize a Wayshard for you." Cadaeth concentrates for a moment, then points. "Roughly west," Tochter says after glancing at the sun. "We can do better than roughly." You pull the compass you borrowed from the Gyrocarriage's cockpit from a pocket and consult it, then look in the direction Cadaeth indicated. "In fact, I'd say it's exactly west." "Surely not exactly," Cadaeth says, standing and moving to look over your shoulder, then frowns as she looks at it. "Okay. Exactly. That would explain why they're able to maintain a flow from so much shallower. How, though? The Waystone is far enough away that it wouldn't be visible even if you levelled all the trees and hills in the way." "The sun and the stars," Tochter says simply. "To within a degree, though?" Cadaeth asks doubtfully. "Yes," she replies firmly. "The Belthani placed great importance on the angle of the sun. I once saw some rubbings that..." She frowns as she thinks. "Actually, I might be able to do better than rubbings. Lady Magister, may I use the authority of the Project to lay claim to some carvings in Talabecland?" "Whose authority do they currently fall under?" you ask warily. "It's disputed. The Taalites and Rhyans claim it because some of the symbols are ones they adopted, and the Order of Life is disputing them but haven't wanted to do so too hard because some of the rituals depicted are potentially questionable." "How questionable?" "Human sacrifice and the summoning of what we believe to be Sevirric spirits." "Ah. Not the sort of thing we generally like associated with the Colleges." She nods. "Do it. We're going to be casting so wide a net that this wouldn't seem out of place. Tell them that the Grey Order will vet the carvings. Then, as long as there's nothing in the carvings that's too improper, the Jades can have them once the Project is done." "Thank you, Lady Magister." You nod. "Okay, let's take rubbings and samples off this and head back to civilization." --- Magister Tochter Grunfeld has been busy, as the next time you see her it's with the fragments of a shattered decades-old jurisdictional deadlock in her wake. As a result thirteen ancient stone steles known as the Talastein Carvings have been transferred to the custody of the Colleges and transported five hundred miles to Tor Lithanel. Nine of them are dedicated to either depictions or instructions for specific religious rituals, two of them to the kind of measurements of sun and stars Tochter spoke of, one to the history and creed of the Belthani, and one either a shrine or a lexicon, filled with larger individual runes rather than pictographic sentences. Under Tochter's nervous eye you scrutinize the two that the Jades didn't want to lay too strong a claim to, and while the carvings are faint and damaged in places, the depiction of a human stretched out upon an altar is hard to mistake for anything else. "I can see why this would be the sort of thing you'd want to distance yourself from," you say neutrally. Tochter nods. "Some accuse the Druids of sacrifice to justify their faith being replaced by the Taalties and Rhyans, either by saying they were no different to the Cult of Ahalt or outright accusing them of involvement with Daemonic powers. This could be used to play right into that sort of narrative." You peer at the pictographs. "Well, to my eye this looks a lot closer to Eltharin than Dark Tongue. Weirdly close, actually. Too close. Tochter, talk to me about this language." "That's something I wanted to bring up with you in private. Your mention of 'silver ships' got me thinking of these in the first place, because this stone here," she points to one of the other steles, "is of the history of the Belthani. And these runes here," she points to a specific pair of pictographs, "were translated as meaning 'silver ships'." "Translated by?" She smiles. "Teclis." "Teclis translated this?" There was a time when you would have not questioned Teclis having knowledge of any language, but your time among the Dwarves and Eonir had introduced you to other perspectives on the Asur. "Why would an Elf of Ulthuan speak a language of the humans of the Old World? Even if they had bothered to learn the local languages when they were colonizing the Reik Basin, why would Teclis have gone to the trouble of learning one that by all accounts is entirely extinct?" "I have a theory about that, one that ties in to old legends about the Belthani coming from the west, just as the Scythians came from the north, the Tylosians from the south, and the Imperial Tribes from the east. Teclis was only able to translate a few scraps of the surviving symbols, but of those..." She begins to point. "'Came from beyond', 'deep waters', 'silver ships', 'nurture Her land'. What if the Belthani 'came from beyond' the Great Ocean? What if Ulthuan could interpret scraps of this language because it's a cousin of Anoqeyån? Because the Belthani were students of the Old Ones, just as the Elves were?" "Are you suggesting the Belthani came from Ulthuan?" "And they were taken across the 'deep waters' on these 'silver ships' to 'nurture Her land'. Is that not what we did? When the Elves got too caught up in their wars, the Belthani completed the network." You note and decide not to comment on the 'we' slipping through. "The idea is intriguing," you say, "and if it's true, then it means it might be possible to translate these symbols further. Teclis might have been able to pick some low-hanging fruit, but he was operating purely from memory. We, on the other hand, have the Library of Mournings to draw from." "Which means," she goes to one of the other rite steles, "that we might be able to translate this, the consecration ceremony, into something we can perform." "That seems like it would be reliant on Teclis being completely correct that the Druids only ever communed with the Jade Wind. He had something of a blind spot for the existence of divine magic." "Would it be so bad if we were able to reconnect the Jades to the Earth Mother?" Her tone is carefully neutral. "No, it wouldn't, but that's not the only possibility. Just because we have Her in mind doesn't mean She's the only one that might answer if we go around knocking on doors." "Ah. I see what you mean." "We'll keep the possibility in mind, but we'll start from the start. We'll commission some menhirs of various materials and start planting them, if we can recreate the tributaries with just a theodolite then we should. Failing that, we'll try enchanting techniques to make it work, and then try to operate within the paradigm of Gods we know the current mailing address of. This seems like it could fit neatly within the paradigms of both Halétha and the Ancient Widow." "Yes, Lady Magister." "Meanwhile, I'll try to find a hard answer for you about those two potentially dodgy steles." --- Spoken Eltharin, as you're very aware, is a beast of a language. Every word has multiple meanings, sometimes to the extent of being their own antonyms. It has sixteen different vowels, four of which are only ever used in proper nouns. To speak it is to constantly battle against ambiguity, which is part of why it's part of the basic syllabus for the Grey Order. Written Eltharin is even worse. Any given rune can be used to represent a specific idea, or to modify another rune, or as part of a phonetic rebus, and individual runes can be combined in various ways to give rise to new meanings. These are often deeply rooted in culture which inevitably shifts over time, meaning that to fully understand a given piece of writing you need to understand the time period of the author. Both are said to be greatly devolved and simplified from the arcane language of Anoqeyån, said to be the original language of the Elves and based on the language of the Old Ones. So you're feeling some trepidation at the idea of using Anoqeyån to try to translate severely damaged carvings with an unknown level of relation to that language. But the alternative would be trying to come up with a ritual completely from scratch, which is a lengthy and often dangerous process at the best of times. So you unleash Cadaeth on the Library of Mournings, and it's not long afterwards that books, scrolls, and tablets on both Anoqeyån and the Old One Tongue begin to emerge. That they do so in a trickle indicates that they're still carefully vetting what they give you, but it's an improvement over their previous complete stonewalling of you over any topic they considered magical. [Mathilde's study: Learning, 12+29+10(Polyglot)+10(Windherder)=61.] [Tochter's study: Learning, 74+18+10(Druid)+10(Ritualist)=112.] The project proves to be as gruelling as you feared, and your own agonizing and plodding research is quickly outstripped by Tochter filling page after page with notes. Unfortunately, having the Druid judge whether the Druids can have access to the questionable Druidic stele is not in keeping with the institutional paranoia of the Grey Order, so this doesn't mean you can drop the matter in her much more skilled hands and leave her to it, so you continue determinedly on. It doesn't take long for her to have broken the consecration ritual into what she believes to be discrete and translatable steps, and after receiving your praise for doing so she takes the first drafts to Cadaeth, Aksel, Zlata, and Niedzwenka for the five of them to see whether they can translate it into their individual paradigms. And you, meanwhile, continue at a cracking pace of two to three pictograms a day. --- It grates at you that you have to hear about progress with the rituals in dribs and drabs as Tochter reports back to you instead of being involved with the whole process, but vetting the steles is the price you paid for the leap forward that they represent, and you're not overburdened with free time to do both. So you suppress your desire to breathe down necks and let information trickle back to you as you make your gradual progress with understanding the steles. Tochter, to her very visible frustration, has had little progress adapting - or, in her words, updating - the ritual to something in the Jade Order's wheelhouse, and Zlata's work has been equally fruitless. But Cadaeth has what she feels is a very solid ritual for encouraging the forest itself to anchor a tributary stone, Aksel has very straightforwardly swapped out the Earth Mother for Halétha and is ready to give it a try, and Niedzwenka thinks she knows just the spirit to make power start flowing. That's certainly promising, but if there's anything you learned about rituals during your lessons at the Colleges, it's that you can never be entirely sure how well you've done at crafting one until you actually do it. And considering the potential repercussions a botched ritual can lead to, you'll have to carefully consider whether to go for a blunderbuss approach and approve all of them, or try to decide which of them is the most promising. [New action unlocked: attempt to create a tributary (select one or multiple: Dreaming Wood tributary, Haléthan tributary, Bereginya tributary)] "This one," you say to Tochter as you indicate the stone, "was an enormous pain. It turns out it's not describing a specific ritual, it's warning against a general type of ritual. If I'm right in that the left half of this rune here is a precursor to 'Urithair', and this one is to 'Tyloir' - which I'm not sure about, as the main meaning of 'Tyloir' indicates that its meaning has shifted in Elven tongues - then I suspect it's the result of some sort of schism or corruption of a branch of the Belthani faith, where sacrifices were made to empower or enrich individuals instead of for the good of the whole. Whatever the full story, it's my judgement that it's benign." "I'm glad to hear it, Lady Magister. Though it's a bit sad to hear that even back then they had those sorts of problems." "There's black sheep in every flock. Now this one," you say with a wave to the second one, "was challenging for separate reasons. A lot of the runes it used are defined only very vaguely by the books and scrolls, when they're defined at all. If you compare the depictions on the two sets of carvings, can you spot the differences?" Tochter looks from one to the other. "The subject on the warning one has their arms up as though bound, while the other doesn't." She peer closer. "They're also closer to the edge of the altar, instead of central to it." "Correct. I presume so they'd be properly accessible to a second participant in the ritual, who would be wielding something quite different to an athame." Tochter looks closer, and a touch of pink comes to her cheeks. "Oh." "Mm. I would guess the mix-up is because the runes for procreation have a lot of overlap with those for summoning, which raises the kind of metaphysical and philosophical questions I don't have time to pursue. I don't know whether the act to be performed is the target of the ritual or just a component of it, but while it might be best not to broadcast the details of it too loudly, I don't see a problem with releasing it to the custody of the Order of Life when we do the others." She nods, a genuine smile on her face. "Thank you, Lady Magister." --- To the gathered crowd of Hatalath, Thorek, Sarvoi, Elrisse, and Zlata, you begin discussing the third facet of the current investigation into the leylines. "At its broadest," you say, "the term 'leyline' has been applied freely to any underground passage of energy. For the purposes of this study, by 'leyline' I refer to the flow of energy between Waystones and Nexuses of the Waystone Network. This brings me to my first question: how does this work in the first place? By all accounts, stone is... not especially conducive to magic. And yet I know for sure that the energy flows beneath the bedrock, as I've seen it flowing with my own Magesight." "That would be an advantage for something like this," Hatalath says. "Channelling it through the air would be easier, but it would also be disrupted the first time a bird flew through it, let alone what a storm of magic would do. Planting the leylines in stone frontloads your difficulties - it's a huge challenge to set up, but once it's set up it'll last." "Magic may not flow through stone particularly quickly, but it does so reliably," Thorek says in agreement. "It doesn't change its speed based on the time of day or phase of the moon or because of the emotions of passers-by." "I'll grant you that, but that answers the 'why', not the 'how'. If you just pumped magic deep underground it'd radiate out in every direction, it wouldn't conveniently flow to wherever you directed it." "Momentum?" Elrisse hazards. "A constantly-maintained effect that makes the leylines the most conducive path?" "Or a permanent change," Sarvoi says, "either comparable to an enchantment, or an actual physical channel running between the Waystones." "Whatever it is, either it's inherently reversible or bidirectional, or the Ice Witches are already capable of recreating them, considering that magic currently flows from Kislev City to Praag." All heads to Zlata, who closes her eyes as she carefully considers her answer. "What I know of how that came about indicates that they are either bidirectional or impermanent," she eventually says. You nod as you digest that. "That seems like it would be testable," you say. "Find a suitable chain of three Waystones connected to a nexus, deactivate all three, and reactive the two furthest from the nexus. If energy begins to flow again, we can conclude that the effect is permanent. If it does not, then it must require a connection to the rest of the network, and either draws power from it or relies on the attractive force of the Great Vortex. If it's permanent, we get a shovel and a pickaxe and go see exactly what it is." "Is it necessary?" Elrisse asks abruptly. "It strikes me that this may be chasing perfection at the expense of sufficiency. How much of a river do we need to understand to be able to upend a bucket into it?" For a moment it strikes you as strange that this would be coming from a Light Wizard, but it occurs to you that they must be as trained to guard against perfectionism as a Grey Wizard is against an excess of paranoia. "Are there places where the Waystone network has been completely eliminated?" Sarvoi asks. One possibility occurs immediately. "Sylvania, I suspect," you say. "The Von Carsteins and their pretenders knew to target Waystones, and the nexus for most of them would have been Mordheim." "The Badlands," Thorek says shortly. "Mousillon, perhaps," Elrisse says. "So there would definitely be opportunities lost if we can't extend the reach of the Waystone network," you conclude, "but being able to strengthen it only where it still exists would still have significant value. What possibilities do we have for these 'buckets', then?" "Point-to-point line-of-sight transmission of magical energy is a well-trod path," Sarvoi points out. "If you don't mind the wind taking half of it on a good day," Hatalath counters. "It all would have been in the wind anyway," Sarvoi says. "Efficiency isn't so important as long as they're funnelled directly into a Waystone, our pseudo-Waystones could just suck it all back up and try again." "Some form of aqueduct for magic," Thorek suggests. "Needn't even be that large. Rope or wire, perhaps." "I suspect unattended rope or wire would have a habit of disappearing entirely overnight," you reply. Thorek frowns. "In areas where Grobi and the like lurk, aye, but what of more civilized areas?" "When rope is a denga a yard?" Zlata says. "It might be safer with the Grobi." "Would manlings really dismantle the Waystone network for free string?" Thorek asks, disbelieving. "Yes," is the instant response from everyone else. As Thorek splutters in outrage, Elrisse pipes up. "Even before its current form, magic flowed down the Great Vitae River. The Empire is built on rivers and they're already flowing in the direction we want it to go." "Ooh, yes, and-" Sarvoi begins, only to fall silent at a glance from Hatalath. You sigh. "You do remember that the path from the Ward of Rain, which we've all been using to come and go from the Empire, goes right past the Rainbow Falls, right?" Hatalath considers that. "While that is true that its general existence can be deduced, the source of-" "Portal at the bottom of the Tarn of Tears," you interrupt. "Have I made my point, or do we need to talk about tunnels and Smith-Priests too?" Hatalath seems to be quite perplexed at that, and falls into silence. "Okay, we can try to figure out the leylines, or we can try to make our own through air, string, or rivers. What do we think is the most promising approach?" [ ] Leylines Investigate and seek to recreate the existing leylines of the Waystone network. Unknown difficulty, potentially extreme. [ ] Air Begin working on a way to transmit magic from point to point through the air. Relatively simple, but results may be unsatisfactory. [ ] Material Begin working on a way to transmit magic through string or wires. Magically trivial, the challenge is finding a way of doing so that will not result in every nearby peasant making new tunics or cotton cards out of them. [ ] River Seek to understand and replicate how Nehekhara and Laurelorn transmit magic through rivers. Likely to be difficult, but could work very well for the Empire. --- You've decided to make a return to Castle Drakenhof, where under the ruins produced by the finest of modern artillery presumably lies untold generations of tunnels, tombs, catacombs, crypts, secret chambers, and, you hope, libraries. Not only are legends of the place thick with mentions of them, you know for a fact that it is possible for forces to have moved from the castle to a network of tunnels underneath the surrounding wilderness. But if you desire results, you're going to have to do more than go there with a shovel and a hopeful attitude. While your reputation and some of Belegar's gold will be enough to get you sufficient amounts of Dwarven miners who won't ask inconvenient questions, Sylvania remains Sylvania, and you're going to need forces to stomp down anything that might still be stirring and to keep watch against the ambient nastiness of the area. Zhufbar could likely be convinced to send a Throng to put a few more nails in the coffin of the Von Carsteins, or the Army of Stirland is already in the area and you'd likely be able to borrow a cohort or so. There's still Battle Wizards in Sylvania if you prefer quality over quantity, and the Knights of Morr are, of course, very well versed in holding off undead forces. But while there are all of those easy and straightforward options, it occurs to you that all of them might hold some strong opinions on the materials you might be unearthing, and may not be as open minded as you are about the diamonds that can be found in the very rough. And it's not really an idea that would be very easily communicable to most, is it? "I read the Liber Mortis and found it enlightening and not at all hazardous to one's soul!" is a conversational gambit that you don't have high hopes for. If you want to have full freedom to winnow through the books you might find, you might need to get creative about where you find the necessary forces. There's also the question of who else you might bring along on this adventure. The Celestial Order, though they usually prefer to make airy predictions that only make sense six months later and if you give them the benefit of the doubt, are actually quite capable of answering questions like 'what is the exact direction of the nearest book'. The Amethysts, judging by their showing last time they were in this neck of the wood, have some idea of where to find interesting buried secrets, and might be a bit more willing to share that information after they've replaced their Magister Patriarch and you've been promoted twice. There's a number of organizations that might be willing to help out in exchange for payment or access to some of the revealed information, such as the many varieties of Vampire Hunters or the Cult of Verena. And more personally, there are a number of trusted compatriots you've worked with that would be willing to go on another adventure with you, if you think they can be trusted to not ask too many awkward questions. There's Johann and Max, of course, as well as Egrimm and Adela. There's Kasmir, who's currently active in the area and is a lot more flexible than he used to be. Heidi is unlikely to be willing to join in in person, but she might have some useful insight - she was a Countess here for quite a while, after all - and might also be able to refer you to trustworthy coreligionists who might be able to help. You might be able to convince Cython to join in if you spin it enough tales about the legendary libraries of the Von Carsteins, though that's likely to result in it laying claim to a portion of the proceeds, and the sort of books most likely to be intriguing are the sort that it's hard to find a scribe trustworthy enough to make a copy of. And... well, you could go on for quite some time. Over your career you've worked with all sorts of skilled individuals. - There will be a twelve hour moratorium. - Part of this update was originally posted here. - The vote for the leyline investigation is separate to the vote for a plan for excavating Castle Drakenhof. The chosen leyline option will take place this turn, the others can be pursued in the future. - This plan is more freeform than usual, but Mathilde has enough clout and contacts that in this case it's not really practical for me to curate all the possibilities down to a finite list without cutting out a lot of interesting and creative options. If you have questions about a possible approach, let me know. - Example vote: [*] Plan No Flaws Whatsoever Garrison: Hire the Cursed Company Institutions: Hire a Skink Oracle, bring in the Cult of Alluminas Individuals: Fozzrick, Eshin-Friend, Templar Diederick Kastner

Turn 39 Results - 2489 - Part 3

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Leylines [*] Plan Redshirt v2 -[*] Garrison: Zhufbar -[*] Institutions: Order of Guardians, Celestial Order -[*] Individuals: Johann, Heidi, Kasmir Tally How does one prepare to see something that will be very faint and very temporary? The Colleges have a few answers, but most must be discarded as they are focused on seeing only one of the Winds and do so at the expense of the others. There are meditative techniques that Teclis tried to teach the Colleges which were duly recorded, but as these were intended to sharpen Elven Magesight - a full-fledged and almost universal sense in its own right, rather than the individual adaptations of the human soul that are filtered through the body's senses - they have proven to be useful only for those seeking insights into Elven spellcasting. So instead the Colleges use the teachings of Volans, the first Magister Patriarch of the Order of Light, who when summoned by Teclis had already spent decades honing his ability to see each of the individual Winds. For that reason, when it comes time to make preparations for the research of the Leylines you propose to Elrisse that the two of you make your preparations together. It's perhaps not the most effective of bonding experiences as it simply involves the two of you consulting Volans' writings on the subject and then spending a great deal of time in quiet meditation in a magically-neutral environment, but it's a gesture of acknowledgement towards the Light Order and it hopefully gets the standoffish-seeming woman a bit more used to your company. The Waystones you've selected for your observation and experimentation are a chain in the Howling Hills of southern Middenland. It cannot be described as entirely safe as the plentiful caves in the region hide their fair share of bandits and creatures, but the area is ruled over by the Knights Panther in Middenstag, making it very unlikely there would be anything in the area that could pose anything like a threat to the five of you. The others have made their own ways here from whatever preparations of their own they had been making, and the group convenes by the chosen Waystone at the appointed hour. "Time?" you ask after your arrangements are set up. Elrisse consults a pocket watch. "One minute until the downstream Waystone is deactivated," she reports. The five of you wait in silence for what feels like at least three before Elrisse says "now," and all of your attentions turn to the leyline below. The first change you notice is that some outer layer to the leyline seems to freeze in place, and them melt into the rest of the stream as it begins to slow. Moments later the flow downstream of this Waystone halts entirely, and energies begin to intermingle and disperse into the stone. The flow coming from upstream, however, continues unabated, and the energy arriving at this Waystone are absorbed by it. But not cleanly, you note - there's something of a pile-up at the Waystone that interrupts the careful dance of Winds orbiting Dhar, and by the time the Waystone absorbs them only Dhar remains. "The Waystones themselves seem to have no mechanism to reverse the creation of the energy packets," you note aloud. "It's reabsorbing the energy as only Dhar." "No wonder Necromancers and Sorcerers love to clog the flow," Elrisse says. "It does all the work for them." "Did anyone else note the way the outer layer of the leyline reacted first?" you ask, and Hatalath, Sarvoi and Zlata nod. "Would the outermost layer of a stream be the first to react?" Zlata asks. Thorek looks intrigued. "A helical energy stream?" "There was a distinct layer that reacted differently," Sarvoi says. "And then it melted into the rest of the energies. A control mechanism, I'd wager, and when it was cut off from wherever the strings are being pulled it collapsed into ambient energies and joined the rest of the stream." "The flow is still coming from upstream," Hatalath observes. "And likely would do so indefinitely. Eventually this Waystone would become filled to capacity, and then the energy will pile up and begin to radiate out, like a river breaking its banks. The disruption would continue upstream until it reaches that Waystone, and then it will reabsorb all the Dhar it releases until it too reaches its capacity. You would end up with a straight line of corruption between the two, with the Waystones turned into beacons of pure Dhar just waiting until a Storm of Magic forces more energy in and bursts the containment mechanisms." "Which would happen everywhere there is a Waystone if the flow to Ulthuan was ever completely cut off," you note grimly. "Which so far seems to include every major population centre on the continent." "Interesting that deactivating a Waystone stops the next Waystone upstream from sending it energy, but not anything further up the line," Sarvoi notes. "Optimistic, I'd say. It was built with the assumption that a Waystone would only need to be cut off from the network for long enough to maintain or replace it, so there would be no possibility of problems accumulating upstream. Having to permanently remove a Waystone from the network wasn't accounted for." "The reign of Bel Shanaar was a heady time," Hatalath says distantly. "We all thought it would last forever." You concentrate and speak a control phrase of Anoqeyån to deactivate the Waystone, and note that the flow from upstream continues unabated. "Energy is still coming in," you note. "So the instruction to halt the flow of incoming energy is communicated by the control mechanism. I suppose that makes sense, with it removed there's no way to communicate against the flow." "I could see a need to isolate one Waystone from the larger network to be a lot more foreseeable than having to shut down an entire branch of the network in one fell swoop," Sarvoi muses. "Or it was assumed that if they did need to do so, they could just go to each one individually." You nod and light a small signal rocket to tell Johann to shut off the upstream Waystone, and wait and observe as the flow finally slows to a stop. "So far it seems like halfway between our two hypotheses," you observe. "There's some sort of central control mechanism, but the flow can continue when cut off from the greater network, up until the Waystones reach capacity." You look to Zlata. "And if the flow was maintained instead of being dammed, and energy was being taken out at least as fast as it is being added, then it could last indefinitely." Zlata returns your gaze, gives it some thought, and nods. "So if we had a way to spend the energies..." Sarvoi begins. "Including the Dhar?" Elrisse asks pointedly. Sarvoi considers that. "Ah. Yes, I see your point. There are arguments to be made about lesser evils in some circumstances, but scaling up to a size of a continent means rapidly running out of evils great enough to justify such widespread use of corruptive energies." "Unless there was a way to convert Dhar into some other, more benign form of energy." You turn your look to Thorek. "It is said," he says heavily after a long period of thought, "that the Ancestor Gods and those that learned from them could create Runes with that capability. Some of the very least of those techniques were rediscovered by the Runelord Alaric, but he drove himself mad seeking more than that. And only a very few Runelords are capable of reliably using them." "Would they be at all scalable?" you ask. "If Kragg had spent his entire long life doing nothing else, then he would perhaps have managed enough to protect a tenth of Altdorf." You grimace. "And it stands to reason that even if any logistical concerns were handwaved away, any still-existing examples of the greater Runes would have a finite throughput." Thorek takes even longer to consider this answer. "It does stand to reason," he eventually concludes. "The only other possibility would be divine," you observe. "A deity willing to dedicate Themselves to a land and take upon Them the burden of purifying a constant stream of Dhar within that land into divine energy." All eyes turn to Zlata. "Kislev is land, land is Kislev, we are Kislev," she says simply, her voice only betraying a hint of nervousness. "But even if we simply assume that it would be possible to implement the same approach in the Empire, the merest hint of the idea would instantly split the Empire into at least three parts." "Bretonnia might be capable of it," Elrisse observes. "Maybe so, but Bretonnia doesn't have the Grey Mountains between it and Ulthuan." After you run out of observations to make, you fire off a second signal rocket to tell Max and Johann to reactivate their respective Waystones as you do the same to yours. Nothing immediately occurs in the Waystones so you sit and watch, and a few minutes later with shocking speed a hollow spool of energies flows upstream and latches on to the underground base of the Waystone like a talon around a fieldmouse, and moments later the Waystone begins to send energies downstream as though it was never interrupted. The grasping energy spool launches itself onwards towards the next Waystone, leaving the outermost layer of the leyline in place behind it and before long it fills with the rest of the energies flowing downwards. "Well, that was abrupt," you comment. "I think we can safely say that there's some sort of centralization at play here, and not merely a passive attractant." "Some sort of enchantment?" Hatalath suggests. "If it is, then it must be modifiable, considering the Fort Solace reroute," Sarvoi says. "Unless it sends those talons up any extant energy stream, then you could add a new junction to the network by sending power down it until the enchantment recognizes it as a pathway." "If it's predetermined then reactivating any old Waystone would let it reconnect to the network, whereas if it's adaptive then there's a time limit before the energies fade to a point where it's no longer recognized and you need to be able to blaze that trail manually," you say. "Considering the sheer amount of power that would take, I don't like the idea of having to trial-and-error that." "What would that time limit be, though?" Zlata asks. "Energy flow through bedrock?" Thorek says. "As a very rough rule of thumb, it won't fade entirely for at least a tenth of the time the energy flow had to establish itself, and if you want to actively keep track of it, check it every hundredth. So for most of the network, in the area of decades for there to be enough time for noticeable change." You frown at that. "Not the sort of thing that's feasibly testable even if we were willing to sacrifice a Waystone to do so, then. Still, we can try deactivating them for a day and then a week and see if there's any observable differences." There's general agreement, and the conversation shifts into lively debate about whether to spend the night at the spa village of Bad Hohne or the ferry town of Delberz. --- The results the next day seem to be more or less the same, so you deactivate the Waystones once more and arrange to reconvene next week. When that day comes around, everything seems to be as normal until the Waystones are reactivated again. You'd braced yourself for the speed that the reactivation had shown previously, but this time it was even faster and impacted the Waystone with enough metaphysical force to send up a nimbus of disturbed energies. There's a flicker of arcane energies and something within the Waystone shifts, its carvings glowing a sullen red for a moment, and then the regenerating network rampaged on upstream. "Well," you say, as you fruitlessly try to blink away the afterimages that don't actually have anything to do with your eyes. "That was abrupt." "Why would it be faster after a long wait?" Elrisse asks. "Does it build up the energy to restore the connection while it waits for it to be restored?" "That might make sense to a much lesser degree, but not this dramatically," Hatalath says. "If we're in the realm of decades for any noticeable difference, such a drastic build-up of energies over merely a week would be completely disproportionate." "It was the same amount of magical energy," Thorek says confidently. "The difference in effect must be down to how it was applied." "I suspect..." Sarvoi begins, then speaks the deactivation phrase, to which the Waystone completely fails to respond. "Yes, see? We annoyed it, so it took away the clapper and slammed the door. Fascinating. I suppose it's at least somewhat encouraging that it didn't smite me for trying." "If it's thinking and feeling, it can't be an enchantment, surely," you say. "Normally so, but at a large enough scale the normal rules break down," Hatalath says. "And it would be hard to find anything larger than this." "Anything that thinks and feels without a soul invites something to fill the void where a soul should be," Elrisse says. "Though the idea of something that could fill a void that large is a daunting one." "Could it be a God controlling it?" Zlata asks. "Hoeth would be the obvious candidate, but by all accounts He doesn't get snappish quite that easily," Sarvoi says. "If you're looking for a thinking mind in the Vortex that's inclined to be cranky, why go past the one we know is there? Perhaps there he endures, drunk on power, bitter with impotence, curdling in the malefic nightmare of his own existence?" "Caledor Dragontamer?" you ask, and Sarvoi nods. "I thought he sacrificed himself to create the Vortex." "Oh, by all accounts he did. But the most potent way to sacrifice your life has always been to do so one day at a time." There's a long, quiet moment as everyone tries to digest that idea, and you find it sticks in the throat quite unpleasantly. Hatalath looks especially horrified. "Whichever it might be, it does answer our original question," you say, plowing determinedly forward. "I assume among the keyphrases Teclis didn't share with us, there's one to point the network towards a new Waystone and let it do the work. I don't suppose Laurelorn has that information?" "Ulthuan was very willing to share the work of creating the network with the colonies, but not so much any meaningful information about it," Sarvoi says. "I'll round up some of my brighter students and examine the known keyphrases to see if there's some extrapolatable commonalities, but at best it would be a starting point for trial-and-error experimentation, and we just learned that it doesn't like that." "What about the Grey Lords?" you ask. "Those of us who were from Saphethion weren't considered trustworthy enough," Hatalath says with a sniff. "Considering some of those that were, I take it as an endorsement." "So we try to extract it from Ulthuan, try to extract it from Naggaroth, or try our luck prodding the enchantment further," you say dubiously, and you get the round of nods you expected but did not want in response. "Well, I suppose we knew going into it that it wasn't going to be easy." - Less substantial of an update than I'd like, but spooling back up after a period of the morbs is always a bit of a process. More to follow when it comes.

Mining Mount Drakenhof, Part 1

To those only passingly familiar with the Dwarves, the concept of Grudges can seem like a toxic one. To spend the lives of living Dwarves on the wrongs done to those long dead seems shockingly wasteful. But as you've become familiar with the Dwarves, you've come to believe that Grudges are not the cause of Dwarven troubles, but a bandage over them. The human mind is capable of letting the past stay in the past: leaving the past in the past, letting bygones be bygones, least said, soonest mended. To a human, a grudge is something that needs to be tended and nurtured, something to be constantly stoked lest those fires begin to die. But the average Dwarf, you suspect, is no more able to let the past be forgotten than they are to breathe underwater. To them, unredressed emotional pain is as strong decades later as it was the day it was inflicted upon them. A Dwarf who has been wronged and has no way to right that wrong will be forever haunted by it until it drives them mad, as inevitably as a river carving a valley through stone. In this way, a recorded Grudge is the mirror to the Slayer Oath: where a Dwarf that has wronged others and cannot fix it seeks to die for the Karaz Ankor, a Dwarf that has been wronged and cannot fix it seeks to live for the Karaz Ankor. Their Grudge being recorded is a promise that someday, somehow, the Karaz Ankor will take vengeance on their behalf, and this means that any act that strengthens the Karaz Ankor becomes an act of vengeance. But the cost of this is that even the canniest and most cynical of Dwarven leaders must still pay heed to the Grudges of the past, because the promises of a Book of Grudges might represent a titanic outlay of lives and resources, but it is also the mortar that keeps the battered souls of the Dwarven people from falling apart. To entirely ignore it would be to undermine their entire society. While often tragic, this has one immediately applicable upside to you: that if you show up at their door with a way to cross out a few of those Grudges that is cheaper in lives and resources than anything else available to them, you can very often rustle up a throng at a moment's notice. Especially if you have a proven track record in that regard. For this reason you have made your way to Zhufbar, to meet with a Dwarf you haven't set eyes on in over a decade. "Thane Weber!" Thane Thori Stoneheart greets you with a hearty handshake. "I'm glad to cross paths with you once more. You showed promise back in Sylvania, but I never could have guessed how much your saga would entwine with that of the Dawi." "The Throng you led was a rock of stability and reliability in a time when it was sorely needed, which played no small part in my decision to lend my sword to the causes of the Karaz Ankor," you reply with a smile. "If it weren't for King Belegar calling for aid, I might have come here instead to join the Karak Varn expeditions for a time." "Aye? A shame that those that lurk in its depths will never know how close they came to extinction, then. I don't suppose you've come here to deliver it to them?" "I'd love to, but there's more enemies in the world than there are days in a lifetime, and my attention is needed elsewhere. The unfinished business I want to put paid to now is that of Castle Drakenhof." "Seemed fairly finished to me. Barely one stone left atop another, as I recall. That's the naming deed for that belt of yours." "I'd call it done and good against most enemies, but not the Zangunaz. We saw for ourselves that there are tunnels leading out of the Castle, and I've heard more stories than I like of tombs and crypts and catacombs within and under the mountain itself, full of treasures and secrets and monstrosities. When the next Von Carstein seeks to start another Vampire War, I want them to have to start from scratch." He nods in thought. "Something like our raids on Karak Varn, then?" "Aye, though ideally without as much time pressure. The Countess of Stirland has Sylvania suppressed enough that there's a reasonable likelihood we'd be able to completely secure the site and excavate at our leisure, unless it turns out something's already moved in." "Hazier payoff though," he says with a frown. "The veins of Karak Varn are very well mapped, but the underside of Karag Drakenhof has only stories to guide our picks." "I'll be bringing in a skilled Skarrenzhufokri of good repute that will be able to point us towards what we seek." "That the same type of Zhufokri that blew up a quarter of that city last time?" You suppress a wince, and after a moment of thought decide to step around that instead of addressing it head-on. "No, that was a Zonzhufokri. I had a Skarrenzhufokri with me during Karak Eight Peaks, and two for the Karag Dum Expedition." "Mm. Well, I suppose if you're vouching for them, that's enough for me. Who else is on board?" "Cleric Tarni of the Order of Guardians and Abbot Ionel of the Council of Manhorak will be available to take care of any ceremonial duties or esoteric difficulties that we might come across." You've yet to meet either, but Gunnars and Kasmir respectively spoke well of them. "That makes things easier." He considers matters a while longer, then nods. "It wouldn't disrupt much to redirect one of the forces preparing for a Karak Varn raid, and I'll see what else I can round up for it. Grudges from that lot always need to be struck out the hard way since they can't be relied upon to properly die, so it'd be worth it for that alone before we even account for the possibility of recovering Dwarven treasures or fallen." You nod, glad the tough part is done with, and then the two of you get to the tricky job of scheduling and logistics. --- Twenty miles as the crow flies is not always twenty miles as an army marches, and when mountain ranges are involved the distances can become very skewed indeed. Most Throngs from Zhufbar that had business in the lowlands would need to travel either westwards to southern Stirland or north to Karak Kadrin to reach the road network, turning it into a journey of two hundred miles or more. But the Throng that Thane Thori has put together is not the usual artillery-heavy force that Zhufbar favours, instead being a Karak Varn raiding force of Ironbreakers and miners reinforced by Rangers, and so they were able to take the direct route across the mountains and follow the uppermost trickles of the River Drak down into Sylvania proper. When they do so, they are met by a rather motley group of three Wizards and two Priests, two of which being you and Johann, the other three new and interesting acquaintances. As one initiated into the service of Gazul, Cleric Tarni has no past that she will speak of, but her fluent Reikspiel with a Reikland accent and her clumsy Khazalid with a Grey Mountains accent tell you plenty. She's quiet, intense, wiry, and constantly seems to be watching you, though you can't tell if it's out of caution or curiosity. She's short even by Dwarf standards, her mail is a dull black, and the sword on her back has an eerie blue gleam that you're rather familiar with. If you find any Dwarven remains, or any Vampiric ones that can be identified as having wronged the Dwarves, they will be her responsibility, and you get the impression that if you encounter any Vampires that still need to be turned into remains, you wouldn't be able to stop her from doing her best to make that happen. Under what you assume to be Kasmir's direction, the Council of Manhorak has structured itself along monastic lines, and so the High Priest of Darmorak is titled the Abbot of Dark Moor. Of the four, it's the one you know next to nothing about. Bylorhof is where the worship of Bylorak kept one corner free of Vampiric influence, and Grim Moor and Hel Fenn were the sites of the defeats of Konrad and Mannfred von Carstein, and, presumably, where they still remain. All you really know is its approximate location on a map, but that location is at the headwaters of the Templa, nestled up against the mountains and no more than twenty miles from both Castle Drakenhof and Zhufbar. Abbot Ionel himself is a beardless man in his forties with kind eyes, long brown hair and a limp, who walks with the aid of a walking stick topped with an axe head and wears a long, curved dagger on his waist, both of which are made of a dull grey metal you'd guess to be bog iron. He's here as a demonstration of both authority and responsibility, and speaks of Vampires in general and Von Carsteins in particular with a quiet and tightly-controlled loathing. The final major figure to this expedition is more prominent than you expected, as you'd asked the Celestial Order for a skilled Magister or a talented and bold Journeyman and instead ended up with Lady Magister Goendul, who you'd last seen taking on Dragomas in the Obsidian Hall and receiving an Amber Spear through the torso for her troubles. She simply claims to have been working in the area anyway so helping out with this wasn't out of her way, but you can't help but wonder if perhaps she's here to peer over your shoulder and make sure you're not up to anything you shouldn't be. Or, as it is Celestials you're dealing with, there might have been some sort of premonition that may have led the Celestials to believe her presence here was necessary. She has the focused stillness of a cat readying itself for a pounce and moves with the unnatural lightness of one who pays only the most perfunctory of lip service to the pull of the earth. Her robes seem to have started as the standard billowing blue robes typical to her Order, but were then drastically tailored and belted until they could no longer be disturbed by the breezes that constantly spring up around her. A second Lady Magister is an always-welcome increase in magical firepower, but her chief contribution will be focused auguries to guide the picks of the Dwarves. "The main problem," Thane Thori says as he lays out maps in the shadow of Mount Drakenhof, "is that last time we were here, we did a damn good job of clogging up every egress. Any entrances to the catacombs from above will have many tons of broken masonry atop it, and the tunnel we found that seems to lead into it from below, we blew up. So we either start at the top and dig down, start at the base of the mountain and tunnel in, or we dig through the cave-in we caused in the access tunnel." Thori looks upwards to the top of the mountain, where Castle Drakenhof once stood. "If we go up the path to where the Castle used to be and clear out a campsite, we'd be the safest from any ambient nastiness that might be wandering around and we'd be able to carefully plan our approach downwards, but we'd also have the most tedious dig to go through." He looks back down at the base of the mountain. "We could start here and just dig our way right in the direction of what we're looking for - I'm told that there's a Zhufokri way to point the lads in the right direction. It would be a very ordinary mining operation, picks on unworked stone, very unlikely to spring any surprises on us. And it means we'd be easily able to fall back into the open instead of being trapped in close quarters with anything nasty that might still be prowling around in there. But it also means that if there's anything thinking and organized calling the place home, we won't be able to scout ahead and see what we're dealing with ahead of time, we'll be breaching right into their living rooms." He waves a hand towards the forest, where the concealed mouth of a tunnel leading to the castle can be found. "Of the three, the tunnels would be the fastest dig, but the riskiest - not just because we might have compromised the structural integrity of those tunnels with the explosions, but because we did so atop a whole bunch of skeletons who'll suddenly become our problem once more if we unearth them. But once we're through that we'd be coming right up through the underbelly." There's also, you reflect, the question of what you'll be doing during the digging. There's a collection of interesting and important people here, and getting to know one of them will keep you entertained while the Dwarves do the difficult work of carving through rock or rubble. Approach: [ ] [APPROACH] Over [ ] [APPROACH] Through [ ] [APPROACH] Under Downtime: [ ] [SOCIAL] Thane Thori [ ] [SOCIAL] Cleric Tarni [ ] [SOCIAL] Abbot Ionel [ ] [SOCIAL] Lady Magister Goendul [ ] [SOCIAL] Zhufbar Ironbreakers - There will be a two hour moratorium. One from each category will win. - The Celestial Wizard recruited for this endeavour was rolled for here.

Mining Mount Drakenhof, Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [APPROACH] Through [*] [SOCIAL] Lady Magister Goendul Tally If you're going to have to dig anyway, why dig through the wreckage you left in your wake last time you're here? Digging through untouched stone is no problem for the Dwarves, and means that you'll be entering the catacombs from a direction anyone inside would not expect. Auguring the correct place to start digging will be the responsibility of Lady Magister Goendul by means of the spell Finding Divination. From what you understand, the spell can be used to pinpoint the direction of a specific object or the nearest example of a type of object, and the limitation that it tells you nothing of the distance can be easily bypassed with some knowledge of trigonometry. The exact details of what may or may not count as an object is apparently rather finnicky and unintuitive, but it's something that Celestial Wizards are quite used to grappling with, and by carefully selecting what items to search for they've developed methods to divine surprising amounts of information from what seems to be such a simple spell. After a couple of hours of circling Mount Drakenhof and performing her divinations, Goendul points the Dwarves towards a specific point and gives them a slightly downward trajectory, identifying it as the most promising dig site. The criteria she bases this on is something you itch to investigate further but are prevented from by College etiquette, so instead you pursue a secondary curiosity: "so, what leads a Lady Magister to respond to a request for a moderately talented scryer?" "The omens were good," Goendul says simply. "That straightforward, is it?" She looks at you seriously. "The omens are never good in Sylvania. My time here has been about finding the least bad omens and doing everything I can to tip the scales into something that can be called a win. But these scales have already been tipped. That means that this will either be very easy or very interesting." Ah. "I also wanted to see for myself the one that has cast such a long shadow over this land." "You might be disappointed, then. She had more ambition than skill, and I'm not even fully convinced she was a Vampire, let alone a true inheritor of the Von Carstein legacy." She smiles. "I meant you." Ah. "Many locals believe that like the Countess' Chaplain, you never left Sylvania after the Drakenhof campaign, and spent years carving a bloody swathe of vengeance across the land. That you slew the Singing King, liberated Nachthafen, purged Teufelheim, saved the Grand Countess from assassins, and laid curses upon the Lahmians of Mikalsdorf and Waldenhof." You're not sure how to respond to that. You were at least peripherally involved in matters approximate to all of those, but you doubt the rumours were entirely accurate. "It seems to be rather overstated, but I have made a point of visiting from time to time," you say vaguely. She gives you a scrutinizing look, then nods. "Besides that, after so long fighting the blight of Vampirism in this land, I wanted to see for myself the place where it began." You gladly take the opportunity to change the subject. "This is where it sprouted, but it first took root in Vanhaldenschlosse during the Black Death." "Frederick Vanhel, yes? The ancestor of Stirland's current Elector Count?" "Yes. A legacy they've spent the generations since atoning for." "There aren't many families that can trace a lineage back that far, let alone ones in such a dangerous occupation. I suspect there may be a touch of destiny in their bloodline." You continue to talk to her and build a general impression of her as remarkably straightforward for a Celestial, and seems to see the study of omens and portents as a means to an end rather than an end in itself. It is, you suspect, a reflection of her background as a Battle Wizard - both because she has spent so long dedicated to warfare, and because her cloistering has insulated her from the dominant culture of her Order. Presuming all here goes to plan, she seems like she would be a useful person to know in years to come - someone with Hubert's practicality, but still within the Celestial College in more than name. While you do so the Dwarves dig and blast through the rock at a shocking pace with a ringing chorus of steel on stone and the occasional low, reverberating thump of mining explosives. Tunnelling through solid rock in the middle of Sylvania would be a job that most miners would hesitate to take up, but the expeditionary miners of Zhufbar are used to mining shards of gromril buried in accreted layers of warpstone right under the noses of Skaven and Night Goblins. "Thanes?" one of the Ironbreakers emerges and says, and you and Thori come over, trailed by the others. "We're about to break through." The miners funnel out and the Ironbreakers in, and you stand just outside it, removing your hat in case you need to enter in a hurry. There's a muffled thump of a detonation, then a distant ringing of gromril on stone, then an echoing screech that is taken up by countless voices within. "Ghouls," Tarni says. "The cannibal Umgi?" Thori says. "Originally, but twisted by dark magic. They're as tough as an Orc and as fast as a Skaven." "Typically only armed with claws and cudgels, though," you say, trying to peer down the tunnel. "Strange to see them here, though. I'm sure it's full of dead, but nothing fresh enough to eat. Something must be controlling them." Tarni nods. "All the bloodlines make use of ghouls, but only one would bother to maintain a population of them amongst the catacombs of the Von Carsteins." "Strigoi," you agree. "This might bode well. I'd put money on Ironbreakers against any of the foot-soldiers of the Vampires, but ghoul armaments make this an especially foregone conclusion." "Their claws have a habit of finding their way around armour, but as long as they're not too deep, cauterization and a swig of something strong will get you through it." You nod and pat your pockets, double-checking you brought your Candle of Cleansing Radiance. You'd originally commissioned it as a precaution against Skaven poisons, but it would serve just as well against the notoriously potent infections caused by a ghoul's talons. Then you settle in to wait and try to pick up any noise of battle under the screeching of ghouls, and fail to do so. Then the screeches begin to fall back, and as soon as a runner passes on that the Ironbreakers have secured a breachhead you duck into the tunnel, stepping carefully over the carnage, all of it ghoul. "Three exits, two of them dead ends," one of the Ironbreakers says to you as he lights a lantern, and you nod as you look around the newly-illuminated room and frown at what you find. "This looks like a Morrite crypt," Tarni says as she enters behind you, her tone unsure. "We've breached a tomb?" Thori asks, alarmed, as he files in too. "It's not sanctified," Ionel says. "Was it built in mockery of Morr?" You run your eyes over it, and frown as you notice some of the details. No, you carefully don't say. This was built in the style of Sylvania's Cult of Morr, before the Von Carsteins wiped it out. "Benedicta von Carstein," you read aloud from the inscription on the sarcophagus. "I know that name," Tarni says. "She's a cautionary tale among the Umgi Witch Hunters - a Dreamwalker that was turned by the Von Carsteins, and was hunted down by the rest of her sect." You look up from one of the other doorways. "Personal effects," you say. "Clothing, weapons, a comb... if I had to guess, I'd say she built her bedroom in the style of a crypt, though you'd have to ask her whether it was sincere or sacrilege." You focus on the sarcophagus, and note the taint of Dhar lurking within. Dormant, but never totally extinguished. "At least part of her is still in there, though I'm guessing the Dreamwalkers have enough to keep her from being reawoken. I wonder if they'd appreciate being able to complete the set." "For one of their own?" Ionel says. "I'd say so." The other dead end proves to be what looks like a scriptorium in miniature, with a writing table, a chair, and what in most contexts you'd take to be a wardrobe, but here and now you both guess and hope to be an armarium - a type of book cabinet from when books were rarer and more precious, and so each book was given enough space to lie flat. You'd adopted a similar design for your library. "The ghouls broke and ran," Tarni says behind you, "so they weren't directly controlled by the Vampire. Best case scenario, it's out hunting. Worst, it's being awoken by its minions and will be here any minute." "I'd put my lads against any number of ghouls, but a Vampire itself can be a tricky foe. And wouldn't it have worse than ghouls at its disposal?" "Some Strigoi cultivate and command ghoul Vampires, and the bloodline has a knack for commanding terrorgheists and varghulfs," Tarni says. "All of which are too large to fit into these chambers, but if we push much deeper in, it will be able to bring those to bear." "If it has any," you say distractedly, speaking up to be heard in the other room as you work a Shadowchisel into the lock of the armarium. "The smart Vampires are laying low, the stupid but strong ones have already tried to challenge Stirland head-on. This one might be too weak to dominate any feral Vampires and not skilled enough to conjure anything up, and might have nothing worse to throw at us than ghouls and perhaps a few wolves and bats." There's a click and the cabinet swings open, and you smile at five inclined shelves containing two tomes each. "Would this place not be laying low?" Ionel asks mildly. "Would either of you fancy your chances against a Vampire?" Thori asks you and Goendul. "Alone, I'd rather not try," Goendul says. Quite sensible of her, you think to yourself, suppressing a wince as memory conjures a pang in your guts. "But alongside Ironbreakers and two fellow Wizards? I like those odds much more." "Then we'd be willing to push on," Thori says. "If nothing else, I'd like to put a name to the Vampire so we know whose ghouls we've been killing." You've somehow managed to stop yourself from leafing through the volumes there and then, and have instead returned to the impromptu council, and now have to decide whether you'd argue for boldness or discretion. "Do we have time for me to scout?" "If you're quick about it," Thori says. "Now that they know we're here, the clock's ticking. The only way to kill Ironbreakers holding a tunnel is to get behind them, and if we give the enemy enough time to get a force behind us and they've enough brains to do so, this whole expedition will tarnish in a hurry." "And if we have arrived with the master of the house absent, the longer we linger, the longer they have to return," Ionel notes. Raise, hold, or fold, then. Or try to sneak a peek at the opponent's cards and hope you won't burn too much time in doing so. [ ] Raise You've got a good track record against forces holding Castle Drakenhof. Your forces should boldly advance and take on the resident Vampire head-on, which if successful will allow you to secure and loot the entire catacombs. [ ] Hold If you stick to the smaller passages, the only threat to the Ironbreakers would be the Vampire itself. You should have them spread out and explore as much of the catacombs as they can without entering any passage large enough to hold anything truly threatening, with you, Goendul, and Johann ready to respond to any sign of the Vampire. Then they grab everything that's not nailed down, pry up anything that is nailed down, and withdraw in good order. [ ] Fold The Ironbreakers can hold this position while you sneak around collecting as much as one set of hands can, guided to the juiciest opportunities by Goendul's scrying, then withdraw before the enemy has time for an encirclement. Reasonably safe, but the smallest payoff. [ ] Cheat You can scout deeper into the tunnels to see what you can find out about the hostile forces present, so a more informed decision can be made. But this will take time, and sneaking alone into a Vampire's domain has had less than ideal results for you in the past. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Current inhabitants of Mount Drakenhof, and the chamber that Mathilde breached into, were rolled for here.

Mining Mount Drakenhof, Part 3

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Raise Tally "Then let's not give them time to get creative," you say. "Can we follow the ghouls back to their nest?" "A few of them were injured enough to leave a trail of blood," Thori says. "They'll probably end up food for the others once they stop running, but until then they're leaving a trail." "Then let's do so. If they are a Strigoi's court, their nest will be either close to or part of where it sleeps." "A Vampire in front of you is a lot easier to deal with than one lurking in the shadows somewhere," Tarni agrees. "Alright, then," Thori says, and turns to the other Dwarves. "Lads, we're going to chase down those Goruzkulit and wipe them out, and see if anything tries to stop us. Medium speed, no trailers, light runes in the front, and treat the Wizards like an Organ Gun." --- With practiced skill, the Ironbreaker formation moves smoothly and steadily down the tunnel with four manlings and a Dwarven Witch Hunter in the middle doing their best to match their pace. Rather than the solid and static block of troops favoured in above-ground formations, an Ironbreaker formation flows like water, pooling at each junction as some of them stand guard at side passage until the rest of the formation has passed and they can rejoin the end. Tactics honed by generations of encounters with Skaven and Night Goblins leave no purchase for ambush from any side as the formation mercilessly pursues the trail left by the ghouls. [Spot check: Learning, 98+29+10(Windsage)=137.] You've grown reaccustomed to a landscape soaked with Dhar very quickly, but that doesn't mean that you fail to notice when a knot of it starts to move of its own accord, and you spot this particular one when it's still several chambers away. By the time it's starting to move parallel to the Ironbreakers you've identified what its bulk and the spiralling Dhar within it must be. "Zangunvarf, rag bin karin," you say to the Ironbreakers, and then "varghulf approaching from the left," to the humans. As the front of the formation comes to a halt and the keening cries of ghouls and the soft sounds of metal on flesh do their best to draw your attention forward, the shields of the Dwarves on your left light up and illuminate a slavering bulk moving with shocking speed and quietness down a passage barely wide enough for it to fit down. The varghulf is the ultimate fate of a Vampire that surrenders itself entirely to the hunger within it, transformed far from anything that even resembles a human to something more like a bear, only with longer limbs and sharper teeth. [Goendul: 5+20=35.][Johann: 52+18=70.][Mathilde: 37+23=60.] This one ducks under a shard of ice that shatters the stone of the roof above it and ignores the crossbow bolt and pistol shot that disappear into its thick fur, giving a shriek of hunger and anticipation as it closes in. Less easily ignored is the steel ball shot from Johann's staff that strikes it square on the snout, halting its momentum and stunning it for a second before it shakes off the impact and throws itself forward once more. [Ironbreakers vs Varghulf: 46+25=71 vs 23+30=53.] [Goendul: 42+20=62.][Johann: 74+18=92.][Mathilde: 34+23=57.] In an open field the charge of a varghulf might be nigh unstoppable, but squeezing through a tunnel arrests its momentum enough that the Ironbreakers are able to arrest its impact, filling the air with the screeching clang of oversized Vampiric talons clawing at gromril shields. This holds it in place long enough for another frozen shard, another bolt, and another few shots from your revolver to be shrugged off by the beast, but putting them all to shame is Johann levelling his golden arm at the thing, claws outstretched, and unleashing the Hysh stored within in a brilliant beam that banishes the darkness and sears a burning line across the beast's chest through fur and skin and muscle. But the moment the light fades, the injury is already beginning to reknit itself. [Ironbreakers vs Varghulf: 92+25=117 vs 62+30=92.] [Goendul: 100+20=120.][Johann: 1+18=19.][Mathilde: 92+23=115.] Screeching with maddened bloodlust, the varghulf throws itself again at the shieldwall, and then shrieks even more as it fails to do more than force it back a few steps, its jaws snapping over helmeted heads barely an arms length from you. Objectively terrifying, but you've gone to a great deal of effort to quash your automatic reaction to things in favour of channelled violence, so your sword is summoned and starting to swing at it when you realize the other two Wizards have reacted similarly. From your left comes a bolt of crackling lightning, and from your right a golden fist, and both impact in the same instant. Azyrric energy fills the beast to overflowing, frying muscle and burning hair, and seeks an escape from a vessel too small for it. It finds it in Johann. Both varghulf and Gold Wizard slump, one atop three cursing Dwarves and the other into an equally cursing you. With some difficulty you lower him into the ground, at first hurriedly and then with more care as you realize that the varghulf is out of the fight. You're able to find a pulse and he's still breathing, but he seems to be very thoroughly unconscious. "Is he okay?" Goendul asks behind you, her voice worried. "He's breathing. What does that lightning tend to do to people?" "Um. It explodes them, usually. Why did he punch it?" "Religious reasons," you say with a sigh. --- While you had been dealing with the varghulf, the Ironbreakers had been putting the ghouls to flight once more, and this time scattered them thoroughly enough that they're unlikely to regroup unless someone rounds them back up. The varghulf is given over to Ionel to oversee the butchery of and you make your way through the thinning formation to examine the chamber where the ghouls had made their stand, which proves to be a vaulted hall that may have long ago been a ballroom or banquet hall, but is now festooned with gnawed bones and shattered wood, with no piece of detritus intact enough to do more than hint at the piece of furniture it may once have been. In the centre of it, Tarni and Thori are looking up, where among the stalactites is a massive shaft leading up into darkness. Standing under it you can smell the slightest hint of fresh air. "Claw marks and moulted fur," Tarni says to you as you approach. "A terrorgheist nests here - a type of carnivorous bat the size of a Dragon." "I'd guess they don't get on with ghouls and varghulfs under normal circumstances," you say. "They don't get on with anything," Tarni confirms, "so it must be under something's sway. The amount of fur means it's shedding, and that means it's still alive. That suggests that it's less than full grown, otherwise the Vampire would have slain and reanimated it. But it would still be big enough to be trouble on its own, let alone with a Vampire beside or atop it." "A Strigoi atop a live and undergrown terrorgheist," you muse. "One returning home with probably a full belly, and possibly a cargo of meat for its court." "That's about as favourable a circumstance as anyone could hope for against a Strigoi," Tarni says. "All the lads are still fighting fit," Thori says. "What about yours?" "Johann's unconscious, and magical healing might do him more harm than good," you say. Magical healing on a Wizard is usually fine, but a gilded Gold Wizard with a recently-fired Hysh arm that's been zapped with Battle Magic levels of Azyr in the middle of Sylvania is far from usual. "Hopefully he just needs rest. But I'm at full capacity, and Goendul will be too after a rest under the open sky." "Your call, then. We've stamped out everything that's here and we can pick it clean at our leisure. Do we call that a win and head home with everything we can carry, or do we wait however long it takes for the Vampire and his pet to get home?" [ ] Stay and ambush [ ] Loot and leave - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Either option gets Mathilde all the loot there is there is to be found in Drakenhof. Ambushing and defeating the Vampire will only add its skull and anything it might have on its person to the total. - Goendul's rolls were that of a Celestial Wizard fighting far from the open sky, rather than using her raw attributes. - The Varghulf was referred to as 'Fluffy' in the in-thread dicerolls in honour of an early Total War: Warhammer meme, wherein the Varghulf that Mannfred von Carstein begins with was often referred to as such.

Mining Mount Drakenhof, Part 4

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Stay and ambush Tally "If we don't finish this now, when the Vampire is unaware and almost alone, then someone else will have to do so when it has an army at its back," you say, and then Thori bustles off to see to matters of watchkeeping and encampment while you entrust Johann to the care of the miners while pointing Goendul towards the shaft. By the time she emerges, Thori, Tarni, and Ionul were waiting to hear her assessment. "It comes out near the top, hidden behind an outcropping," Goendul says as she lands among you. "Practically invisible unless you know where to look, and partially clogged with rubble from the castle. Judging by the width and the clawmarks inside it, it's too narrow for the terrorgheist to fly all the way through, it has to clamber through the bends. We should have about two minutes of warning between it hitting my Magic Alarm and it reaching this chamber." Thori nods. "The lads will have to stay in their armour, but at least they'll be able to get some food and sleep. What's the plan?" You run through a mental list of possible spells. "I don't believe there's anything either of us has that can make a Vampire more directly susceptible to damage, so our best bet is to do some damage ourselves with the first volley of spells. We'll hit it once it arrives in the room, then the Ironbreakers focus on surrounding it and its steed and bringing them down." "Urannon's, then Curse," Goendul says, nodding. "Not Chain Lightning?" you ask. "If the Vampire is riding the terrorgheist, Urannon's will get them both." "Ah, I see. I've got a bound scaled-up Fireball, and afterwards I'll either engage it in melee or hit them with Melkoth's." "Tarni?" Thori asks. "I've got a set of bolts that contain a number of the common Vampiric weaknesses. If we're really lucky it'll be vulnerable to gromril." "Abbot Ionel?" He smiles and flexes his hand on the haft of his walking stick. "This close to the Drak, I believe I can be of assistance." Thori waits for further elaboration, but when none is forthcoming he moves on. "Very well. When's the most likely time for the Vampire to return?" "My best guess would be around dawn, either shortly before or shortly after," Ionel says. "Either it seeks to avoid sunlight altogether and will be here before the sun rises, or it will conclude whatever grim business it is on with the sunrise and travel here then." Tarni considers this, and nods in agreement. "Right then, I'll have some of the lads doing sweeps around this chambers and the Miners' one outside of that window. Everyone make what prayers and preparations you deem fit." --- "Lady Magister?" a deeply worried voice says, and you open your eyes to see a circle of concerned-looking Ironbreakers around you. "There's, your, erm, I think..." The Ironbreaker trails off and simply points, and you turn your head to see a small fire flickering happily away as it eats at the corner of your bedroll. "Ah," you say, slapping it out as casually as you can. "Yes. That happens from time to time. It's a Zhufokri thing." The Ironbreakers nod in understanding and disperse once more as you frown at the blackened mark on your bedroll. You vaguely recall a crowd of people dressed in outfits of eight different colours being given uniforms and sent off to war, as Prince Vladimir with Regimand's beard cautioned you against doing something so powerful and efficient. Bloody Sylvania. An interminable amount of time staring moodily at the fire later the alarm goes very quietly up in the form of Goendul murmuring to Thori. Thori nods to the nearest Ironbreaker and then it spreads from Dwarf to Dwarf in nudges and nods as helmets are donned and fires are doused. A minute later the room is almost completely dark again as the Ironbreakers form a ring around the part of the room below the shaft, then with a final round of nods from the Dwarves the last lantern is extinguished and the room is as silent and still as it must have been before this Vampire decided to move in. Among this ring of gromril is yourself, Dragonflask in one hand and staff in the other. A scrabbling sound of claws on stone approaches and then grows in volume beyond any reasonable level, and you have to sidestep a small avalanche of rubble as the bulk of the terrorgheist makes its way down the crooked shaft. To your Magesight it is a sinewy beast of Ghur with only a few veins of Dhar running through it, matching Tarni's assessment of it as not yet transformed, but looking at the sheer size of it you find yourself doubting that it could possibly be anything less than fully grown. [Mathilde: 74+23=97.][Goendul: 51+20=71.][Ionel: 91+?=?.][Tarni: 15+?=?.] On the bright side, the sheer bulk of the beast makes it an easy target. The medium of Dwarven whiskey delivers a payload of Aqshy into your mouth and then the world transforms into brightness and heat as the oversized fireball expels itself from your face and tears through the air directly upwards and into the torso of the dangling, oversized bat, and your senses return to a world that is filled with the shrieking of an enormous bat and the stench of burning fur as it falls flailing to the stone. [Ironbreakers vs terrorgheist: 59+25=84 vs 42+10=52.] [Ironbreakers vs Vampire: 86+25=111 vs 87+25=112.] [Mathilde: 14+29=43.] [Goendul:23+20=43.][Ionel: 1+?=?.][Tarni: 45+?=?.] Wisps of Ulgu and strands of Azyr envelop the thrashing terrorgheist in magics to further weaken it as the Ironbreakers descend upon it with axes and hammers swinging, but the density of magical energies this results in blinds you for just long enough to the trajectory of the beast's erstwhile passenger, who has flung itself free of both the impact and the arcane ensorcellations levelled against it. But not, in seems, the divine. Gurgling in outrage as swampwater curdles its bellyful of blood and spills from its fanged maw, it somehow manages to hone in on the source of its discomfort and leaps across the room at Ionel, claws flashing and sending the priest sprawling across the stone before the Ironbreakers nearest it manage to interpose themselves between the two, shields raised high. [Ironbreakers vs Vampire: 76+25=101 vs 23+25=48.] [Mathilde: 54+23=77.] [Tarni:78+25=103.] Leaving the still-thrashing terrorgheist to Goendul, you summon your sword and join the Ironbreakers in pressing the bestial Vampire back. Its claws find no purchase on gromril shields, and prove only slightly able to parry Branulhune, as its attempt to catch your blade does succeed in altering its course enough to save its unnatural life, but costs it most of a hand in doing so. It starts to backpedal, its red eyes darting around the room for an escape, but then it abruptly slumps forward, the back third of a crossbow quarrel protruding from the back of its head. You don't hesitate in stepping forward and taking its head off before it has a chance to recover, and it's only your relative lack of encumberment that allowed you to beat the Ironbreakers to it. You look over to the terrorgheist, which seems to have stilled, and then go over to check on Ionel, who has propped himself up against a wall and is smearing some sort of faintly-glowing mould over the long but shallow cuts across his torso, his brow creased in concentration and an occasional shiver going through him. "Do you need healing?" you ask him. He takes a breath to answer you, wincing as he does so. "No," he gasps out, and then groans out the rest of the breath before he has a chance to elaborate. You can guess what he might have been about to say, though - a scar earned in battle with a Vampire at Castle Drakenhof would bring much-needed prestige to the least-known son of Manhorak, and legitimacy to Ionel as His representative. You nod and leave him to it. "Huh," Tarni says, finally managing to yank free the bolt that had felled the Vampire from its decapitated head and examining its tip. "Ithilmar, of all things." "Is that significant?" you ask. "It's an uncommon weakness, but not unknown. It might help identify it, it's the sort of thing Vampire Hunters keep records about." She turns the head around and frowns at its face. "I'll take a sketch of its face as well. Hopefully that will be enough." You consider the head, and wonder how many outstanding Grudges are still levelled against Vampires who have since been felled and interred in the Empire or Tilea or Bretonnia without their name ever being recorded. Are the Grudges considered inherited by the rest of the bloodline after too much time elapses without the culprit being sighted, or do they forever linger in limbo, an indelible weight on the Dwarven psyche? Questions like these, you suppose, are why Grudgelore is an entire field of scholarship. "Any casualties?" you ask Thori as you reach him. "Bruises all around, but that terrorgheist was dying before it hit the ground. It might not be the sort of thing songs are sung about, but ambushes certainly get the job done. Aught else left but the looting." You nod. "When the Ironbreakers and Miners get to mapping the place, make sure they come find me if they find anything intact. Necromantic traps can be nasty if you walk right into them." --- [Rolling...] The first chamber you are summoned to is a sealed door on the far side of what seems to have been a small armoury, but has been quite thoroughly looted at some point. The door bears the scratch and scorch marks of several failed attempts to breach it, and after eyeing the door for a while and weighing the risk of using Substance of Shadow - any fire within would have long since gone out, but it's far from implausible that there might be a glowing chunk of warpstone on the other side - you instead borrow the expertise of the miners and blast the hinges loose from the stone walls. Within you find exactly what you had been hoping for - the private study of some absent Vampire, papers still scattered across a writing desk, notes left half-written, ink long-evaporated and the quill having molted away to a bare shaft. The notes prove to mostly be in Reikspiel, but leaning heavily on what seems to be Sylvanian and Low Nehekharan jargon, and record the writer's attempts to parse two similar but contradictory prophecies - the Prophecies of Nospheratus, wherein a 'Pale Prince' brings about an 'Age of Blood', and the Vampire Prophecies of the Scrolls of Zandri, wherein a 'Champion of Night' brings about an 'Age of a Thousand Thrones'. This whets your anticipation even further, and sure enough within the scroll brackets you find copies of some of the infamous Scrolls of Zandri, Tilea's equivalent to the Liber Mortis. Plundered from the Nehekharan fleetport of Zandri during the Great Crusades, among the very many writings taken back to Tilea were the transcriptions of the words of the Necrarch progenitor W'soran during the fall of Lahmia that scattered the Vampire bloodlines. Composed of ream after ream of ramblings, rantings, portents, promises of vengeance, terrifying insights, idle thoughts, and musings on the nature of life and death, these scrolls - among very many others - so rattled the Tileans that had stolen them that they invested all of their looted wealth into the founding of the Priory of the Spear, the order of Myrmidian Vampire Hunters. And in the bookshelves, among many varied books on prophecies and their interpretation, you find the counterpart: the Prophecies of Nospheratus, bound in human skin. You'd have to learn Nehekharan to even begin to try to extract anything from the scrolls, but they'd make quite a crown jewel in your library, or a great icebreaker for dealing with the Priory of the Spear. And the books on prophecy have been drawn from quite a wide selection, including some sources that aren't usually the types to share their insights. --- The second discovery is one that would have been very easy to overlook: one mausoleum in a mountain riddled with them. But this one is not built as a simple storehouse for the dead, the necromantic equivalent of an armoury, nor as a morbid resting place for Vampires. This is the final resting place of the last human ruler of Sylvania, Otto von Drak, who married his daughter to a mysterious foreign stranger by the name of Vlad von Carstein. This is the memorial to the legitimization of the rule of the von Carstein bloodline, the cornerstone of the Vampiric claim on Sylvania. To you, this is a curiosity, but to Roswita Van Hal and to whoever she ends up putting in charge of Sylvania - you'd heard a rumour that a minor noble by the name of Nyklaus had actually shown some interest in the task - this could be used to cement the claims of human hands on this corrupted province. Or so you had consoled yourself, until your search of the burial goods uncovers an enormous tome in a chest, the name of which you recognize - The Creeping Flesh. Written by one of the apprentices of Frederick van Hal, this tome is second only to the Book of Gaelen in advancing the knowledge of medicine within the Empire, but it is as suppressed as it is sought after because the knowledge within it was gathered by and for the more physical aspects of necromancy, and the insights it provides for physicians and healers is only incidental. It's easy to understand why this was merely tucked away as one memento among many in the grave goods of a long-dead noble - why would Vlad have any use for his own insights filtered through several generations of mortal fumbling? But the original and complete Creeping Flesh, written in the hand of generation after generation of Von Draks, is quite a collector's item for a nascent library, even if it's the sort of thing one shouldn't brag about too loudly. --- On a hunch, you spent some time carefully scouring the tunnels near the mausoleum, and it didn't take long until you found the section of wall that gave way to a pull on a wall sconce and a hefty shove. Behind it, you find not the sort of thing that you were hoping for, but perhaps the kind of thing the you of twenty years ago might have expected to find behind a hidden door. A realm of delicate silks, soft lightings and cushioned surfaces, the sort of bedroom one might describe as a boudoir. This, you begin to suspect, may have once been the hidden pied-à-terre of Vlad and Isabella von Carstein, a place where they could shut out all distractions and focus on either pet projects or each other as the mood took them. It has also been carefully but thoroughly ransacked, every drawer pulled out, every cushion upended, every bookshelf stripped bare. Wardrobes and dressers hang open, showing a dizzying variety of underthings and delicates, some so delicate as to be sheer. You find one cabinet curiously closed where every other hangs ajar and open it, and after considering the even more esoteric form of bedroom accoutrement stored within, you do as the preceding ransacker must have done and close it once more. You do find something of interest amongst the stripped-bare shelves surrounding a writing desk: a sheaf of papers covered in Nehekharan script that, judging by some of the diagrams, are an investigation into an enchantment placed upon a ring. It is not much of a leap to speculate which ring might have been under investigation: the Carstein Ring, the source of Vlad von Carstein's ability to recover from any wound within a single day, a feat that greatly outstripped any other Vampire. Its disappearance from his hand sealed the end of the First Vampire War, and the one responsible for its disappearance is believed by many to be Mannfred von Carstein, whose magical prowess is said to have outstripped any other of the bloodline, and was second only to his arrogance. So, you speculate, Mannfred returns from the First Vampire War, his progenitor's blood on his hands and his rings on his finger, and goes about looting the quarters of his former master. He takes all of Vlad's books, but in his arrogance leaves Vlad's notes behind. If he has the ring and believes he has outstripped his master, then what use would he have for his master's attempts at understanding the ring? And, it occurs to you, if Vlad was studying the ring, then he cannot be the creator of the ring. There's very few possible candidates for who its creator might have been. Doing another lap of the room with an eye not quite as narrowly focused on the written word, you note that the furnishings of the room and the jewellery left untouched would represent a not insignificant value if sold, especially if they had a frisson of the forbidden about them. You also eye the silk sheets of the bed, which is a luxury that still remains frustratingly out of your reach, though you're not sure if sheets taken from the marriage bed of Vlad and Isabella would be any better than ones taken from a Druchii. --- As the Dwarves confirm that the entire catacombs are mapped and explored, and as Johann regains consciousness and complains to anyone who will listen of tingling in his golden extremities, you force yourself to accept the fact that you're probably not the first to have scoured the tunnels of Castle Drakenhof in the three centuries since the end of the Vampire Wars. Countless numbers of Vampires and Necromancers have probably had the same idea you had and taken the treasures of legend off to parts unknown. You quietly mourn the death of your dream of discovering the entire and untouched library of Mannfred von Carstein, complete with the Liber Necris as its centrepiece, and turn your attention to planning what to do with what you have found. First are the skulls of the Strigoi and the Varghulf, which will be turned over to your care to join your existing collection. Though they might prove interesting research subjects one day, to everyone else present they are merely a burden that they are happy to allow you to take upon yourself. Second are the books on prophecy, which are benign, and the Prophecies of Nospheratus, which is creepy but unknown, and so there's no obstacle to claiming them for yourself. After that, things get trickier. There's the various items of silk and precious metals, which could be sold for a not insignificant sum, and the body of a subadult but very large terrorgheist that has already been butchered into various rare and valued components. Though the Dwarves came here primarily to settle grudges, going home with a profit will put a significant skip in their step. Alternatively, the Council of Manhorak would undoubtedly appreciate a contribution of such liquidatable assets in thanks for their contribution, though your own wallet would likewise benefit from it - though you vaguely recall something about a vow of poverty that might object to that sort of thing. There's also the question of whether you're going to claim those silk sheets for yourself or not, though that's more of a personal matter than a question of diplomacy. [ ] [MONEY] Zhufbar [ ] [MONEY] Council of Manhorak [ ] [MONEY] You [ ] [SHEETS] Yes [ ] [SHEETS] No Then there's the books of Benedicta von Carstein. While there's no question that the corpse is going to be turned over to the Morrites, also turning over the books of her armarium, which contain a great deal of information on Morr, Vampires, and the Undead, would make it a much more meaningful gesture that could get you in the Cult's good books. Or turning it over to someone else to claim that credit could get you in their good books instead. Or, of course, the books could go to your library. [ ] [ARMARIUM] Cult of Morr [ ] [ARMARIUM] Council of Manhorak [ ] [ARMARIUM] Order of Guardians [ ] [ARMARIUM] You The Vampire Prophecies of the Scrolls of Zandri are as touchy a subject as the Liber Mortis, though the fact that they're written in Nehekharan instead of plain Reikspiel means you'd be able to hand them over to some proper authority without drawing too much paranoia. Though they're named for the Prophecies that are the most famous feature of them, they also contain every errant thought that W'Soran gave voice to during the siege of Lahmia, making them a treasure trove of horrifically dangerous insight. The Priory of the Spear, of course, have the originals and would likely be very interested in taking an illicit copy of them out of circulation. The Templars of the Empire would also be interested in expanding their own repertoire of two-steps-removed-from-Nagash forbidden writings to try to draw actionable information out of. Or you could smuggle them out of here and into your own library to keep the Liber Mortis company. [ ] [SCROLLS] Priory of the Spear [ ] [SCROLLS] Templars [ ] [SCROLLS] You The Creeping Flesh is... not quite forbidden, not to a Lady Magister. In the balance of things, its contributions to medicine have probably done more good than its contributions to necromancy have done ill, and for that reason turning it over to the Cult of Verena or the University of Altdorf as a morbid but prestigious centrepiece of a literary collection would be an entirely legitimate way to make friends. The Cult of Morr, on the other hand, very much disapprove of the book because of it being such a product of and contributor to the grim industry of body snatching, and so turning it over to them would be an entirely righteous way to make friends - or a good way for the Council of Manhorak to make friends of them. Or you could claim it for the glory of your own library. [ ] [FLESH] Cult of Verena [ ] [FLESH] University of Altdorf [ ] [FLESH] Cult of Morr [ ] [FLESH] Council of Manhorak [ ] [FLESH] You Then there's the study notes of the Carstein Ring. There's absolutely no laundering this. Notes in the hand of Vlad von Carstein as he studies the necromantic enchantment that may have been created by Nagash himself is the sort of thing that the only legitimate response to is to burn. But it's not like this is the first time you've been faced with this sort of choice, and you do wonder if Vlad's insights into enchantment would be as educational to you as his insights into necromancy were... [ ] [RING] Burn [ ] [RING] Take - There will be a three hour moratorium. - You could claim everything for yourself without annoying anyone, but spreading the joy around a bit is the sort of thing that makes people want to be involved in future adventures. - Mathilde's skills are such that she will have no problem smuggling out the scrolls and notes undetected, if she so chooses.

Turn 39 Results - 2489 - Part 4

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [MONEY] Council of Manhorak [*] [SHEETS] No [*] [ARMARIUM] You [*] [SCROLLS] You [*] [FLESH] You [*] [RING] Take Tally The Council of Manhorak are the ones who are going to be responsible for making any victories against the forces of Necromancy in Sylvania stick, and they're going to need funding to make that happen. And Darmorak in particular will be of particular value to the Dwarves of Zhufbar if they're able to turn Dark Moor into a bastion against the Vampires, as a route from Zhufbar directly into Sylvania would emerge from the mountains in its vicinity. As such there are only a few grumbles when you make the case for the secured valuables to be turned over to Ionel to help fund the establishment of a shrine village at the headwaters of the Templa. The rest of the items are books, and by the ancient and well precedented principle of Inventores Tenentes you claim them for your own library, trumping any possible claims that the various Cults or educational institutions of the Empire might make in the future. Using the more mundane and benign items as a distraction, you're able to smuggle out the more dubious scrolls and notes without anyone being the wiser. This is greatly aided by the fact that in a Dreamwalker tome on Vampires and Undead, Benedicta von Carstein, formerly Benedicta the Radiant, has made a series of corrections, elaborations and observations that both Tarni and Ionel spend some time flicking through and making notes of. Apart from that, while the catacombs do seem to have been picked clean of treasures in the centuries it's been since the Third Vampire War, the Dwarves have found a number of Dwarven corpses amongst the tombs and charnel pits, and have acquired a number of carts from Drakenhof to transport them. Their planned path will take them north along the Drak, where they will send the remains and effects of Benedicta von Carstein downriver to Siegfriedhof and organize passage upriver to Karak Kadrin, where the corpses will be properly entombed and Karak Kadrin's records searched for information on the slain Strigoi, and then they will make their way home to Zhufbar. You hope that the Vampire has at least a few Grudges to its name, as a strike against the Strigoi bloodline in the abstract might be considered by some to have been a poor reason for the journey to have been made. You travel with the Dwarves as far as Drakenhof, from where the rest of the journey will be along patrolled roads, before parting ways with them and heading towards Altdorf. --- Creation of a powerstone, you quickly learn, flies in the face of everything you've ever been taught of how to cast spells, and is entirely made up on the hardest and most tedious part of enchantment. Casting a spell is a matter of understanding the nature of a Wind and what it wants to do, and giving it a way to express itself that is in line with its nature. Crafting a powerstone is nothing like this. A Wind wants to be free to wander in accordance with its nature, and being compressed down into a solid and static object is not in the nature of any of the Winds. No, not even Chamon, it's attracted to dense objects, it doesn't want to be a dense object. Enchantment wrestles Winds into static shapes, but the key is to get it into the desired shape as quickly and efficiently as possible and then embed them into an object that has been crafted to hold it. In contrast to both of these, the creation of a powerstone is about pinning down a single strand of a Wind and then compressing it through sheer force of will over a period of weeks. And that's what makes it truly difficult, that it takes weeks of constant pressure to transform a strand into a stone. This isn't the sort of thing you can dabble in for an hour here and an hour there in your spare time. Any time not spent enforcing your will upon the stone is time where your hard work is undoing itself, and if left unattended for too long the strand will completely and violently unravel. There are ways to mitigate this, meditative techniques that allow something almost like sleep while still enforcing your will upon the nascent stone, spells and environments and apparatus that can somewhat slow the unravelling, identifiable plateaus where the process can be safely suspended to allow the person forming the stone to get some much-needed rest. But there's no way to completely bypass it. The creation of a powerstone requires one person to dedicate almost the entirety of their attention to a monotonous task for a solid month. For a certain kind of person, the creation of powerstones is a cushy and comfortable job, a way to contribute to their Order in a way that is always needed and appreciated and doesn't require leaving the safety and comfort of the College itself. There are quite a few Wizards that steadily pump out powerstones to exchange for the resources and materials they need for their pet projects, or even just to fund a comfortable lifestyle for themselves. For you, however, it sounds like a living hell. If it weren't for the prospect of trying this with completely unknown complications and completely novel results waiting for you on the other side, you'd drop the subject and never look back. The lessons on educating Apprentices is an extreme contrast, as instead of being entirely focused on a single specific act, it needs to touch on all the possible problems that might be encountered. Even a typical Apprentice varies in age from 15 to 25 and is almost as likely to come from one of the cities of Tilea or kingdoms of Estalia as they are the provinces of the Empire, and the less typical Apprentices might have just had their Quickening or could have grandchildren, and might be from Kislev or Bretonnia or Araby. Their preconceived notions of magic can run the gamut from fear to suspicion to complete ignorance to worrying enthusiasm. Magic might have saved them or doomed them, it might have lifted them out of crushing poverty or snatched them from opulent luxury. It is emphasized throughout that the reason that there are Apprentices at all is that there's no one answer that can be applied to all these myriad people. The only way to reliably teach someone to handle magic in a way that makes them an asset instead of a danger to the Empire is for the approach to be tailored from the ground up for them specifically. But while they can't give you the exact course to take, they can point out the most treacherous of shoals and the most beguiling of maelstroms, and give you an idea of what to do should you spot the signs that your Apprentice might be in danger of foundering. There is, of course, the symptoms and effects of Dhar poisoning, where you have to stop yourself from butting in and elaborating further on the topic. There's the dangers of addiction, whether to the rush of channelling magic itself or to the control and power it offers, which proves to be a tricky subject to navigate as it is very easy to argue that an element of at least appreciation for those is required to be a Magister in the first place. There's the myriad effects of miscast, and how to mitigate both the immediate dangers and the social consequences of that sort of thing happening in public view. There are the many kinds of Apparitions, and an acknowledgement of the ongoing debate as to whether they should be swiftly killed or driven off, or left to the Apprentice to face as a lesson. On top of the direct challenges of magical use, there's the many challenges the world will present an Apprentice with. There's the many faces of Tzeentch, who always seeks new ways to tempt the Magisters of the Empire, and the many Cults that He acts through. There's the temptations of Slaanesh and Nurgle, the former of whom tempts those who fly the highest and the latter of whom offers succour to those who struggle the hardest. Then there's the other Cults who will target Magisters in other ways, from the Khornates who seek to kill magic users on general principles, to the Cult of the Broken Wheel who seek to tear asunder the Orders for the crime of 'stealing' magic from Tzeentch, to the Cult of the Yellow Fang who see Wizards as some of the greatest threats to their unstated masters. And while all of those can be opposed with thorough violence, there are other threats from those who should be allies of Wizards for whom a more moderated response is called for. There are the various Witch Hunters, both Cult and secular, and while a Magister has little to fear and a Lord Magister nothing at all from their ilk and can directly extend that protection to ward them off, the lessons emphasize that doing so will leave an Apprentice vulnerable when they become Journeymen. It is important for an Apprentice to develop their ability to present their papers to the proper authorities and insist on proper treatment, because there are plenty of Witch Hunters out there who will browbeat an overly-compliant Journeyman into all kinds of trouble, from manipulating them into inadvertently incriminating themselves to using them as cannon fodder under twisted interpretations of Articles 14 and 15. In the end, it's likely that everything the course tells you are things you could have figured out for yourself, but there is value in seeing all of the common trouble spots laid out for you. --- What do you get the city that has everything? It's a question that's been hovering in the back of your mind of late as you walk the streets of Tor Lithanel, wondering how it can be interwoven with the Empire that surrounds it. It has been self-sufficient for over four thousand years, and anything it could not provide itself it has long since worked around or forgotten it ever wanted. What could such a city want from the outside world? The first answer you stumble across is one of the most obvious: Ithilmar, the sky-silver of Ulthuan, found only in the occasional eruptions from the volcano of Vaul's Anvil in Caledor. Light as silk and hard as steel, it allows the lightest and most delicate of weapons to retain an edge throughout an entire battle, and for the swiftest and most graceful of warriors to be armoured without encumberment. It is often described as priceless, but that is because the ones doing the describing are the sort of adventurers and mercenaries who come away with that impression after finding themselves unable to acquire it at the local blacksmith. Pieces of it do circulate throughout the Empire, either sold through Marienburg, dug up from former Elven settlements, or acquired from unscrupulous traders who barter with the Norscans or the Fire Dwarves for their plunder, and though the price asked for them is always exorbitant, the price that Laurelorn would pay to acquire some more would be greater still, as the amount available to them has only dwindled since they were cut off from Ulthuan. This would require a huge amount of liquid capital to act upon and would likely draw a lot of attention as astronomic offers are made for various items within private collections, but would greatly enrich whoever is first to act upon the opportunity. The artisans of Laurelorn seem to have an open ear for the possibilities of foreign materials, such as leathers and fabrics to the clothiers and new ingredients for the cooks. Just about any kind of raw material that is not available within the forest of Tor Lithanel will find a buyer while the Elves explore the possibilities of the materials of the outside world, but it's impossible to say which, if any, of these will find a long-term market. It's easy to imagine an Eonir baker realizing the potential of milk and eggs and it unlocking a permanent new customer base, or their leatherworkers discovering the durability of cow leather or the softness of sheep and revolutionizing their armours and fashions, but it's as easy to imagine the fad fading within a year or two and the Elves returning to the traditions of millennia once the novelty wears off. There's also the possibility of small volume, high margin, permanent demand luxury goods, such as spices, dyes, and pigments. There's never any possibility of entire cartloads of them flowing back and forth, but there'll always be some that will pay good prices for a bagful every so often. You follow the thread of raw materials and end up having conversations with various forms of smith. You quickly learn that almost all of them employ magic in their furnaces, greatly reducing the demand for fuels. This would be where the conversation ends for most enquirers, but as a Wizard you're able to dig further and find that this introduces a significant amount of Chamon or Aqshy, which often needs to be compensated for in various laborious ways. While none of the smiths seem likely to share the details of those processes, all of them do admit that if fuel was cheaper, then there are many times when they would use it instead of magic. You also speak to them of prices of raw metals, and find that Laurelorn fossickers are able to supply nuggets that are as remarkably pure as they are scarce. They'd likely turn up their nose at any products of the Empire's smelters. Ingots produced by the Dwarves might serve their purposes, but ideally there'd be something the Empire produces that could fulfil the same need. You dig further, carefully asking questions that display curiosity of the subject matter itself without actually asking for anything that might be considered a trade secret, and you learn that while most metals come from Laurelorn trees that draw trace metals from the soil and extrude them in nodules along their trunks, the Faniour do occasionally uncover surface veins of metal-bearing rock, and the city retains the knowledge of how to process these. If the Empire was able to supply suitable ores and flux, then the city would be willing to pay a decent price for them. This sounds good at first, but after crunching the numbers and looking over maps you find a considerable logistical issue. The Middle Mountains are infamously barren of minerals, and the only ones to be found under the soil of Nordland are the ones that Nordland was extracting from under Laurelorn. The nearest exploitable resources are some very minor tin and lead mines in Ostland and some iron panning in southern Middenland. The distances involve make transporting raw ore by cart entirely uneconomical, and there are no routes for Empire-mined minerals that don't pass through Marienburg, which you're rather hesitant about, and so too would the Eonir. They might be willing to build very careful links with the Empire, but they don't want those links going through a catspaw of Ulthuan. So, you summarize to yourself, there is a high (and highly-visible) short-term profit to be made in the trade in Ithilmar, some profit to be made in raw materials with unknown long-term prospects, and long-term opportunities in supplying small amounts of spices and dyes. There's a significant opportunity in the possibility of smelting in Tor Lithanel, but it will require significant investment and the supply needs to be able to get to the Sea of Claws by boat without passing through Marienburg. But there's one good that the Empire is able to supply easily and in bulk, and that Tor Lithanel has an untapped demand for: charcoal. --- With the first half of the book on Windsoak mushrooms already written, the remaining task before you is the instructions on how to take a fully-grown and soaked mushroom and turn it into something portable and palatable. Your experiences with food are mostly confined to the eating thereof, and so it would be difficult to describe the writing of a cookbook as something within your areas of expertise. Nevertheless, you square your shoulders, consult your notes, and do your best to plow forward. [Writing the book on Windsoak Mushrooms, Learning: 6+29+7(Library: Sevir)+5(Library: Chemistry)=46.] [Panoramia interrupt?: 20.] It proves to be something of a nightmare, one that brings to mind your struggles years ago with your very first paper. For lack of familiarity with cookbooks you'd decided to use your books on chemistry as a model for how to describe the cooking process, and while it produces a set of instructions that could technically be followed to produce something that is technically edible, it's very far from your finest work. Panoramia absconds away with your draft while you grumble and pout and are consoled by Wolf, but returns after having consulted a few knowledgeable Halflings who all agree that this isn't the sort of thing that can be salvaged with a few notes and tweaks, it will take a full revision. Your immediate instinct is to do so, but there's always more work to be done and papers to be written, and more time spent on this might not be the best investment of your very finite time, and of the very many things you have written and will write, this is never going to be anywhere near the most prominent. Perhaps you should simply publish and let whoever reads it work out the details for themselves - all the information they'd need is in there somewhere. Current estimated rating: [Thaumomycology, 2489. Subject: Rare, +1. Insight: Revolutionary, +2. Delivery: Impenetrable, -2. Thorough, +1. Varied, +1. Exotic, +1. Useful, +1. Shared Credit, -1. Total: 4.] [ ] Publish [ ] Revise Thus concludes the work Mathilde performed these past months, but not every waking moment was filled with work. With whom did she spend her free time? The five with the most votes will be chosen, not counting those locked in. [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) Laurelorn [ ] Max The entire time you've known Maximilian, he has been pursuing his own goal of true transmutation via magically-enhanced blacksmithing. Check in to see how he's going with that. [ ] Thorek See what inroads Thorek has made with the Major Houses of Tor Lithanel. [ ] Magister Tochter Grunfeld Get to know Tochter Grunfeld, ritualist, traditionalist, and veteran of the Sylvanian Campaign. Karak Eight Peaks [ ] Gretel She's apparently getting involved in the Karaz Ankor's ambitions in the Border Princes. [ ] Okri You've met Loremaster Okri of Karak Eight Peaks once before. Pay him a visit and see how his great ambitions for heavily-armed Ironbreakers delivered by Gyrocarriage are going. Foreign Relations [ ] Sylvania Meet this would-be Markgraf Nyklaus for yourself. [ ] Wissenland Rumours of some sort of earthquake having struck Nuln are circulating. [ ] Middenland See how the Ulricans are going with their new Eonir coreligionists. [ ] Karak Vlag There's rumours of an unknown Slayer carving a particularly bloody swathe through the beasts and marauders of northern Kislev. The only Dwarfhold anywhere near there is Karak Vlag. See what's happened to cause one of theirs to take the Slayer Oath. [ ] Karaz-a-Karak To investigate their preparations for the Mount Silverspear campaign. [ ] The Black Water Canal Pay another visit to the canal project, and see if there's any further signs of sabotage. Friends Abroad [ ] Kasmir See how his partnership with the Council of Manhorak has been going. [ ] Eike Hold some sort of celebration for her upcoming graduation out of Junior Apprentice. Following Up [ ] Brief the Emperor Though the Waystone Project is in early days, you've achieved promising progress in getting so many disparate traditions to work together. [ ] Amber College Check in on the salamanders. [ ] Gold College See what's become of their research into Skaven technology. [ ] Skull River Ambush Look into the investigation of the mining of the Skull River, and any consequences of it. - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Final book-mining tally: +6 Prophecy, +3 Undead, +3 Vampire, +2 Morr, two new notable tomes, two new objects of study, empowered and legitimized the Council of Manhorak. - Revising the Windsoak mushroom book, if voted for, will be added back to the list of potential papers at [2/3] and can be done as a future writing action.

Turn 39 Social - 2489 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Revise [*] Eike [*] Karak Vlag [*] Magister Tochter Grunfeld [*] Kasmir [*] Karaz-a-Karak Tally Pursuing your curiosity, you find Magister Tochter Grunfeld in the room that has been turned over to the Talastein Carvings, where she's trying to tease meaning out of the more damaged and faded fragments with a set of Elf-made optical lenses and the Ghyran variant of the Multidimensional Aethyric Polysevirric Projection, tracing runes in softly-glowing green light and waving them away as they fail to fit either the remaining fragments or the surrounding context. You can tell she's noticed your approach, and you wait for her to reach a point in her study where her attention can be split. "Do you know what the month of Sigmarzeit was called while Sigmar still walked the world?" she says to you, after some time. You consider that. "Battle-tide?" She looks over at you. "Interesting. Why do you say that?" "Most of the months are close translations of the Dwarven ones, with Ulric-tide replacing white-tide. Sigmarzeit's equivalent is Kazakzet, battle-tide, and the tribes of Sigmar's time would have agreed with that, since late Spring is after the planting and calving and lambing. Why, what were you expecting?" "Taal-tide is the common answer, and the most popular theory. But I've always doubted that. In the old understandings, Taal is the God of Summer, He would not have had a Spring month named after Him." "So, Rhya-tide?" "No, if they were going to name a month after Rhya, it would have been Pflugzeit." You nod as you consider that, then something occurs to you. "If Rhya is Spring, Taal is Summer, and Ulric is Winter, who's Autumn?" "Good question. The triskele is one of the symbols of the Jade Order, and it's theorized to be from when Rhya, Taal, and Ulric were a seasonal triad. There's no reason to assume they had four seasons just because we had. Paranoth says that Nehekhara has three seasons, Ind has six, the Southlands only two. Maybe wherever the Belthani came from, there were only three distinct seasons." "That might rule out the Ulthuan theory, then. They have Frost, Rain, Sun, and Storm. The Wards were named for them." You frown as you think. "I wonder how many seasons the Norscans have?" "Hmm. I'll have to look into that. The timeline doesn't line up right for the Belthani to have been pushed out by the Norsii, but there might have been some interstitial people that have been lost to history." "Is that why you're studying the carvings further? To learn more about their origins?" "To learn more about anything about them. Being able to gather and record and share all this information is a privilege denied to the pre-Teclisean Druids and one that the Order of Life has not been taking advantage of. The history of the Earth Mother was prey to the Cults of Taal and Rhya, but the history of the precursors to the Order of Life can be gathered and written and distributed with at most a few grumbles from them. But the problem is that much of that history is as old as that of Sigmartide's previous name. That's why I brought it up, that happened right at the heart of the newly-formed Empire and involved something literally everyone would have known back then, and still it's been lost." She sighs and looks down the row of steles. "That's why I see it as my duty to wring every scrap of information out of these, because it could be that parts of what's written here no longer exists anywhere else in the world." "Would you still feel that way if the fears regarding the questionable steles were justified?" "I would," she says, unhesitatingly. "We have processes for getting usable information from tainted sources. That's what prevented a Von Carstein Emperor." You nod in understanding, and leave her to her examinations to go over your impressions of the Jade Magister. Considering they're of the same Order and a similar age, it's difficult to completely avoid comparing Tochter to Panoramia. There's even enough similarities in their features for you to be fairly confident that Tochter comes from the Druid bloodlines, just as Panoramia does, and that the two would work out to be some variety of cousins if you studied the family trees. But when comparing their natures the gulf widens considerably. Where Panoramia has the relaxed strength of a deep-rooted oak, Tochter's strength is that of forged steel. Her muscles aren't from tilling the soil, but from battle and drills; her grasp of Ghyran is focused on control and efficiency that speaks of battle in unfavourable circumstances, rather than a loose but practiced grasp over vast torrents. She seems to have a deep and genuine faith in her conception of the Earth Mother. She's reserved but not standoffish, she speaks most of her mind, and she's quite good at finding ways to line up her pet projects with her duties to the Orders and the Empire. It wasn't until you'd shared this impression with Panoramia that she pointed out what you should have spotted immediately: that though you've been comparing her to Panoramia, Tochter is actually a lot like you. You're not sure whether to take this as reassurance or as a reason for further caution. --- It is, it seems, a time of some upheaval in the Karaz Ankor, as Watchtower-Clans that have called the Grey Mountains home for millennia have been offered the opportunity to fight for the homes of their distant ancestors once more, and have to decide whether they will answer the call to arms or finally accept that the Grey Mountains have become their home. Though Karaz-a-Karak's diplomats swarm the Grey Mountains to try to nudge those Clans on the fence into moving, what would normally be their counterbalance from Karak Norn remain silent. This is likely due to the fact that every Dwarf that travels to Karaz-a-Karak is answered by an equal weight in gold and siege weapons flowing to the Grey Mountains, ostensibly to bolster the defences that the loss of such stalwart Dwarves would have weakened. You've observed yourself that the wealth of the Old Holds is perhaps eclipsed by the growing and hopeful population of the Young Holds, and it seems that the High King has seen the same and is balancing the scales in the most direct way possible. That part is known to anyone that pays attention to news and current affairs in the Old World, as entire Dwarven Clans travelling from one end to another is difficult to miss. But the other part of the realm-wide build-up is one that only comes to your attention as you travel from Karak Eight Peaks to Karaz-a-Karak with Sky-Thane Gotri, who also has business there and is always happy to share his own skewed perspective of events within the Engineers Guild. From what you gather, the way the Pilots Guild normally works is by the same Apprenticeship system that almost all Dwarven enterprises are built on, except with graduation to Master being reliant upon an available Gyrocopter to call their own. While this does ensure that every pilot is highly skilled and intimately familiar with the workings and quirks of his vehicle, it is also a system that does not adapt well to a sudden surge in demand for skilled pilots. And demand there certainly is, because while an actual assault on Mount Silverspear is still many years away, the second Silver Road War has begun, as almost overnight the greenskins have found that any of their number moving along the Silver Road during the day are met by the bombs and clatterguns of the Karaz-a-Karak Aircorps. So Karaz-a-Karak has sent word out to every corner of the Karaz Ankor that every Apprentice and Journeyman Pilot that joins the second Silver Road War will have a Gyrocopter built for them that they can return to their home with upon its conclusion. For Dwarves that would normally have to wait for the death or retirement of their Master to inherit a Gyrocopter of their own, and for ones whose only path to being a full Pilot was cut off by the destruction of the vehicle they hoped to inherit, it is an irresistible lure. Even the Piloting Clans don't complain, as for every Apprentice or Journeyman Pilot that leaves there's many young Dwarves who yearn to fly but would normally be forced into some other occupation due to the hard limit on possible Masters, and now they have a chance to fulfil those dreams and increase the wealth and prestige of their Clan and Hold. It is, you reflect, a gratifyingly win-win arrangement. The reputation and authority of Karaz-a-Karak could be used to bludgeon through any objections and drain the strength of the other Dwarfholds, but instead they are emptying vaults that have been filled to bursting with ancient treasure for millennia to ensure that the rest of the Karaz Ankor will be stronger for the second Silver Road War, even if Mount Silverspear is not successfully retaken. Even Gotri, normally so suspicious of the actions and motives of Karaz-a-Karak, can only find one thing to grumble about: that it's driving up the price of certain metals used for Gyrocopter parts. And that complaining, which normally would be foremost in Gotri's priorities, takes a backseat to an even better topic: pontificating on hangar design. Karaz-a-Karak, he begins to explain the second you show any interest at all in the topic, has built its hangars on the assumption that they will be infrequently forming up great flocks of Gyrocopters to see to some distant threat, and as such they have run into all sorts of problems in adapting to having to send out small amounts of Gyrocopters almost constantly, and as such they're calling on expertise from all over the Karaz Ankor to explore solutions to this. Gotri had overseen the construction of Karak Eight Peaks' hangars in a 'honeycomb' design, wherein each Gyrocopter has its own hangar that can open to the outside world, but he explains to you that this was made possible by him being able to treat the interior side of Karag Lhune as 'safe', as they could only come under fire from enemy siege weapons if they were set up in the Eastern Valley. Karaz-a-Karak, being a single mountain that towers above any to be found around it, can only count on sheltered entrances where minor peaks of its own flanks shield it, and those tend to come with unpredictable and dangerous cross-winds that would make them unfavourable launching points. After the rest of the ride passes with Gotri speculating on the other possible solutions and pointing out problems, real or imagined, in their application, you part ways with him and see to the more grounded portion of the nascent war. A small town of 'temporary' structures - which in Dwarven terms means they can be relied upon to last only one or two centuries without maintenance - have sprung up outside the famous main gates, where mercenaries have flocked to rumours of Dwarven gold and those that seek to relieve them of that gold in exchange for food, drink, or company have followed. Though the retaking of Mount Silverspear itself seems to be planned as an entirely Dwarven undertaking, the wider front of the second Silver Road War is accepting all comers. Your outfit means that your personal space is respected in even this most disreputable of crowds, as though it says 'Grey Lord Magister' to those who are familiar with the ways of the Colleges of Magic, to an untrained eye the garb of a Wizard with the hat of a Witch Hunter is the sort of outfit that highlights its wearer as someone to be treated with caution. To the Dwarves overseeing the courtyard, that you entered from within Karaz-a-Karak means you can only be one person, and the Thane in charge is quickly informed and bustles over to see what has made you their problem. To someone with that responsibility, it's a great relief to find that no more than curiosity brings you, and satisfying that curiosity is a small price to pay in exchange for you leaving sooner. "The Bloody Spear tribe," the Thane explains to you, "is one of the most widespread and numerous of greenskin tribes in the entire Old World. They're nominally a Night Goblin tribe, but their territory encompasses Mount Gunbad, Mount Silverspear, and most of the Silver Road and Mad Dog Pass, so they're wealthy and prestigious enough to be something of a constant, low-grade Waaagh, bringing all manner of other greenskins to their banner. Having Umgi and Ogri poke at them will increase the draw of the Waaagh and cause more to flock to their banner, but if it happens now, then we can note how many and what they consist of and plan around them. If that happened as we marched on Mount Silverspear, then we would not." "Ogri?" you ask. "Aye. We've been hearing of some king of theirs uniting a big chunk of the eastern mountains under their banner for some time, and had to fight off a number of tribes pushed out by them. But it seems that some form of stability has been achieved, as the traders that came through their report that those roads through the eastern mountains are as safe as they've ever known them, save for having to pay a tribute to their king. The last two Ogri tribes to come out of those lands had some of that same civility beaten into them, being willing to work for gold instead of dying for it, and they'll happily pay a mountain of greenskin heads for weapons built for their size. And the heads they deliver are picked clean of flesh, which makes it a much cleaner interaction all around than those the Umgi deliver." He shows you a map of the mountains, where the territory of the Bloody Spear tribe is split neatly in two by the Silver Road, and you note that some of the westernmost Watchtowers of the Silver Road and Mad Dog Pass - which by modern standards are more like small, heavily fortified Dwarfholds in their own right than mere guard posts - have been retaken, and you consider the lay of the land as a Gyrocopter buzzes over you, as they have been doing every few minutes. Silver Road, once the highway and hunting grounds of the Bloody Spears, is now a deathtrap for them. "Are you hoping they'll try to contest the road?" "They're not likely to, as their leaders are Night Goblins, as are most of the greenskins within Gunbad and Silverspear. They'll cede the surface and plot by day and raid by night. But that'll cause a rift between them and the Urks and other Grobi, especially the ones living south of the Silver Road. In time they'll be forced to either send forces across the Silver Road anyway to crack down on dissenters or start losing territory and respect. Best case scenario, they either have a full-blown civil war or they have some rebel Warboss draw away their biggest and boldest to go Waaagh somewhere else. But even if they don't, we'll have cut off communication enough between north and south that they'll be unable to coordinate a response when we march east, and the southern half might stay out altogether." "Any idea when the marching will begin?" "Depends on the Watchtower-Clans. We want to use the watchtowers as staging and supply points, but the High King refuses to march forces into a tower unless the Clan that has claim to it is leading it, or has given up all claim on it. So there's a limit on how far east we can go until all the Grey Dwarves commit one way or the other." And the airborne front, you think as you thank the Thane for his time, is making preparations that won't pay dividends for years to come. This is a campaign on Dwarven terms, and that means reliable, iterative progress with each foothold properly secured and fortified before moving on to the next, with a constant, patient toll being bled off the enemy at every step. Greenskins don't have the patience to wait out that sort of campaign, they'll either decide to stop mucking about and throw themselves into the teeth of Dwarven defences or they'll seek out a proper scrap elsewhere. It's also a campaign that might have taken a note or two from the Karak Eight Peaks campaign, as it shows an awareness and willingness to take advantage of fracture points in the enemy ranks instead of treating them all as a unified force. It's not quite what Dwarves would call Ranger tactics, but it is a step closer to it than you'd normally expect from the heart of traditional Dwarven orthodoxy. You jot down a few mental notes in preparation for sharing your impressions with Belegar, who's shown a quiet but intense interest in the goings-on at Karaz-a-Karak recently, and begin to make your way back to the airport. --- At any given time there are dozens, perhaps hundreds, of Slayers seeking their doom in odd corners of the Old World, so for one to be notable enough for word to reach you from northern Kislev is something you find notable enough to investigate, especially since the only extant Dwarfhold nearby is Karak Vlag. Is some dissension in the returned hold causing some to dye their hair and seek death? Or did one of the bewitched Dwarves who served Slaanesh in a horrific parody of Slayerdom survive the battle with the Karag Dum Expedition, and is now wandering Troll Country and turning their dark blessings upon any being they encounter? Karak Vlag has reclaimed all but the uppermost level of the Hold, which it maintains as both a meeting place with outsiders and a way to draw any would-be invaders into the darkness they have become accustomed to. There they welcome you with a level of wary suspicion that would be deeply hostile by any other Dwarfhold's standards, but for them is mild enough that you feel touched by their trust in you, and tell you that between the perversion of that custom by Slaanesh and how readily available doom had been until very recently, the Slayer rites had fallen almost completely into disuse, and has not been performed at all since their return, so the Slayer could not have come from their ranks. What they don't say is that they have no knowledge at all of the Slayer in question, and it's the loud and uncomfortable silence Dwarves adopt when they're being polite about someone else's shame. You might be able to extract more information from them, but not easily, and the Slayer in question seems to be leaving such a trail behind them that they shouldn't be hard to find. From Praag you make your way into the Northern Oblast, a cold and sparsely-populated landscape exposed to Troll Country and Norsca. Its population is mostly Ungol and mostly nomadic, and information on the movements of Trolls and Norscans flows as swiftly and reliably as juicy gossip through an Altdorf ballroom, so even with your limited grasp of Gospodarinyi you find no difficulty in following the violent trail carved through wandering beasts and raiding parties. After a few days of pursuing tales that grow fresher and less exaggerated by the hour, you finally find your quarry on the banks of the Tobol, the path having steered south after penetrating deep into Troll Country. "Hello Borek," you greet the orange-haired Dwarf, sitting by a bubbling pot over a fire on the riverbank. Not Thane Borek, not Borek Forkbeard. Just Borek, now. When you spotted him he'd already seen you, and he'd relaxed somewhat as you approached and he got a good look at you. Beside him is a massive and ornate rune-axe, and his hand never strays from its handle. "Did you tell them?" he asks you, his voice quiet. You've seen a fair few Slayers in your time, and all of them looked... well, like Slayers. Borek looks like Borek with his hair dyed orange. It even still hangs downward, instead of being shaped into the mohawk that most who walk that path wear. Even his mood seems different, being more of a resigned sadness than the bleak despair you're used to seeing from that kind. "I did," you say, remembering his last request to you. Tell them we did the best we could. "Thank you," he says, his expression flickering in the general direction of a smile without actually reaching it. "I didn't expect to lay eyes on you again," you say. "Has Karag Dum fallen?" He barks a laugh. "That's a complicated question." "I hardly ever wrestle with ones that aren't, these days." He looks at you, a flash of anger going across his face, but then it fades and he nods. "I suppose not. An Umgi wielding Elgi teachings in service of the Dawi, you could hardly be split more ways, could you?" He looks at the fire, and sighs. "When I left it, Karag Dum was as I had found it. I couldn't find it in myself to help or to hinder, so I left." He pauses. "Did the Expedition get home alright?" "We lost another of the steam-wagons to rough terrain, but the rest of it got back fine. The Rangers are watching over Karak Vlag, and the Engineers would likely be contributing to either the canal project or preparing for the retaking of Mount Silverspear." You watch him carefully. "You know, I almost decided to try following you into Karag Dum, just to get some answers." 'Almost' might be a slight exaggeration, but you were certainly tempted. "It's good you didn't," Borek says simply. You meet his terseness with silence. He might be wearing a shroud of grim silence, but underneath that is the diplomat, someone who believes in talking. Eventually, he continues. "He almost certainly would have slain you. Maybe not if you were from Tilea or Araby, but..." He looks at you, takes in your expectant expression, and sighs. "You're not going to leave me be until I give you answers, are you?" "I blazed a trail through mountains and wastelands, through Daemons and Fire Dwarves and Skaven and Kurgan, to get at those answers, then you took them and left. The Karaz Ankor might be content to leave it at 'Karag Dum has fallen', but I'm not." "And who is it that seeks those answers? Belegar's Loremaster?" "I left that role years back, I'm currently pursuing a research project in Nordland. The one that wants the answers is just me." "And they'll go no further?" "You have my word." To Dwarves, that's ironclad. To you, it means that if you feel the information needs to be shared, the consideration that needs to be made is the amount of damage one Slayer from a fallen Dwarfhold can do to your good name. But he doesn't know that, nor does he need to. Besides, he wants to talk. You can see it whirling inside of his guts, sitting as unsoundly as a halfpenny pie. "And I'll have a task from you in exchange, in service of my new career." You consider that, and weigh the calibre of foe that a diplomat with a found axe might be seeking assistance with. "Very well." He nods, and turns back to the fire. "We call the Ancestor Gods the Ancestor Gods, because we once had gods who were not our Ancestors," he says in an oddly detached tone as he stares at the fire. "Long ago, far to the south, the old gods were our teachers and our wardens. But their numbers dwindled over time, and when the time was right we escaped, thanks to Grungni and Valaya and Grimnir. But some of those that followed did so not because they desired freedom or venerated our three leaders, but because they mourned their teachers who one day had stopped visiting, and remembered their Names, and knew that such things never truly die and must linger on somewhere. Karag Dum was founded by those who most mistrusted the old gods, and claimed a home with its back to the Chaos Wastes, as Chaos was the only force that could rival the old gods. We watched with suspicion as the Dawi turned their backs on a mountain range that could be mined for a thousand thousand years to spread to all corners of the Old World. Why Ekrund, pinned between the Badlands and the sea? Why Norsca, the shattered remnants of another prison? Why the Middle Mountains, desolate and cursed? Why risk everything to travel across the Dark Lands and the Great Ocean, often never to be heard from again? "The southern Holds called us paranoid, even as history gave the horrible answers to our other two suspicions: Why Uzkulak? Why Tylos? "One of the names we remembered was reshaped into Khsar, blowing across the deserts we had once fled across, feeding on the faith of the desert tribes of the Umgi as they built themselves into a great civilization. Then Elgi sorcery in Umgi hands carved corpses from the desert gods to be receptacles for the prayers of the dead, and the name sought refuge across the seas as Kavzar. But there it was betrayed, a betrayal that birthed a race of betrayers, and what was left of it after being thrice ripped from its domains was as close to death as such things can ever be. In pain and madness it found a fourth family in beings as broken as it was, and walked the world as Morghur, a meaningless bleat from the throat of a beast. "But even after it had forgotten, we remembered its true name. As Chaos crept closer and threatened us with extinction, the founding truth of Karag Dum was reversed. The old gods are the only force that could rival Chaos, so Karag Dum called the least terrible of those known to it. Karag Dum called the being that was Shadowgave, that was city-father, and that was the desert wind, because the first thing it was, was the teacher and warden of the Dawi. So once more it teaches and it wards, and the skulls of Kurgan and the essence of Daemons sink into the sands that it rules. "Chaos has swallowed Karag Dum, but every step down its gullet will extract a price in blood." He sighs, and glances at the axe he has still not relinquished his hold on. "I couldn't find it in myself to judge whether that was a grim victory to support, or a betrayal to condemn. Nor could I go down the path of the few Elders that still linger in Karag Dum, doing nothing but watching with hollow eyes and still tongues as their grandchildren go about their lives never knowing that their very souls have been reforged into weapons of spite against the Chaos Gods. "So I left. On a final task from my fallen hold I followed the path of Prince Morekai, who had tried to follow my path to the Old World, and instead of dying in the attempt I managed to find his skeleton in a cave surrounded by that of Beastmen. I took up his axe," he pats the weapon beside him, "and bundled up his remains to carry with me, so he may be put to rest in the proper manner in the Karaz Ankor. Karak Vlag has taken his corpse and an oath to see it safely to Karaz-a-Karak, and then I set out to seek my doom." He frowns. "So far I have found it to be rather elusive. Perhaps the reputation of Troll Country is overstated." The silence stretches between you as you try to digest what he has told you. "Now," he says abruptly, "I'll have your assistance, that which you've already pledged to give, in crafting the hairstyle that is the uniform of my new profession." You look at the bubbling pot of what you now know to be troll fat, and almost regret your impetuous curiosity. Once Mathilde has completed her messy and fragrant task, will she remind Borek of the financial debt she still owes him from the Expedition? [ ] Yes [ ] No --- As you make your way back towards the Empire (while taking every opportunity to wash your hands without any noticeable lessening of the stench of boiled troll fat that clings to them) you turn your mind towards the matter of your new Apprentice, who will be entering your care upon your return to Altdorf. Such matters are typically marked with some sort of ceremony, but these are left up to the whims and quirks of the Master who takes them on, and are an opportunity to make an impression in your new mentee about their position in the world or what their priorities should be. What manner of induction will you give Eike? [ ] Wizard Modify the induction oaths of the Grey Order into something fitting her promotion, to emphasize her progress within the Grey Order. [ ] Stirlandian Induct her in the same way that any quickened child of the Empire would be taken on as an Apprentice, emphasizing her status as a citizen of the Empire. [ ] Dwarven Induct her in the same way that a Dwarf would be taken on as an Apprentice, building her ties to and familiarity of the Karaz Ankor. [ ] Religious Induct her as your Apprentice within your shrine to Ranald and Shallya, acknowledging her faith. [ ] Secrets Read her in to a number of minor but exciting secrets to emphasize her duties as a knower and uncoverer of secrets. [ ] Swordswoman Present her with a training blade to emphasize her duties as a warrior. [ ] Blood (Greenskins) Take her out to give her her first taste of combat in a controlled environment, against the greenskins of the Badlands. [ ] Blood (Sylvania) Take her out to give her her first taste of combat in a controlled environment, against the ambient undead of Sylvania. [ ] Other (write in) Specify what impression you want to imbue, or what culture you want to give Eike a new tie to. - There will be a six hour moratorium. - If one of the Blood options is chosen, Mathilde is sufficiently skilled that she will be able to protect Eike against whatever is encountered, if it proves necessary. - Congratulations to @Garlak (here, here) and @Chronic (here) for getting eerily close to the truth of the matter of Morghur and Karag Dum.

Turn 39 Social - 2489 - Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Yes [*] Secrets Tally You know Eike has been considered an adult by society since she turned ten, but despite that she still seemed like a child to you, firmly placing her in the category of 'not your problem'. But now, with Ulgu pooling within her instead of flowing freely through her, she looks more like the adult she actually is and you're doing your best to adjust your thinking accordingly. That, and she's... what, almost fifteen now? She's already as tall as you and seems like she's nowhere near done growing, and has long dark brown hair in a ponytail and a prettiness that hints at the beauty her mother once possessed and she seems destined to inherit. She's also put on some muscle, suggesting that she took more advantage of the available combat lessons than you did at her age. She's currently standing beside a bag packed with her things in the entrance hall, as she's been instructed to. She wouldn't have been told why, simply given her instructions and left to either unquestioningly obey or investigate for themselves. The Grey Order is filled with these little tests, used to determine the nature of the Apprentices before they're trusted with any of the deeper secrets of Ulgu - and sometimes just to keep the Apprentices on their toes. "I hear you've finished your Junior Apprenticeship," you say to her as your Invisibility dissipates. To her credit, it only takes her a moment to answer you. Either she already suspected or she's developing a good sense of composure. "Yes, Lady Magister Weber," she says to you, a little louder than she likely intended. "That's a bit of a mouthful," you say with exaggerated casualness. "'Master' will do. Follow me." It's the same induction into the next chapter of her life that you once received, and as you turn and start walking she falls into place just as you once did. "Karak Eight Peaks will be our base of operations, and we'll be working in Tor Lithanel frequently as well, so there'll be a fair bit of going back and forth. I find it to be a good opportunity to catch up on reading, though it may take you some time to get used to the motion and noise." You lead her out a side door and into a disused courtyard, where the Gyrocarriage is waiting, and you give her a moment to get used to the sunlight she hasn't been directly exposed to in three years. "This is my pilot, Journeywoman Adela Burgstaller of the Bright Order. Adela, this is Apprentice Eike Hochschild." "Hi!" Adela chirps, in the slightly alarming half-yell she uses when she's wearing her piloting helmet. "Hello!" Eike responds in the same volume Adela had used. Either she's quick on her feet or she reflexively echoes the mannerisms of whoever she's talking to. "Eight Peaks, Adela," you say, and she nods and begins the series of odd rituals required to awaken the Gyrocarriage as you open the door to the passenger compartment and wave Eike inside. She only hesitates for a moment before clambering in, luggage first, and you follow after her. While your Gyrocarriage is a fair bit more comfortable than the previous one you used, where the passenger compartment was originally a bomb rack, there's still no getting around the fact that the noise of the engine makes conversation impossible. It's a little unkind to spring this all on her and then leave the very many questions she must have trapped inside her, but unanswered questions are good for the soul of a Grey Wizard, and whichever ones make their way to the forefront after she's had a good, long time to think on it will tell you more about her. You turn to your current reading - two competing translations of The Doom of Kavzar - and you conceal a smile as Eike frowns at the rising noise of the starting engine and digs around in her luggage, eventually producing what you eventually manage to make out as My Years as a Bounty Hunter in Reikwald, Bretonnia and the Grey Mountains. You vaguely recall that it was written in the aftermath of the latest troubles in Drachenfels about one of the more prominent mercenaries that involved themselves in that mess. As recreational reading goes, you've certainly seen more frivolous volumes. --- "Why did you take me on as your Apprentice?" is the first question Eike asks as the engine winds down and you lead her into your home. That's a complicated question, with an equally complicated answer. But the answer you give is much more pared down. "Because I think you have the potential to be a good Wizard, and I think I can help you realize that potential." "Not because of Oma?" she says, with admirable boldness. "I know you well enough to have evaluated you because of her, but if this was just about the EIC, well, I know you know the numbers. It would take a lot less time to lean on Anton or the Counts and have enough votes to appoint whoever I wanted than to try to make a puppet out of you." "Oh," she says simply. "Before you settle in, since you're going to be working in and around the Karak a fair bit, there's something I need to read you into. Tell me, do you know of any form of Beastman other than the standard equine, caprine and bovine varieties?" She frowns as she considers that. "There's the birdmen, well, birdwomen, the wolfmen of Norsca, and the frogmen of the Wasteland, and the lizardmen of Lustria and the Southlands..." "Any within the Empire?" you hint. She frowns, hesitating. "The Ulricskinder?" "Good guess, but I wouldn't describe them as Beastmen within earshot of an Ulrican unless I really wanted to have an argument. There's a much more numerous and dangerous form of Beastman in the Empire - the ratmen, known as Skaven. They live underground, very often under our very own cities, and they aren't publicly acknowledged because neither we nor they want a war of mutual extinction - we've got plenty of problems to deal with already and they like to be left alone to fight amongst themselves. If we really go at it with each other we'd each end up being stamped out by our respective other foes once we bleed each other dry. But, of course, neither side can openly admit that without it being seen as weakness or cowardice by the more militant members of our societies. We call it the 'Conspiracy of Silence', and helping to enforce it is one of the more important duties of the Grey Order. But the Dwarves have been in open war with them for millennia, and several of their factions were present in Karak Eight Peaks during the reconquest, so they're talked of openly here." She frowns. "Do they serve Chaos?" "Not that we know of - they serve their own God called the 'Horned Rat', and though It's certainly an unpleasant deity, It doesn't seem to act in concert with the Four, even during the time of an Everchosen. They have their own forms of Dark Magic, and their society is split into Clans with each specializing in a specific type of magic or warfare. Their society is very insular, which means little was really known about them until very recently, when a particularly clever person was able to capture one of their officers and extract from them enough information to translate their most common dialect. A project that is, I understand, still ongoing, and increasing the Empire's knowledge of the creatures of the Near East, where that Skaven previously commanded an outpost." You stop as you reach the door of Qrech's cell, and weave an Illusion of an empty corridor around Eike. "Keep quiet and still." You knock, wait a polite few seconds, then enter the cell to find Qrech staring into the air with a pair of pince-nez balanced upon his snout. He seems distracted, and doesn't seem to react as you enter his room. "How go your studies?" you ask him lightly. "Good, fine." He says distractedly. "More interest than usual, more resources available, more students that need teaching. Trade routes shifting, people want to know more about what might prey upon them on the way east." "That's good to hear. Bodes well for your ambitions." "Mm," he hums in vague agreement, which isn't like him. "Something wrong?" "Have you been poisoning or potioning or magicking me?" he asks abruptly, turning his gaze to you. You frown as you consider that. You used to ensorcel him before making changes to his prison, but in recent years the only changes necessary have been those that he requested. "Not in many years. Why do you ask?" He stares at you a while before answering. "Qrech is old," he says frankly. "And I have never known anyone older than I am now that did not owe it to the Grey Seers or the Master Moulders or the Warlock Engineers. Qrech is strong, but not stronger than everyone I have known who died younger. Why do I still live?" "Why would you not?" "Because Qrech is old," he repeats. You're starting to see what he's getting at. His vision seems to have faded in recent years, hence the pince-nez, and his fur is a little greyer than you remember. "By which you mean, your reactions are a little slower, you get out of breath a little easier, you take a little longer to recover from exertion and injury?" He nods, a little hesitantly. "You're just getting older. It typically happens to humans somewhere from thirty to forty." He looks at you quizzically. "You are thirty to forty, yes?" "I turn forty next year." "You have suffered this?" "I have," you lie. He glances up to your shoulder, where you once wore a sword and now wear your staff instead, though not for the reason you think Qrech is assuming. "And have not been supplanted?" "Why would I be? In all likelihood I have several good decades left that would be lost if some ambitious underling killed me, so it is not allowed to happen." "But if one were to do so, it would prove they were stronger." Qrech's voice is quiet, and thick with the tension of not letting the doubt swirling inside of him show in his voice. "Does strength write books or weave magic? Does strength build guns or grow grain or spy on enemies? Why should the strongest have authority over that which does not require strength?" "If they are strong, they can take it." "They might be stronger than one person, but they are not stronger than their society. If their society does not allow them to take all that they desire, they cannot. And then those who are weak in body but strong in mind use their minds to better their society for their entire lifespan, not just until they are no longer able to keep themselves from being killed by their underlings." You weigh the matter for a moment, then decide to go a step further. "I do not think you have ever known a Skaven that has died of old age. You only know those who reach the highest heights they could manage when they were young and fast and strong, and then grow older and can only make up for the speed and strength of youth with cunning and treachery for so long. I think that while you're here, with no ambitious underling and no shortage of food, you could have as much as half your life still ahead of you." Qrech stares at you in obvious bafflement. "Half?" "Sure. What you're describing is what we call 'middle age'. Most humans who survive childhood reach it, and if we reach it and are careful and a little lucky, we could still have half our life ahead of us." You watch Qrech try to process that, and recall the sense of urgency that had been propelling him to try to achieve his doctorate, a status he seems to equate with that of a Master Moulder of his former Clan. He had thought he had only a precious few years, maybe even only months, left to spend, and now he finds himself grappling with the possibility of decades stretching out before him. It has to be quite a shock. Of course, this is all just supposition on your part. It could be that Skaven senescence is fundamentally different to that of humans and he really is on the verge of death from old age. But it wouldn't be the first time you told him a lie to put a wedge between him and his former society. And if he dies a little happier for thinking he still has plenty of years ahead of him, then you don't see any harm in that. After it becomes clear he has nothing more to say, you leave him to his thoughts and back out of the room, closing the door behind you and then dismissing the Illusion. "That was a more intense conversation with him than I expected," you admit as you turn to Eike. "He thought he was dying?" she asks quietly, and you're surprised to see tears in her eyes, and you lead her down the corridor to avoid any chance of Qrech overhearing. "Apparently so. Skaven society is extremely treacherous, and Skaven age quickly and most don't reach twenty. Only their leaders live much longer than that, and that's with magical intervention to maintain them at their physical peaks. How long they'd live outside of their extremely violent and stressful society is an open question." "That's so sad," she says, a catch in her voice. You consider that. "I suppose it is," you concede, "though I try to focus on preventing human lives from being cut short. If we had met under other circumstances Qrech would have happily killed and eaten me, and him having the chance to live a long and relatively happy life is just a happy side-effect of my service to the Empire." "Are there many happy side-effects as a Grey Wizard?" she asks you, wiping at her eyes. You lead Eike out onto the balcony so she can get some fresh air, and find yourself smiling down at the patchwork of fields in the Eastern Valley. "There can be," you say, your smile growing as Eike gasps and leans out on the railing as she takes in the view, her tears forgotten as she looks over the flourishing community that has taken root in Karak Eight Peaks. Spoiler: Coming Next When you had been told there was going to be some sort of diplomatic soiree in the anterooms of the Silver Tower that you were invited to attend as a representative of the Empire, you had a few guesses as to what it may be about. Those guesses needed substantial revising after a Druchii Ravenship sailed up the Schaukel and docked at the city, flying three flags depicting an eye, a pegasus, and a hydra, and in doing so attracting only a few curious onlookers and a greeting delegation rather than a raising of the alarm.

Turn 39 Social - 2489 - Part 3

When you had been told there was going to be some sort of diplomatic soiree in the anterooms of the Silver Tower that you were invited to attend as a representative of the Empire, you had a few guesses as to what it may be about. Those guesses needed substantial revising after a Druchii Ravenship sailed up the Schaukel and docked at the city, flying three flags depicting an eye, a pegasus, and a hydra, and in doing so attracting only a few curious onlookers and a greeting delegation rather than a raising of the alarm. You send sketches of its flags to the Grey Order with an urgent request for information, and though the response is prompt, it's also scanter than you'd like. You're told that the flags represent three of the six major city-states of Naggaroth: Ghrond, the headquarters of the order of Sorceresses and domain of the Queen Mother of the Druchii, Hag Graef, the city atop a sprawling network of mines and quarries that make it second only to the capital in wealth and power, and Clar Karond, the shipyard and breadbasket of Naggaroth. Notable by their absence are the other three flags: the clutched moon of the capital Naggarond is missing, suggesting that this is either unofficial or a gambit of Queen Mother, rather than the King, and that the bloody heart of the Khainite stronghold of Har Ganeth and the harpy of the Corsair capital of Karond Kar are absent suggests that those present could be as reasonable as the Druchii are capable of being, since they left the fanatics and the slavers at home. What the letter does not tell you is that you're authorized to speak on behalf of the Empire in such a gathering. Such trust was already granted to you when you were given the role of Lady Magister, and needs not be restated, even if it would be comforting to hear it now. You're painfully aware that what little reading you've done of material concerning the Druchii are very unlikely to be applicable to the coming challenges. Though you know you have nowhere near enough time to actually do it, you mentally run through the contacts and funds you could have taken advantage of to secure all the written knowledge of the Druchii to be found in the Old World and yearn for more time. Then you set that yearning aside, make sure your robes are neat and clean - not for the first time, you thank all the Gods that the robes of office of a Lady Magister count as formal dress - and do your best to spend the mere days before the gathering productively. --- By the time of the gathering itself, you've calmed down a bit and gotten your thoughts in order. While the Druchii are reprehensible in practically every respect, from an entirely Imaschiavellian perspective they can be considered to be mostly someone else's problem. Though their corsairs do periodically visit the coasts of the Empire, such coastlines are already thoroughly preyed upon by the Norscans, so what little infrastructure and what few population centres exist on that coastline are either fortified well enough to make any raid on them more trouble than its worth, or so minor that their loss is hardly noticed. Their only other direct impact on the Empire is in the form of piracy, and with them competing for prey with the Norscans, the pirates of Sartosa, the corsairs of Lashiek and Al-Haikk, the zombie pirates of the Vampire Coast, and the fleets of the Skaven and the Chaos Dwarves, it's hard to say whether their absence from that motley pack would reduce the total amount of piracy or simply result in a greater share of the plunder for everyone else. The overwhelming majority of their attention is focused on their millennia-long internecine war with Ulthuan, and there are those in the Old World who would argue that keeping the Asur distracted is to the Empire's benefit. After all, the Druchii never lent military support to a breakaway state of the Empire. You're greeted at the door by a servant that leads you to the Queen, and you ask her what brings the Druchii here. "Yourself, of course," she says, smiling mischievously at your look of shock. "Indirectly, that is. Even if they knew about it, I doubt they'd have any interest in the Waystone Project for its own sake. They have sufficient skill with Dhar to make use of all that is available, rather than needing infrastructure to whisk it away. But if Ulthuan has a foothold in the Old World, then they'll want one too, if only to keep tabs on what Ulthuan is up to and to watch for opportunities to interfere with it... but I digress. In truth, since we're working with humans, there was no reason for us not to also put out feelers to the two claimants of the Phoenix Throne to see if we can play them against each other. The board between them has been stalemated for so long that the introduction of even a minor piece is one that either could be tempted into paying handsomely for." "You think they might be convinced to contribute to the Project just to spite Ulthuan?" "I'll leave whether the opportunity is given to them up to you, but I think they'd do literally anything to spite Ulthuan. And in this specific scenario, there'd be no downside for them. If everything goes according to plan, then they can parlay that into countering Ulthuan's influence and interests in the Old World. If something goes wrong, then it creates problems that Ulthuan has to fix, because it's Ulthuan that's most directly dependent on the integrity of the Great Vortex. And in either case it has a good chance of widening the rift between Ulthuan and the Empire, which is something they'd delight in all on its own. But what they're formally here for is the more prosaic forms of trade while we dance about the possibility of endorsing one candidate or the other. There's few Elven societies that wouldn't pay a premium for novel luxuries, of which we've developed many over the years, and the Druchii have an endless hunger for new kinds of beasts. We won't be shipping off any Unicorns or Great Stags, of course, but there's less salubrious inhabitants of the darker corners of Laurelorn, and Boris has said he'd be more than happy for our hunters to scour the Drakwald." She opens her mouth to continue, and then halts mid-step, staring through an archway into a room filled with buzzing conversation, her face falling. "Oh no, it's Uncle Harathi. Sorry, I have to handle this." You have barely a moment to process this before she's gone, and with her gone you are now vulnerable and are ensnared by a nearby conversation. There is a set of physics at work in gatherings like this that you're helpless to fight against once you're this engulfed, and do your best to tread conversational water as the currents and eddies of the soiree pull you to and fro, and before long you find yourself drawn towards one of the three guests and the apparent leader of the Druchii delegation, who has just topped up her drink and wrapped up a conversation as you reach her with such ease that it's only her smirk that tells you that it was no accident. Dreadlord Ylrishen of Hag Graef - you managed to pick the name up while circulating - is dressed in ornate black full plate armour trimmed with gold, as well as a purple cloak and at least five knives. Her long white hair reaches down to the back of her knees - presumably in battle it would be tied up under her helmet, which she isn't currently wearing - and the clawed gauntlets she is wearing must make her careful holding of a crystal goblet rather difficult. Her face is starkly attractive in an intimidating sort of way, all smooth skin and sharp angles, and rather than the aloof superiority that you might expect from such a woman, her gaze is surprisingly intense as she studies you, as though trying to decide whether you'd make better prey or product. "Greetings, Sorceress," she says to you, her voice an amused and aristocratic drawl with a hint of roughness. "And to you, Dreadlord Ylrishen." She looks you up and down, eyes flicking from your shadow to the shadows and wisps of smoke clinging to you. "Fascinating. You humans really do take every scrap of magical knowledge you get your hands on and wring it to the last morsel, don't you? A pity the usurpers got to you before we did, who knows what you might have accomplished with better instruction." "And what would have been the price of that tutoring?" you ask, in a voice that could technically be considered polite. She tuts. "Nothing beyond your Empire's capacity to withstand. Don't let the usurpers mislead you, cruelty is just one of the many blades that we masterfully wield." "And one, it seems, that would need regular rehoning." She smiles, making no attempt to disagree. "It is a fundamental truth of this world that all civilization is paid for in suffering." She angles her glass to catch the light of a nearby sconce. "All forms of governance are means of dictating who it is that will do that suffering. So many object to the Druchii because we freely admit that which they invent entire realms of philosophy to try to conceal. Tell me, would you take the life of a Goblin to save the life of a human of the Empire?" "Of course," you say. "What about a Goblin that did not directly threaten the life of a human, but was raiding their farmland and thus would starve them to death in the long term?" "I do see where you're going with this." "Then you see that there is only logistical differences between the slaying of a Goblin raider to save a human from starvation, and the enslaving of a human to feed the Druchii. And by embracing the truth of the matter, we have been able to greatly increase the efficiency of the transferral of suffering, so that the maximum value is extracted from each slave, minimizing the total number of beings that need suffer - for reasons of cost rather than morality, I'll grant you, but the effect is the same." "The Greenskins I've combatted have been those in a state of war with the Empire or its allies, though," you say, though you see the counterpoint coming before you even finish the sentence. "All of them? Every single one? Or do you simply assume that is the case because it so often is, and act accordingly? The overwhelming majority of experiences that the Druchii have with humans is defending our northern border from the Hung and the Dorstan, and our coasts from the Norscans. If this has led us to assume that all the humans of the Great Ocean are offshoots of these, then it is a mistake that the righteous Asur also made until a mere couple of centuries ago, and it is one we have a lot more shed blood to justify. Entire cities in Naggaroth exist solely as a bulwark against the northern tribes." She takes a sip of her drink, then looks mildly surprised and gives it a curious look. "And despite all that, here we are, seeking a cure to our ignorance and rebuilt ties with our lost kin. We have taken no states of the Empire as vassals, we have sent no Sorceresses against your armies. Let our actions prove our superiority to the Asur, rather than letting their poisoned whispers doom us to an eternity of enmity simply because they got to you first." You give the appearance of thinking over her words as you resist the urge to narrow your eyes at the Dreadlord, and then you take a breath and actually think over her words. The cruelty and brutality of the Druchii are legendary, but if they were all entirely true, then they would describe a society that could not exist for more than a few decades, let alone the millennia of apparent stability it's achieved. Downgrade those fancies to less lurid and more sustainable forms of harshness and you have something that might be thought justified, or at least understandable, when visited upon those humans that were enslaved because they threw themselves against the thousand miles of Naggaroth's northern border at the orders of the Chaos Gods. If that was the case, then could that be overlooked, in the same way that the Empire does the more dubious institutions of its human neighbours? After all, the Empire's ban on slavery is more an accident of history than a purely moral stance, as Sigmar had enforced it to give the newly-united tribes one less reason to raid each other. And there are plenty of agitators that argue that the institution of slavery lives on in various forms throughout the Old World, and the ones that point to serfdom and debt bondage might have a point, even if they do tend to get drowned out by the rather shriller ones that consider religion or taxation forms of slavery. And even if you don't believe any of these arguments, there may be value in at least pretending to. You've done business with worse than the Druchii, and it may be to the Empire's betterment if Ulthuan is given reason to rethink spending all its influence in the Old World on propping up Marienburg's belligerence. There are many forces that prey upon the Empire, and though the Druchii could easily be argued to be one of them, they wouldn't have any compunction against arming the Empire against the others if they thought it was in their interest. "You have given me much to think about," you say to her. "That said, your words would ring all the truer if they were matched with a ceasing of raids on the Empire's coastline." She gives a negligent shrug. "I cannot speak for all of my kind, just as you cannot speak for all of yours. There are always rabble from Karond Kar who will raid anywhere and feel no compunctions against lying about the provenance of their cargo." She gives you a considering look. "That said, a better understanding between our people might result in all sorts of information flowing back and forth. Clar Karond and Karond Kar are bitter rivals, and Clar Karond would profit if Karond Kar needed to come to them to replace ships lost by a chance encounter with that navy of yours. A few such opportune encounters and they would learn to seek softer shores." She drains her glass and starts craning her neck to seek a refill. "Give the matter some thought. My door will be open to you, should you wish it to be. Dalakoi, Sorceress." --- The hithers and thons of the flow of conversation takes you from one end of the room to the other, and in doing so you manage to pick up the gist of the trouble with 'Uncle' Harathi - great-great uncle to Queen Marrisith, and also half-nephew to Malekith and therefore, you think... great-nephew-in-law to Morathi? In the current era he is an ancient and respected Grey Lord, but there was a time when he was little more than a child and a student of magic in Saphethion, the former capital of Saphery, and when the Civil War started he survived the civil war on the airborne streets, and then the transformation of the city into an enormous engine of war and the subsequent battles it fought in, and then the crash of the city into the Annulii Mountains during the Sundering, and then the long journey from the mountains back to civilization. And what awaited him at the end of all of that was banishment in all but name to Laurelorn, where his sister, Handmaiden to the Everqueen, was overseeing a research expedition to study the area. In time that Handmaiden became the first Queen of the Eonir and Harathi became one of the Grey Lords, but it seems that even large amounts of time are not reliable healers of emotional wounds among the Elves. You exercise what little control you can manage over your course to try to direct yourself away from that potential drama and instead find your path taking you towards the other remaining Druchii, Captain Maktig of Clar Karond. As you brace yourself for another mental duel with an ancient mind of cruel cunning, the gaze that turns to you is instead a forlorn and guileless one. "Have you ever been to sea?" he asks, in a voice with only the most battered shred of hope remaining in it. You get the impression he's asked that question quite a lot already, and received the same answer every time. You open your mouth to dash his hopes, then remember something. "Once, technically. Over the Frozen Sea." "Oh? Visiting the Fire Dwarves?" "Not that time. I was coming back from an expedition into the Chaos Wastes and cut across the Frozen Sea to reach Kislev via Norsca." He looks baffled and impressed in equal measure. "Why would you go into the Chaos Wastes?" "To see what was there." He stares at you a while longer, then grabs a glass from someone nearby to thrust into your hand so he can clink his against it. "That's the only sensible thing I've heard in four thousand miles of rough seas. Tell me about it all." You comply, carefully editing out the true purpose of the voyage and the company you had, which still leaves a fairly gripping yarn of battling Daemons, raiding Skaven lairs, visiting Uzkulak, bartering with Kurgan, and duelling Norscans. By the time your reimagined caravan has reached Kislev once more you've attracted quite a crowd, and you wrap it up by lingering regretfully on you having to decide against attempting to purloin a mammoth from the Norscans. Maktig shakes his head in amazement. "By Mathlann, you're wasted here on land. Join my ship and I'll pay you a Sorceress' share and you'll have a cabin all to yourself." You take a moment to entertain the possibility before shaking your head. "My current job isn't one that can be just walked away from." "So I figured, but I had to try. Say, you ever encountered the other kind of Dwarves? The Stone Dwarves?" You smile. "A time or two." "Are they as fierce on land as they are at sea?" "From what I understand, they're rather out of their element at sea, so I'd say even more so." "That must be quite a story," he says promptingly. You take a breath and begin to weave together and tell a suitable yarn on the fly. --- After a surprisingly enjoyable time spinning yarns with Captain Maktig, you part ways with him and surrender yourself to the inevitability of being drawn towards the last Druchii delegate, Sorceress Myrielh of Ghrond. But there's an eddy in the currents because, it seems, the Queen has failed to properly corral the renegade Grey Lord and now everybody's side-eyes are on the confrontation occurring in one corner of the room. "My, my," the Grey Lord says, eyeing up a Sorceress with severely frayed composure, who is wearing what looks like the front and back quarters of a skirt and a metal bustier that must be absolutely freezing to what little of her it covers. "The dress codes Auntie Rathi enforces have changed dramatically since she taught me." "The First Sorceress sends her regards, Prince Harathi," she says in a voice only slightly quavering with nervousness. "Only her regards? Nothing else this time? No poisons, no kidnappers, no assassins? A shame. I've had quite some time to hone my skills since her last offering to me. Tell me, does she still teach the quarter-spinwards turn on her vortices?" There's a moment of hesitation. "I have not had the honour of being personally taught by the First Sorceress, but-" "Because if she is, she's playing the same games with you that she did with Sapherion. It gets you to the point of being able to cast a little faster, but it prevents any real mastery until you spend more time unlearning it than it saved you in the first place." The Sorceress does not react, but her lack of reaction instead of reacting with any sort of confusion or denial is apparently enough for Lord Harathi. "So she is. Well, to be fair to her, she might not be outright sabotaging the Dark Convent, she just may not have had the time to teach you properly among all of her other distractions. She's only had six or seven millennia to do so, after all. Hardly any time at all to a woman with as many little hobbies on the side as she has." "The Dark Convent are ever loyal to the Queen Mother of Naggaroth," the Sorceress says with practiced firmness. "And nobody else, I'm sure. And yet here you are, on an expedition with only equal status to Clar Karond. I never knew Auntie Rathi to willingly play second to anyone but my dear uncle. Are you sure she sends her regards? Are you sure she knows of this visit at all?" The Sorceress seems to have regained some of her composure, and only stares back, managing not to give anything away. "Tch. That's a shame. It would be a waste of a perfectly good murder if she didn't even know you were here." As Harathi flaunts away, the Sorceress takes a breath, the Winds rippling and a series of dirty looks turning her way as she recentres herself. Dhar blooms and writhes within her and she seems to transform without externally changing in any way, her outfit going from ridiculous affectation to a flaunting of her dominance over the elements, the traces of Dark Magic clinging to her going from an elusive whiff of foulness to a sickly-sweet scent that hovers just between cloying and enticing, and the gaze that turns to you is almost fully restored to that familiar look of superiority. "Elven society is built out of feuds and resentments that were old long before any of us were born," she says with a laugh that almost manages to conceal her rattled nerves. "Compared to such beings, the difference between you and I seems to vanish." "From a certain point of view, I suppose," you say cautiously. "It is my pleasure to be Sorceress Myrielh of Ghrond, and at your service." "Lady Magister Mathilde Weber of the Grey Order, at yours," you respond. Thankfully, millennia of back and forth have established firm precedent that no matter how creative someone tries to get, the rote phrase 'at your service' means nothing more than to be willing to listen to what they have to say. She smiles at you, and then gives you a more calculating gaze that suddenly turns surprised. "Have you... pierced your soul with Ulgu? Repeatedly?" You look down at yourself, and wave away some of the mist clinging to you. In Tor Lithanel there's much less smoke than in human cities, so currently most of it is perfume. "That would be one way to describe it." "How do you manage that? Wouldn't breaching the surface tension of the soul that many times be ruinous to its integrity?" "Not if it's performed from within." "It's self-inflicted?" she says, looking closer with an expression of delighted horror. "We knew that you'd received some instruction from the usurpers, but hadn't realized you'd developed upon it yourselves in such a bold way." "We do our best. What is it that brings a representative of Ghrond to the Elthin Arvan?" you say, changing the subject before you're forced to undermine the unexpected impression you've made. "Most visits from the Druchii to our corner of the world are to isolated coastal hamlets." "Only on the rare occasions that the Norscans don't get to them first," she counters with a sniff. "Very few of the cuts your Empire is forever bleeding from come from Druchii blades. In fact, I believe that much more of your blood has been shed by the riders of the bastard steeds to the west in any one of the wars you've fought, than has been by all the Druchii Corsairs throughout history, and yet you ride to war alongside them when circumstances dictate you must." You try not to show too much agreement at that. For all that Bretonnia did fight alongside the Empire in the Great War Against Chaos, there have been the Third and Fourth Parravon Wars since then. The Third started before the dust had fully settled from the Great War, and the Fourth was recent enough that some of the songs about it are still floating around. "Perhaps. What's the point you're angling towards, Sorceress?" "My point? My point is that you owe so much to a single precocious youth sharing the tattered scraps of the pale shadow of the past that is the White Tower. Imagine what you could achieve with just a few secrets from my ageless mistress." "Your mistress in Ghrond, or your mistress elsewhere?" She appears unruffled by the question. "Are you knowledgeable enough to meaningfully differentiate between the two?" Not really. Oh, you've heard a few legends of dubious provenance about Morathi over the years, but they have the salacious ring of propaganda rather than anything grounded in truth, and you don't know anything at all about whoever might be her counterpart in Clar Karond. So you simply nod in acknowledgement and move on. "And what price would your mistress, wherever she may be, demand in exchange?" "Knowledge for knowledge. Every corner of the world has its mysteries, and as you well know, most of your Empire has never seen the visit of a single Druchii ship. Descriptions of those within your reach, and samples of whatever of them can be sampled and transported, would garner quite a bit of her attention and gratitude, and would be paid for handsomely." "Better terms than I expected, but it does contrast rather glaringly with the origin of our Orders." She snorts. "Your Orders should have learned that impulsive generosity is so very fleeting when your princeling abandoned you. That my mistress would speak to you as one scholar to another is a kindness, because that is a relationship you can rely upon to last, and one you will know you have earned." You allow yourself to nod in slight approval at that. As grateful as the Orders were and are to Teclis, that he promised to return after seeing to personal business in Ulthuan and then never did is something that weighed on the minds of many that knew him, and still a perhaps embarrassing amount today. The self-interest of the Druchii might be seen as a rather more reliable rock upon which to build a relationship. "And would such a relationship preclude future predation upon our shorelines? Both present and future?" She grins in a way that is difficult to describe as unpleasant, even though it is thick with smug savagery. "Should such a relationship be established, we could do more for your hopes of a revanched shoreline than merely promise not to prey upon them. Your errant subject has benefited greatly from the patronage of our oldest enemy, and we would welcome an opportunity to demonstrate both the limitations of Ulthuan's beneficence and the depths of Naggaroth's maleficence. The contrast between them, I assure you, would be quite staggering." You try not to be tempted. You try not to think of a sunken steamship, of Dwarven corpses floating in black water. Of obscenely wealthy families threatening to starve the Empire for the crime of building canals on the other side of the continent simply because they might slow their acquisition of even more wealth. "I have no doubt." "As you shouldn't," she says, giving you a look that's as approving as it is patronizing. "Well, we'll be back and forth quite often as we bring word back and forth between thrones. Should there be anything we need discuss, leave word for us and I'll pay you a visit next time I'm in this surprisingly charming example of pre-Betrayal architecture." She waves her fingers in farewell and pivots with an undoubtedly deliberate swing of her hips and swish of her skirts to delve back into the crowd. You frown after her, already having started to unpick exactly how many ways pursuing the opportunities that these three Druchii represent could blow up in your face, and how many ways they could catapult your many projects forward. - Opinions expressed by Druchii are solely their own, and do not express the views or opinions of the writer.

Turn 39 Social - 2489 - Part 4

It was, perhaps, inevitable that the branches of the Council of Manhorak would begin jostling for position amongst each other. On one hand, the village of Bylorhof has remained true to Bylorak throughout the centuries, so some argue that this demonstrates the faith and strength of will that makes it worthy of being the heart of the resurgent faith. But others argue that the reason Bylorak survived is not due to any inherent virtue of its believers, but because of the simple fact that it is far from all of the other population centers of Sylvania, making it not worth the trouble for the Vampires to subjugate. The same remoteness that saved it also makes it an impractical location for any sort of centralized bastion of faith. "I think it's going to end up being Drakenhof more or less by default," Kasmir says to you. He's met you in a tavern by the Tempelhof docks, and the two of you sit outside as you watch the bustle of Sylvania tentatively connecting itself with the rest of the Empire's economy, bland Ostermark ales in hand. "It's the largest town in Sylvania, and it's been the administrative centre of it since the time of the Von Draks, so it's going to be where the Markgraf operates out of. Having the heart of the faith be somewhere it can easily access the ears of those that will be ruling Sylvania makes too much sense not to. But that puts Bylorhof's nose out of joint, because Drakenhof is harder to access for them than it would be for representatives from Waldenhof or Tempelhof." "It does back up the argument that the reason that faith in Bylorak survived was geographical," you say, measuring distances on a mental map. "It almost makes more sense for Bylorhof to be part of southern Stirland than Sylvania." "It probably would have ended up that way if Abelhelm had been less ambitious," Kasmir says with a sigh. "If he'd only cleansed the Hills, then the western half would have ended up being folded into Leicheberg, Bylorhof included. That or spin off Swartzhafen as a new barony with all the fresh farmland reclaimed from what had been the Ghoul Wood. In either case, within a generation or two they would have been completely assimilated, and Bylorak probably would have been declared an aspect of Taal or Manann." "It's a pity the waterways don't link together anywhere closer than Nuln," you observe. "Funny you should say that," Kasmir says with a laugh. "Some of them actually want to build a temple to Manhorak on the banks of the Black Water, since that's upstream of all of them." "Is that really so crazy? The paths have been improved a fair bit these days, and once the canal's been completed there's going to be plenty of traffic going back and forth." "That's what I thought at first, but the Dwarves say that while it's mostly safe to travel on or beside it, anything permanent needs a permanent garrison to fend off raids from the residents of Karak Varn." "Clan Ferrik," you say with a nod. "No, the Yellow Eye Tribe. We know a fair bit about them since they regularly launch raids into Averland and ambush travellers in Black Fire Pass." You give Kasmir a sideways look. "What are the odds of that temple actually being built?" "Fairly low, but there'll probably end up being pilgrimages and maybe a shrine of some sort once the canal's done. Why?" "Do you know of any other enemies that might be an issue in the area?" He starts giving you the same sideways look, then nods in understanding. "Oh, of course you'd know about them. Clan Ferrik are rats, then?" You relax, glad you're not going to have to do the full reading in. "Yes, a Warlord Clan that was rival to Clan Mors, and either closely tied to Clan Skryre or a Thrall Clan to them. So given the circumstances they'd probably be even more active and ambitious than usual." "Ah. I'll try to dissuade the idea of establishing a presence up there, then. One of the very few mercies of Sylvania is that they don't have to deal with the ratmen." He frowns and nods towards the waterfront. "Speaking of rats..." Among those disembarking a nearby ferry is a man whose appearance is aggressively bland, dressed in well-worn breeches and slacks in faded greys and browns with a leather scabbard on his hip. But as you turn your full attention to him, you note that there is no dull weight of Chamon lurking within the scabbard, only more traces of Ghur. Bone, then, and from something exotic for it to be able to serve as a long blade. Now that you're looking for it, you also spot the ivory buckle to his belt and the polished wooden toggles on his tunic. A Taalite, then, and one of particular zealousness, as mainstream Taalite strictures only frowned upon metal armour. You say as much, and Kasmir nods. "There was a Stormguard last month, and what I think was an Amarite before that." Kasmir raises his tankard in greeting to the man, who turns at the movement, halts mid-step as he takes in the two of you observing him, and after a moment of thought he turns around and walks back aboard the ferry. "They're a practical lot, the Taalites." "You knew he was coming?" He nods. "There's not a boatman or docker on the Stir who would lightly invite Manhorak's displeasure, so they've been tipping the Council off about unusual travelers. Some of them go right into the Fenn, but others need a more measured response." He gives a half-smile. "Part of me wishes things were still simple - see Vampire, smite Vampire. But they weren't actually simple, were they? The complicated stuff was still there, it just wasn't getting done." You nod in commiseration. "The reward for digging the best holes is to be taught about a new kind of shovel." --- Reports from the EIC, like most streams of news and gossip in the Empire right now, are dominated by the matter of Nuln. You flick through the conflicting early reports until you get to ones written after the dust had settled and the damage tallied: what appears to have been a massive sinkhole opened up in the southeastern end of the Universität quarter of the Neuestadt district, and the Town Hall, the Hall of Archives, and the Imperial Gunnery School have collapsed into the cavern below. The death toll is not as high as it could have been if it opened up under a residential area, but those that were lost were several dormitories of what would have been the next generation of the Empire's siege engineers and artillerymen. Unmentioned in any of these reports, but unmistakable to anyone who knows of the War Below, is those to blame for all of this. By all accounts Under-Nuln was absolutely flooded with soldiers and mercenaries, ostensibly to search for survivors, and that they all seem to have emerged again indicates that this was a parting shot from the Skaven as they withdrew from Under-Nuln, rather than the opening shot of a whole new war. Either Clan Skab did very poorly out of the civil war and felt unwilling or unable to fight a war with Nuln, or they did very well and were able to claim more prestigious and less contested territory, and have shifted their seat of power there. Whoever has taken up the Spymaster role for Wissenland seems to be a deft hand, because official blame was levelled against shoddy maintenance of the sewers below Nuln and unofficial blame against the city's mythical 'Night Market', a supposed secret city of mutants that is said to exist far below the city. Now the undercity is being flooded with engineers, architects, cavers, and regular patrols, with the Elector Count Konstantin von Liebwitz promising that the sewer system, famously dating back to the time of Sigmar, will never again be allowed to become a threat to the city above. Very neatly phrased, too neat for you to credit it to the plain-spoken man you encountered previously. Permanently shutting the Skaven out of Under-Nuln might be a poor compensation for the lives and records lost, but it would have to do. Seriously, it would have to. The Empire doesn't need a vengeance-obsessed Elector Count dragging it into all-out war with the Under-Empire. As you try to put the possibility out of your mind, you recall the Imperial Gunnery School sprouting off its new branch in Karag Nar, and the vast amount of institutional knowledge that had to be very laboriously taught and copied over to make it work. In the years to come it will all be copied back as the original is rebuilt, and you wonder how much would have been lost altogether if it hadn't all been so recently duplicated. You recall the words of the Magister Matriarch of the Celestial College, warning you to take good care of the Karag Nar branch. Very needed, indeed. You do your best to turn your attention away from the matter. These were matters of concern to the Spymistress of Wissenland, and also theoretically to a Loremistress-at-Large of Karak Eight Peaks or a secret catspaw of the Empress, but not to someone trying to manage a research project on the other side of the Empire. Besides, a more pressing problem for you is your encounter in the northern wastes of Kislev, and your decision to remind Borek of your outstanding debt to him. When you did, he looked confused, then surprised, then thoughtful. 'I pass the debt to Gotrek's remaining kin,' he'd said. 'Poor recompense for the loss of a husband and a father, but there is no other I can make.' Your current liquid funds, if converted from Imperial and Kislevite coinage to Dwarven, comes in at a little over 2,200 gold coins, which came from various windfalls and if exhausted would take half a decade of frugality to replace. It is just capable of repaying the 2,000 gold coins of the debt you now owe to Gotrek's widow. You'd found, to your surprise, that she'd ended up in Karak Eight Peaks, but instead of moving in to Karag Rhyn she'd joined the small community of Imperial Dwarves that have made a home in Karag Nar. This raises an interesting possibility, as with most of the economy of Karag Nar dominated by the EIC, there is what might be thought of as a more elegant way to repay the debt - credit her with that sum at EIC-backed establishments and allow it to disappear into the ledgers as just another operating expense. This could be classified as a form of embezzlement, but could also be classified as a good way to strengthen the EIC's good name and to gain influence over an unexpected but influential minority among Karag Nar's community. And besides, two thousand crowns in retail credit will cost the EIC significantly less than that in wholesale acquisitions. Or you could abrogate the matter altogether, let them know that a debt you owed has been passed to them and let them decide how to use it. The ephemeral economy of boons is one very familiar to the Dwarves, and there could be services you could do for the two of them that money could not buy. Or you could just... keep the gold. You did remind Borek about it when you could have not done that, but perhaps part of you thought he'd just wave it off and then you'd have done the right thing for free. And Borek is doing his best to die on the other side of the continent, he's not going to be dropping by to audit you. Is this what we have become? one corner of your mind asks. Robbing the widow of a comrade in arms? This is what we have always been, another counters. We have done worse to achieve a fraction of the good that much gold could accomplish, and will do so again. To at least consider it is what we seek to be, a third muses. A Grey Wizard weighs all possibilities, not just the nice ones. You absently push a gold coin around the table, your attention turned inwards as you observe in fascination as parts of your mind war against each other. [ ] [DEBT] Pay in coin [ ] [DEBT] Pay in credit [ ] [DEBT] Owe a boon [ ] [DEBT] Don't pay Library Purchases: [ ] [LIBRARY] Colleges of Magic Name four magical, non-divine topics to acquire all available Empire books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Barak Varr booksellers Name three public topics to acquire all available Empire and Dwarven books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Library of Mournings Name two non-magical topics to hire Cityborn scribes to copy all available Laurelorn books on. [ ] [LIBRARY] Back-fill. Instead of seeking books on specific topics, give a very broad direction and have your bookselling contacts grab everything on it that you don't already have, with special attention to existing but incomplete topics. Possible categories: Dwarven religion, human religion, geography, war and combat, social science, natural science, applied science. Dwarf Favour Purchases Aethyric Vitae can be spent instead of favour at an exchange rate of 3 favour per gallon; for Rune-related purchases, this will also guarantee the cooperation of Runelords who may otherwise be disinterested. To use this, simply add 'paid by Vitae' or similar to an item you are voting for. [ ] [DWARF] No purchase. [ ] [DWARF] Write-in. College Favour Purchases [ ] [COLLEGE] No purchase. [ ] [COLLEGE] Write-in. Other Purchases [ ] [PURCHASE] No purchase. [ ] [PURCHASE] Write-in. - There will be a twelve hour moratorium as various purchase plans are dug back up and I get a night's sleep. - This kind of is a relitigation of a previous vote, but I did see an awful lot of people speculating that Borek was going to shrug and say 'keep it'. I want an explicit answer before I write it into Mathilde's psyche. - Don't worry too much about trying to work expenses around each other, if you end up going into the negatives a bit as a cumulative result of this set of votes I'll allow you to repay it with future income without penalty.

Turn 40 - 2489.5 - Start Slow...

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [DEBT] Pay in coin [*] [LIBRARY] Colleges of Magic: Rituals, Rune Magic, Liminal Realms, Forest Spirits [*] [PURCHASE] No purchase. [*] [DWARF] No purchase. [*] [COLLEGE] No purchase. Tally After considering your options and being tempted by some of the only moderately dubious ones, you dismiss them. The debt was for gold, you'll pay gold. You've done some bad things in the name of necessity before and undoubtedly you'll have to do so again in the future, but here and now you have the luxury to do what is right. All that's left to do is to find out where you can find Gotrek's widow, and come to think of it, you should probably stop referring to her as 'Gotrek's widow'. You check your notes for her name and mentally rephrase: you'll give the gold to Gotrek's widow- Moving very carefully, you turn back to the notes and reread the name, watching your own thoughts process it. It's Helga - you recognize that, so it's not that the name isn't being remembered, it's that it's not registering as the proper label for that individual. The phrase 'Gotrek's widow' is... overruling it? No, not so dramatic. It's more like you're considering it the more proper way to mentally refer to them, the same way you think of Max as Max instead of Magister Maximilian de Gaynesford. And once you identify that it's an increased conceptual emphasis rather than anything more insidious, it's not hard to guess why the title of 'widow' has accreted more weight. You incurred a debt to this woman on the steppes of Kislev, after all. The only question is whether it's just happenstance, the metaphysical equivalent of tracking mud in on your shoes, or whether it's the sign of some sort of actual external attention. You cast your senses around and detect nothing out of the ordinary, but you know that doesn't really tell you much. Your Magesight is good, but it's not good enough to spot the mere attention of a God if they don't want it to be spotted. Now doubly glad you decided as you did, you make your way down Karag Nar towards where - you make a mental effort - to where Helga has recently set up her business at ground level. That there's only a faint whiff of blood and sawdust in the air speaks well of her standards of cleanliness, and the inside is all clean bare stone and racks of gleaming steel implements. The woman herself is tanned and has short dark hair hanging loose around her ears, and though partially hidden by a clean apron, the long dagger on her waist seems very unlike a surgical implement. "What can I do for you, Lady Magister?" she asks, her Reikspiel bearing a trace of an Ostermark accent as she looks you over. "Your lot usually get each other to sort out your problems. Haircut then, is it?" You frown at the idea. Your hair has gotten rather long, but it's not often you hear a Dwarf talk of cutting it as anything but an insult. "I'm not here as a customer. During the Karag Dum Expedition I incurred a debt to Borek Forkbeard, who now seeks the Path of Grimnir and has passed that debt on to you, in gratitude and sorrow for Gotrek Gurnisson's part of the Expedition." You place a large and rather ungainly bag of gold coins on a bench with a chorus of clinking, and she approaches the bag dubiously and her eyes widen at the contents. Even for a skilled and accredited physician that much gold represents several decades of income. She seems rather taken aback, and after processing the sight for a few moments she simply says "Thank you, Lady Magister." That somewhat takes you aback - Dwarves don't thank someone directly for repaying a debt, as thanks could imply that there was ever any doubt of it being repaid. Instead they would express gratitude in roundabout ways like thanking the promptness of the repayment or their gladness to have assisted in the first place. But that's not really true, is it? You take a moment to properly formulate the truth of the matter in your mind: Dwarves adhering to the mainstream culture of the Karaz Ankor act in that way. But Helga is an Imperial Dwarf, and Clanless besides, and even when moving to a Karak she's taken a home within the human quarter of it. Looking around the room you can see a shrine to Shallya tucked away in a corner, and while there is an icon to Valaya on one of the walls, it's no larger or more prominent than the one to Groplotta, the Halfling Goddess of Herbalism. "You're quite welcome," your mouth has been continuing while you thought. "Without Gotrek's machines, the Expedition would have been much less likely to achieve what success it did." "And once he built them, he wasn't going to let them go on their quest without him," she says with a deep sigh, passing a hand over her face - a Morrite salute used when speaking of a deceased loved one, in the hopes that He has taken them to His realm. "He never was the sort to do anything halfway." She snorts in sudden, bleak mirth. "Gurna would be a bastard if he was." You don't know how to respond to that, so you don't. --- Your first tentative steps into researching the Waystones have been somewhat promising, but more than that, they've been eye-opening. Your mapping of the nexuses of the Empire has indicated that while things might not be quite as dire as you feared, the ability to continue distinguishing between the eastern Old World and the encroaching Chaos Wastes is the transmitting of magical energy through Marienburg and Athel Loren - two polities that can be rather difficult, to put it lightly. You'd guess that if you briefed the Council of State on this, the first follow-up question they'd have is about whether it would by possible to bypass them, and right now the best answer you could give is that Ulthuan seems to be capable of doing so. An answer that would likely be better received is one that either put forward the possibility of reactivating a nexus in southwestern Reikland, or erecting entirely new Waystones in a chain along Axe Bite Pass or the Gisoreux Gap. Possibly multiple chains in parallel to manage the throughput that would be required. But that's rather getting ahead of yourself, because on the topic of erecting entirely new Waystones, you have the revelation that something inside of the current network is capable of disapproving of your meddling with the network. That leads you to the choice of trying to negotiate with Ulthuan or Naggaroth for a way to communicate with that intelligence, or making a new method of magical transmission from scratch to feed into the existing network without needing it to approve of your efforts. You also have a number of possibilities for creating tributaries, which has the exciting possibility of turning into a theological minefield as most of the promising possibilities rely on the intercession of Gods or other ephemeral beings. The Empire has a lot of fine qualities, but widespread agreement on theological matters are not among them. Still, if it was going to be easy, you wouldn't have had to spend so much time gathering together resources and expertise from throughout the Old World. You have five action points (AP) you can apply without engaging in overwork. For every two AP spent across all members of WEB-MAT, including recruiting new members, you can spend one 'free' additional AP with any member of WEB-MAT. WEB-MAT actions are performed by Mathilde alongside that person when possible, such as studying something alongside that person, cowriting a paper together, one teaching the other, both of them learning something new, et cetera. Current overwork status: [-] [ ] [ ] Each box will be filled by one action of overwork, and will take the two turns after that to fade as you recover. The first box incurs no penalty. The second will give a -10 penalty to all actions during the first turn of recovery. The third will give a -20 penalty to all actions on both turns of recovery. Overwork incurs no penalties on the turns taken, only on the turns recovering from it. You can take as many actions of overwork as you have unfilled boxes. When you use overwork it fills the left-most empty box, so [-][ ][ ] becomes [-][+][ ], not [+][-][ ]. All boxes recover in parallel and independent from one another, but second and third apply maluses on your actions during that cooldown period. WEB-MAT: Magister Maximilian de Gaynesford, Gold Wizard [ ] MAX: Learning: specify what and from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] MAX: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] MAX: Receive dictation: specify which two papers or one book will be written. WEB-MAT: Magister Johann, Gold Wizard [ ] JOHANN: Learning: specify what and from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] JOHANN: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] JOHANN: Write a paper: specify which. WEB-MAT: Lord Magister Egrimm van Horstmann, Light Wizard [ ] EGRIMM: Attempt a Windherder enchantment with Egrimm (specify what) [ ] EGRIMM: Learning: specify what from who. You may pay for a trainer. [ ] EGRIMM: Study an artefact: specify which. [ ] EGRIMM: Write a paper: specify which. WEB-MAT: Other [ ] WEB-MAT: Hunt an apparition with a member of WEB-MAT (specify who and which) [ ] WEB-MAT: Attempt to recruit someone to WEB-MAT (specify who) [ ] WEB-MAT: Enchant or otherwise modify your Gyrocarriage (specify how) The Waystone Project, Recruitment [ ] Attempt to bring an Order into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a non-Order magical tradition into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a human Cult into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a Major House or Ward into the Waystone Project (specify which) [ ] Attempt to bring a Karak's Runesmiths into the Waystone Project (specify which) The Waystone Project, Research [ ] Waystone: Capstone [ ] Waystone: Runes [ ] Waystone: Foundation [-] Waystone: Build an Elven Waystone Requires Capstone, Runes, Foundation, and Leylines to be fully and successfully completed. [ ] Waystone: Nexuses Specify which: Marienburg (Almshoven and Fort Solace), Forest of Shadows (Brass Keep, Blood Fane, Tower of Melkhior), Reikland (Axe Bite Pass and Grey Lady Pass), Mordheim, Los Cabos, Bugman's Brewery. [ ] Waystone: Tributaries Specify which type: Scythian, Lornalim. [ ] Waystone: Mapping Specify two of: Bretonnia, Tilea, Estalia, Araby, Badlands. [ ] Waystone: Other Networks Specify which: Karaz Ankor, Kislev, Laurelorn, Athel Loren, Nehekhara. The Waystone Project, Development (NEW) [ ] Waystone: Tributary Design (select one or multiple: Ranaldian, Druidic, Ice Witch, Runesmith, Teclisean) [ ] Waystone: Tributary Prototype (select one or multiple: Dreaming Wood tributary, Haléthan tributary, Bereginya tributary) [ ] Waystone: Leyline Prototype (select transmission medium: Air, Material, River) [ ] Waystone: Leyline Keyphrase Negotiation (select one: Ulthuan, Naggaroth) For the above options, as well as any option-specific specifications, also state who you will be researching this with. You can specify as many or as few members of the Project as you please, as well as bringing in people from outside the Project if you pay for their services or convince them in some other way. If the only ones involved are members of WEB-MAT the action can count as a WEB-MAT action. In general the fastest progress will be made by involving only those with the most applicable knowledge, but also keep in mind how each individual might feel about being included or excluded in a particular investigation. Lovely Laurelorn [ ] Explore the wonders of the ancient and beautiful city of Tor Lithanel. [ ] Explore one of the Wards of Laurelorn (specify which: Storm, Rain, Frost) Self-Improvement: [ ] Receive training: specify who and what. (acquaintances may train you for free, or you can hire someone with money or favours) [ ] Attempt to learn Battle Magic at the Grey College. (1 College Favour per attempt) [ ] Attempt to gain control of one of your Arcane Marks (specify which) [ ] Try to see through Pall of Darkness with your improved magical senses. [ ] Practice shooting while invisible. (applies to Substance of Shadow and Invisibility) [ ] Branulhune's ability to disappear and reappear at a thought allows entirely new forms of combat. Continue to work on them. [ ] Attempt to finish off the Grey College spellbook by learning Shadow of Death, Cloak Activity, and the MAPP. Research and Publishing: [ ] Study an artefact: select which. [ ] Write a paper: select which. [ ] Write something else: write in. Once per turn, you can write a paper or write a 'something else' without spending an action thanks to your Tower of Serenity. [ ] The Second Secret of Dhar teaches how to collapse it upon itself. Practice upon local Dhar taint, and very cautiously see if this works with Warpstone. Aethyric Vitae (19 gallons): [-] Create Orbs of Sorcery solo (requires one of each Power Stone) (insufficient CF) Mathilde will have full control over what happens with the resultant Orbs, including the option of presenting the full collection as a shockingly impressive fait accompli. Any Power Stones Mathilde does not have will be acquired for 5 CF each. [ ] Create Orbs of Sorcery with College buy-in (no cost) Mathilde will not have to source her own materials, but will have to negotiate in advance what happens with the resultant Orbs. [ ] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to being subjected to power stone creation methods. [ ] Using the secrets you already know of the Vitae, attempt to weaponize it. Enchantment and Spell Creation: [ ] Enchant an item: specify what and how (current skill level allows for Fiendishly Complex spells and lower; you may use Windherder to attempt to enchant something with spells from different Winds) [ ] Attempt to create a spell (see Approved Spells threadmark) [ ] Attempt to codify Rite of Way so that others can learn it. [ ] Attempt to capture an Apparition (optional: specify which) [ ] Turn a staff (specify for whom) (optional: specify from what) Foreign Relations: [ ] Involve yourself in current affairs: specify what and how. Current examples: Eastern Stirland pacification, Marienburg affair, Black Waters project [ ] [ ] [ ] Travel to Nagarythe at the invitation of Ambassador Daroir, and join their eternal war against Naggarothi invaders for three months. Personal Relations: [ ] Spend time assisting or ingratiating yourself with someone else: specify who and how. [ ] Spend time investigating a character without their knowledge: specify who. [ ] Teach Eike (specify what) [ ] Wolf is fully grown, very smart, and a Very Good Boy. Train him further. (specify what he will be taught) [ ] Wolf is fully grown and very magical. Deepen your familiar bond. (may unlock a new familiar ability; risks obsession) The Eastern Imperial Company Your share of EIC profits: 200 crowns / turn Current Focus of the EIC: Eastern Stirland EIC Handler: The Hochlander The first AP spent in this category is free. Any additional choices cost 1 AP. [ ] EIC: Completely hand over management of the EIC intelligence apparatus to the Hochlander. [ ] EIC: Found an auditors division, to make sure the ledgers are in order. [ ] EIC: Insert agents into a particular province, cult, company, or institution to start gathering their secrets. (specify who) [ ] EIC: Reach out to Roswita, and have the EIC start passing on tips about any tax evasion or other naughtiness by the EIC's rivals. [ ] EIC: Improve and expand the EIC's paramilitary river navy. (optional: specify how) [ ] EIC: Have the EIC keep tabs on mercenaries so that they can be more easily hired if needed. [ ] EIC: Gather as much Ithilmar from throughout the Old World as possible to resell to the Eonir for a one-time profit (NEW) [ ] EIC: Attempt to establish a trade route with the Eonir (pick one: spices, ore, charcoal) (NEW) [ ] EIC: Negotiate and plan a magical route through the Schadensumpf to allow for easier trade with the Eonir without compromising their defences (NEW) Kron-Azril-Ungol Status: Being colonized by a new We, not yet open to the general public. The first AP spent in this category is free. Any additional choices cost 1 AP. [ ] Go about recruiting an army of scribes so you can start copying entire libraries of material. [ ] Seek the publishing contacts to start acquiring large amounts of books from a nearby realm (specify which: Bretonnia, Kislev, Tilea/Estalia, Araby) Gives wide and easy access within a language, but is subject to local restrictions and is a less efficient use of the Library's acquisition budget than other methods. [ ] Seek an exchange arrangement with another Library or a Karak's archives to be able to make copies of their corpus (specify which, eg: Great Library of Marienburg, Great Library of Altdorf, Ancient Library of Carroburg, Karaz-a-Karak Archives, Karak Vlag Archives) Difficulty will depend on the size, prestige, and disposition of the library in question, and the relative impressiveness of Kron-Azril-Ungol. [ ] Seek an agreement with a Cult to have access to their libraries (specify which, eg: Verenans, Myrmidians, Sigmarites) Difficulty will vary heavily depending on the Cult in question, but can allow access to rare tomes and esoteric subjects. [ ] Set up a no-questions-asked bounty system for books within the Cult of Ranald Results will be unreliable and depending on what is sought may result in blowback, but this may allow you to acquire books that would otherwise be entirely inaccessible. Apprentice Eike Hochschild Specify which of the above actions Eike will be present for and (hopefully) learning from, as well as what she will be directed to study when she's not doing so. Her study may involve lessons you pay for, or tutoring from your employees and allies. These do not cost AP. [ ] Eike Actions: [ ] Eike Study: Ranald's Coin - specify which face it will be set to [ ] The Gambler: specify an action this will apply to. A +20 bonus to up to two dice rolls resulting from a single chosen action. [ ] The Night Prowler As long as you are outside of private property and within a town or city, nobody will question your presence and nobody will be able to find you if you do not wish them to. [ ] The Deceiver: specify how this will be used. Lies you have developed beforehand will be delivered perfectly. The listener may believe you to be mistaken, but they will never believe that you are lying. Cannot be used to tell truths. [ ] The Protector When you act in a way that defends an individual or group from a danger that you did not cause, they will become aware of what you have done and will believe you acted selflessly in doing so. Rule of thumb: if you have to explain why this might apply, it probably doesn't. [ ] The Father Ranald's daughters, and Their followers, will recognize you as being worthy of trust and faith. Spoiler: Accumulated Artefacts Ranald's Coin (note from Ranald: don't) Vampire skulls Branulhune - investigate the odd flash when it is desummoned underwater Books and rubbings from an Asur explorer of Lustria and the Southlands The Vampire Prophecies of W'Soran Vlad von Carstein's study notes of the Carstein Ring Ghyran Nut Kurgan Shrine to Mannsleib Kurgan enchanted weapons Spoiler: Potential Papers Note: Fresh and Refreshed papers confer a +10 bonus; faded ones a -10 malus. Papers get one step less 'fresh' each turn: Fresh; Fading; Mostly Faded: Faded. Only the first and last have an effect on the diceroll. Observations on the Windfall north of the Dark Lands (FADED) Comprehensive notes on possible terrain obstacles (FADED) Waaagh energy and magic witnessed during the Expedition (FADED) The Black Orc Warboss' worship of Only Gork, and what you saw of the Rogue Idol ritual (FADED) Preliminary paper on Aethyric Vitae (TIMELESS) Coins of Nehekhara's Fifth Dynasty (TIMELESS) You can literally write the book on a topic for the same amount of effort as two papers; this can be split over multiple turns. You don't need to have all the pieces to do so, but it would be more efficient and impressive if you did. Windsoak Mushrooms (missing: Chamon, Shyish) (2/3 completed) The Currency of Strygos The Currency of Tylos Coins of Nehekhara's Fourth Dynasty Coins of Nehekhara's Sixth Dynasty - There will be a 18-hour moratorium. Voting will be in plan format. - The point of the Apprenticeship system is that it lets Apprentices learn without being significant drains on the time and efforts of their Master. Eike has been trained to the point that she can tag along on most endeavours and make herself useful enough to make up for time spent explaining things to her. As long as Eike is being brought along on at least one action per turn, you are meeting what the Colleges would consider to be your minimum obligations to her as your Apprentice. Whether Mathilde is to exceed that minimum, and if so by how much, is entirely a personal decision, not a matter of obligation. - I'm deliberately keeping the options for Eike's self-direction vague and open-ended because this is not something Mathilde will be closely monitoring. Instructions can be simple, like 'study diplomacy', or as complicated as 'study music theory and learn Khazalid in preparation for being taught Dwarven War Yodeling'. I will not penalize Eike for being given a series of ultraspecific six-month cram sessions instead of a balanced syllabus.

Turn 40 Results - 2489.5 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Plan Ritual Blunderbuss -[*] JOHANN: Explore the wonders of the ancient and beautiful city of Tor Lithanel -[*] MAX: Receive dictation: Windsoak Mushrooms (3/3), Waaagh energy and magic witnessed during the Expedition -[*] Waystone: Nexuses (Reikland) (Max, Egrimm, Johann) -[*] Waystone: Runes (Hatalath, Sarvoi, Elrisse, Egrimm, Thorek, Tochter) -[*] Waystone: Tributary Prototype (Wood tributary, Haléthan tributary, Bereginya tributary) (Max, Tochter, Zlata, Cadaeth, Aksel, Niedzwenka) --[*] The Gambler -[*] Investigate how the Vitae reacts to being subjected to power stone creation methods. -[*] EIC: Attempt to establish a trade route with the Eonir (spice) -[*] KAU: Go about recruiting an army of scribes so you can start copying entire libraries of material. -[*] SERENITY: Write a paper: Comprehensive notes on possible terrain obstacles -[*] Eike Actions: Explore the wonders of the ancient and beautiful city of Tor Lithanel, Receive dictation, EIC action -[*] Eike Study: Petty Magics Tally When I had agreed to join the Grey College, I had thought that the teachings it would offer would give me some form of insight into Mathilde Weber, the woman who appeared in my grandmother's stories alternating between an adorably earnest youth far out of her depth, and a terrifying and mysterious force of nature whose actions could only be fully understood in retrospect. In this I was to be swiftly disillusioned, for the stories I heard from those who theoretically should have far greater insight were just as confusing. It seems that from the perspective of the Grey College, a promising young Journeywoman had disappeared into the mountains and emerged years later completely transformed, in something of an echo of the meteoric rise of the current Supreme Patriarch. Were it not for the steady stream of papers on every topic imaginable that had emerged from the strange and deadly Badlands, the question may have arose as to whether they were the same person at all. That said, enough study did allow for commonalities to emerge that gave me some glimpse of the woman that gave rise to the stories. All of them agree that she is fiercely loyal to those close to her, that she is in possession of, if not possessed by, an endless curiosity that flits and flies as freely and as mercilessly as a pegasus. All agree that to call her a staunch ally of the Dwarves is, if anything, insufficient to describe how much she has made herself at home amongst beings who normally treat humans with at best condescending tolerance. They describe a woman who is at best serviceable at diplomacy, who nonetheless regularly achieves diplomatic coups that would be thought impossible had it occurred to anyone to previously consider them at all. They describe a woman who is as able to infiltrate as any Grey Wizard, but who unveils herself with a runic greatsword cleaving through a neck instead of with a dagger being buried in a spine. In short, they give few solid answers and many reasons to become even more curious. So when the Lord Magister had taken it upon herself to be my Master, my hopes for understanding were raised once more. The first thing she revealed to me was a redemption of the unredeemable, and then she took me across the continent to explore the home city of a mysterious and staunchly isolationist people who were recently on the brink of war with the Empire, where she appears to be considered an honoured guest. It seems my number of unanswered questions is doomed only to rise. --- Atop the roof of the palace of House Yavanna, ensconced within an attic of glass, row after row of plants in the very bloom of health grow. Some of their shapes hint that they once they might have been siblings to plants that can be found at dinner tables across the Empire, but the attentions of the Fay Folk of Laurelorn have so strengthened their properties that I found myself beginning to grow lightheaded from the overwhelming melange of scents that they gave off. Others were completely alien to me, either originating solely within Laurelorn or having been brought over from the magical isle of Ulthuan thousands of years ago, or perhaps being born entirely of magic instead of owing any kind of debt whatsoever to the natural world. "I am not here as a client to a patron," my Master said, in a tone of voice that shapes reality as sure as her grasp of Ulgu. "I am here as a courtesy. If you don't take this deal, Sumier probably will. If neither of you do, Maeglin definitely will." "Are you suggesting that House Maeglin would assent to to Tor Lithanel becoming reliant on the Empire for sustenance?" replied the Elf archly, wary suspicion underpinning the condescension. "Of course not. Even Toriour are capable of eating unspiced food, and it's not like all this would wither away because a few bags of piper or crocus crossed the walls. All I want is for you to come to learn that there's more than danger in the world outside your forest." A very similar conversation occurred with the head of House Sumier, and then to light a fire under both sets of feet she had Magister Johann of the Gold Order distribute some of the hotter spices amongst the disciples of Asuryan and Vaul, who frequently boast of their ability to withstand extremes but had never encountered this precise variety of food outside those enhanced with a touch of Aqshy. Even among Elves magically-enriched food is too dear to be anything but an occasional treat, and so the possibility of the same effect becoming available through a pinch of only moderately exorbitant powder garnered interest from these influential corners. Thus was the trap set: two isolationist Houses who currently shared control of Tor Lithanel's spice markets staring mistrustfully at each other, each knowing that even if both of them refrained from allowing in this foreign interloper, the amenable hedonists of House Maeglin would leap at the chance to intrude on the millennia-old duopoly. It is here that I began to understand part of my Master's contradictory reputation. When she engages in diplomacy, she does not do so in the traditional means and methods of diplomats and ambassadors. In a world of circuitous maneuvers she charts a course directly towards her intended destination. When such methods fail, they are the hallmark of one completely inept at diplomacy; when they succeed, they alter the very course of history. In the end, House Yavanna broke first, and from there it was all trivial logistics. Spices from the West we would do no better than breaking even on, as our best source was to buy from the markets at Altdorf. This troubled me at first, but my Master pointed out that it is better for this to be no real loss to lose, as both Marienburg and Ulthuan could trivially undercut it. It is spices from the East where profit is to be made, as the EIC is able to take their pick of spices from Ind and Cathay as they pass through Karak Eight Peaks, before any other middlemen have a chance to take their cuts. Politically, the inevitable result of this is that House Sumier will slander their former isolationist ally as a collaborator with the humans, pushing House Yavanna into the orbit of the loyalists and further tilting the political scales in the direction of peace. It is a total victory on all fronts for my Master, and one that I took embarrassingly long to spot the heart of. For this was, in truth, a victory of intelligence: the day was won not because she arrived in Tor Lithanel with a bag of kardamon, but because she was able to identify who could be made to want it, and who could be made to need it. --- My Master's first foray into academia was at the age of twenty-six and seems to have been prompted by necessity, as it served as her masterpiece to attain the rank of Magister. Whether this was an artefact of her own Master or her unusual Journeying, or something she considers to have been a failing on the part of her younger self, I can only speculate, as she has thrown me straight into it by having me sit in on and read along with her latest works. This is with the assistance of her frequent collaborator, Magister Maximilian of the Gold Order, a man whose personality and affectations make it difficult to take him seriously until one sees him with a hammer or quill in his hand. From dusty and voluminous notes taken during the initial reconquest of Karak Eight Peaks they intend to wring out any insight that may be found into the bizarre energies of Waaagh Magic, a topic that my Master's expertise has already led her to deliver a series of lectures to an audience drawn from all corners of the Old World. It was a privilege to be a spectator to the nostalgic recollections that the initial readthrough of their old notes prompted, as they discussed their perspectives of the Battles of Karag Lhune and Karag Nar. To me more so than to my Master, perhaps, as Magister Maximilian was quite sidetracked by some insight he seemed to have stumbled over regarding one of his signature spells, and from then on the notes and dictation he took were marred by Chamonic equations and sketches of crossbows in the margins. His distraction would prove to be my opportunity, as it gave me the opportunity to interject my own questions until the conversation became something of a lecture to an audience of one. I did, I must admit, feel some guilt for having so selfishly diverted the attention of a Lady Magister to my own ends, but if there is one garnered insight into the nature of my Master that I feel quite confident of, it's that she has no aversion to the sound of her own voice. Many days passed with only the most minute amount of progress made on the paper itself, but each word unwritten upon paper was insight delivered unto myself. I believe I can now boast to have developed the beginning of an understanding of the strange energy of the Waaagh, those that sit astride the line between Arcane and Divine, as belligerent in its defiance of categorization as the beings themselves. [Mathilde's contribution: Learning, 69+29+4(Library: Waaagh Magic)-10(Faded)=92.] [Max's contribution: Learning, 3+18+4(Library: Waaagh Magic)-10(Faded)=15.] [Eike's supervision: Learning, 90+13+4(Library: Waaagh Magic)=107.] [Observations on Waaagh Phenomena During the Karak Eight Peaks Expedition, 2489. Subject: Uncommon, +0. Insight: Agreement, +0. Delivery: Dull, -1. Thorough, +1. Varied, +1. Accessible, +1. Tactically Relevant, +1. Total: +3.] Would that the other writing project was as captivating. There was in progress a book on a variety of mushroom that was apparently capable of storing the Winds, and could be eaten to deliver the stored energy to a Wizard so they could harness greater power than they could usually manage. The only part of my exposure to this I was able to find any interest in at all was trying one of the Ulgu varieties for myself, which proved quite invigorating - if hubris is not an as yet undiscovered side effect of the mushroom, I believe I may be capable of casting a true spell of Ulgu. For the rest of the time, I exercised my willpower to remain conscious while they revised paragraph after paragraph to try to batter a previous draft into something less soporific. That they eventually succeeded, delivering a slimmer and much more readable volume in place of the previous doorstopper of a tome, was as impressive a feat as it was as welcome a mercy. My Master seemed similarly relieved. [Writing the book on Windsoak Mushrooms, Learning: 61+29+7(Library: Sevir)+5(Library: Chemistry)=102.] [Max's contribution: Learning, 34+18+10(Patient)=62.] [Eike's supervision: Learning, 11+13=24.] [Thaumomycology, 2489. Subject: Rare, +1. Insight: Revolutionary, +2. Delivery: Compelling, +1. Thorough, +1. Varied, +1. Exotic, +1. Useful, +1. Shared Credit, -1. Total: +7.] --- Now that I had enough grasp of Ulgu to control my intake of Winds and had learned the basics of manipulating it without provoking it into restiveness, I could begin to learn to shape it into the simplest of spells. The first few sessions were under my Master's supervision, and to literally 'roll up my sleeves' and reveal that Ulgu had seen fit to grant me its Mark was quite gratifying, and gives me a glimpse of what motivates my Master to act as she does. She did seem surprised, though what else she may have felt is beyond my ability to perceive. Dare I hope she is impressed? Would pride push me to wish for jealousy? She herself is, of course, as festooned with Marks as one would expect of a Lord Magister, but though flame, smoke, and shadow all bend to her presence, I have neither heard or seen anything to suggest that Ulgu has blessed her in the same way. That is, of course, not entirely indicative - there are several tales of questionable origin that tell of Runes placed atop or aside various anatomical features in unfortunate ways that would make most think twice about displaying for the general public. In any case, at long last it was my time to wield, rather than merely channel, the Grey Wind. I had previously imagined all sorts of trying scenarios in which I might be called upon to first partake of the Lore of Shadows, but my Master is no wandering hedge witch for whom a dingy tavern is the best sanctum that could be hoped for. In a room as soaked with Ulgu as the Grey College itself and bolstered with the wisdom of a library to rival any I've seen, I breathed deep of the Wind I had come to know so well and prepared to bend it to my will. [Studying Spells: Learning, 63+13+20(Grey Tower)+5(Library: Ulgu)=101.] It was everything I'd dreamed. For all that I'd been warned that magic was never more than an errant thought away from betraying those whom it dwells within, it leapt to my fingers at a thought and almost seemed to divine my intentions before I even thought to impose them. It was as natural as walking, as instinctive as breathing, and as satisfying as a balanced ledger. Within days I'd begun to turn metaphorical shadow into literal light, and by the end of the month I'd learned to both imbue it into objects and to incarnate and command it to move according to my whim. [Studying Spells: Learning, 4+13+20(Grey Tower)+5(Library: Ulgu)=42. Rolling for miscast.] It was, with the benefit of hindsight, exactly the thing to lure a gifted nascent mage into overweening confidence. With light conquered, I thought it would be simplicity itself to move on to sound, but I knew my error as soon as the magic snarled in my fingers and transformed into something I had little knowledge of and less control over, and my only recourse was to ground the energies. But they grounded themselves, unleashing a wave of transformative energy that washed over everything around me. It wasn't until I had scoured the room and inspected every corner of my person that I finally accepted I had suffered no worse than an upset stomach, and for the remainder of my study time I returned to my Master's books to strengthen my grasp of the theoretical before I tried to turn my grasp to the ephemeral. But I would soon be wrenched away from my study, as my Master intends to deepen her understanding of the strange folk of Tor Lithanel, as well as lay the foundation of my own. --- What part of Tor Lithanel will Mathilde encourage the impressionable Eike to pay close attention to, if anything? [ ] Politics [ ] Culture [ ] Economy [ ] Language [ ] Military [ ] Eike's choice [ ] Other (write in) Eike has learned: Diplomacy: Eonir of Laurelorn (1/3) Magic: Waaaghbane (2/5) Glowing Light Marsh Lights Spoiler: Eike's charsheet Diplomacy: 7+1+1-2=7 Martial: ? Stewardship: ? Intrigue: ? Piety: ? Learning: 11+2=13 Magic: 1+1=2 Traits: Grey Wizard: She has the ability and education to wield the winds of Ulgu, the grey magic of shadow and illusion. Apprentice: She has reached the level of training where she is able to begin learning the simplest of spells. Her Master is Lady Magister Mathilde Weber. ??? ??? ??? Mark of Ulgu: She bears the Mark of Ulgu upon her right arm, signifying the claim that the Wind has laid on her soul. +1 Magic. Diplomacy: Colleges of Magic (1/3) Empire of Man: Under the tutelage of her grandmother, she has achieved a solid understanding of the provinces of the Empire. +1 Diplomacy Eonir of Laurelorn (1/3) ??? Martial: Fitness (2/3) ??? ??? ??? Pistols: She was taught to wield her grandmother's weapon of choice from a young age. +1 Martial Intrigue: ??? Stewardship: Accounting: As heir apparent of the EIC, she has been taught the arcane art of double-entry bookkeeping. +1 Stewardship Trade: She has a basic understanding of the endless flow of goods and gold that keeps civilization running. +1 Stewardship Piety: Old World Pantheon (Northern) (1/3) Old World Pantheon (Southern): Having grown up in the softer corners of the Empire, she is familiar with the more civilized of the Empire's Gods. Shallya (1/3) Learning: Economics (Old World) (2/3) Languages: Reikspiel Lingua Praestantia Tar-Eltharin (2/3) Magic: Waaaghbane (2/5) Spells known: Glowing Light Marsh Lights - There will be a two hour moratorium. - Some or all of the rest of Eike's charsheet will be revealed as Mathilde learns more about her. - Using Eike's PoV here is an experiment. I'm not sure yet whether it will continue in the future, but if it does, it will only be for Eike's part of the turns.

Turn 40 Results - 2489.5 - Part 2

Spoiler: Voting results [X] Culture Tally You're interested to see how Eike reacts to life within Tor Lithanel. It is a city that has all but eliminated the most basic forms of mortal suffering, as food grows freely from the trees and bushes that line the grand avenues of the city, and bunkhouses run by the Great Houses grant shelter to any Cityborn for the low price of a few murmured thanks. But for all their freedom from material needs, there is a sense of claustrophobia clinging to many of the Cityborn as they chafe at the dominance of the Great Houses. They're as practically unable to enter the ranks of the Great Houses as the average peasant is unable to join the Empire's nobility, but the nobility of Tor Lithanel also dominate the religious and economic sectors of the city. To pursue success in just about every practical pursuit means attempting to wrest a sliver of power from noble families that have had millennia to consolidate power. It's beyond question that some Cityborn flourish in these circumstances, pursuing their passions for their own sake instead of as a means to any end that might threaten the Great Houses. It's also beyond question that some resent what they see as a gilded cage, one that they can leave at any time but, if they do, they can never return to. Plenty do so, but others quail at permanently abandoning the safety of the only home they've ever known for the dangers of the Laurelorn. Some do their best to excel as a priest or a crafter in direct competition with the Great Houses, others pour themselves into cultural pursuits, but some amount of them are never able to find peace within the city, without ever being able to gather the courage to leave it. With food and shelter guaranteed, there is still suffering. Will she see this city as a paradise, and the languishing of those with stifled ambitions as a mere indulgence? Will she see it as an intricate torture, where the Elves live their long, long lives doomed to have everything they need except purpose? As a lesser societal evil to be disregarded until all the much greater ones can be defeated? Or will she not make any judgement at all, as a studier of beasts might observe and even feel pity for the plight of a preyed-upon animal without taking a moral stance on something she is not a part of and cannot change? You don't put the question to her quite so blatantly, of course. You simply tell her to pay attention as she trails behind you and Johann as he shares with you what he's learned of the myriad ways the Toriour spend their copious amounts of free time. Your first stop, of course, is to meet with the Asuryanic hopefuls who refine their skills and physique in hopes of earning glory at the festivals dedicated to Asuryan. They're not what you'd describe as the most inclined to deep thinking among the Elves you've met, but it would be a mistake to dismiss them as stupid, as it does take some amount of cleverness to achieve martial omnicompetence with any degree of success. Where things get complicated is when you look at the wider social context and notice the social circles built around these beings of muscle and skill like ivy growing on stone. There is, of course, the Cult of Asuryan and the court of the Queen, both of whom try to influence who will become Champion and cultivate a relationship with likely winners by extending resources to some and denying them to others. Less expected is the circle of enthusiasts who seem to treat the contenders for the title as characters in a play, cheering for some and throwing peanuts at others and constantly arguing with each other over who's most worthy of eventual victory. There are enough people engaged with this sort of activity on varying levels to have evolved into an ecosystem of its own. Some Elves offer tribute to their favourite in art or verse, others distribute competing screeds lauding or decrying particular candidates and inviting inevitable responses in kind, other still simply seek like-minded folk with whom to wax lyrical of their virtues. It is a strange and often worryingly intense phenomena, and now you know where to look for you begin to realize that you never go long without seeing someone wearing a symbol declaring their allegiance to one or another. Is this what Tor Lithanel has in place of street gangs? Well, no, because as you dig deeper with your eyes opened to an entirely new form of signalling between the Toriour, you learn that Tor Lithanel has street gangs. Or rather, client gangs made up of those in debt to, or desiring the favour of, one Great House or another, their allegiance marked by a particular cut of their silks, set of their jewels, or style of their hair. That the look can be achieved in a moment or two with the help of a hand mirror means that you don't so much see it everywhere, but when you do see it you tend to see a lot of it. Ostensibly public areas are often dominated by one group or another, and while they don't go so far as to muscle out members of other groups or demand a display of loyalty to their own, their numbers are a clear signal that if they were so inclined, they could. While this is not necessarily a form of political unrest within Tor Lithanel, it is a sign that if unrest does break out, it could escalate extremely quickly. Part of you is disappointed to find such base tribalism lurking under the surface of what had seemed so serene, but another part of you feels vindicated to see that even the Elves are prone to dividing themselves along those lines. Not even the kithbands are safe, as you discover that many of them are formed only of members of one side of the main political divide of the current era, tainting the apparent purity of purpose of these peculiar social groups. While you delve into the murkier side of the politics, you have Eike familiarize herself with those kithbands by introducing her to some of those that are dedicated to learning about and discussing their old neighbours and new allies of the Empire, making the learning process a little more two-way. In exchange for answering their questions about life as a human of the Empire, Eike is introduced to their other kithbands for their other interests, and in this way she is given access to a cross-section of the many ways that the people of Tor Lithanel express themselves. Just as you were, it doesn't take long for her to be struck by the melancholic note so common to Toriour art, and once she has enough time to organize her thoughts on the matter she approaches you on the topic. "Is there ever a point where things stop hurting for someone?" she asks you. "Beggars on the street and nobles in their castles both have parts of their life that hurt them, and so do the Toriour. Is there ever a point where you have enough of everything and you're just happy? Or is it that no matter how much you have, the things that hurt you still hurt you just as much?" "How do you measure suffering?" you ask. "Is a beggar pining for food hurting only as much as a noble pining for a greater fief?" This is partly rhetorical on your part, but this is a field of philosophy you're not very well-versed in. "Most Shallyans say that suffering that can kill you is more meaningful than suffering that can't," Eike replies slowly. "Is that in terms of objective measurement of suffering, or just a matter of triage?" She considers that. "I don't know," she admits. "There's a lot of Shallyan writings about it, but I didn't pay much attention to it. Maybe I should have." "I don't either," you say. "That's not our department, thankfully. Our remit is to keep the Empire intact and functioning, and I doubt either of us will see the day when the greatest threat to it is ennui." That doesn't seem to put the matter to rest in Eike's head, and she mulls it over for a while longer. "It used to be different," she finally says. "The Wards of Sun and Frost used to be almost as safe as Tor Lithanel was, so most of the Toriour that resented the Great Houses were a lot more likely to join the Faniour." "Which means that tensions were building up, because more of the belligerent Toriour were staying Toriour, because they didn't want to join the front line of a war against the Beastmen and the Forest Goblins and maybe against Nordland." "Nordland broke things in a lot of ways," she says, her brow furrowed. "Why couldn't they just stay on their side of the river?" "Because each individual Elector Count made choices that would bleed Tor Lithanel just a little bit and benefit themselves a lot. That sort of thing is easy to find justifications for. But one tiny little border infringement per human lifetime is a lot of accumulated slights to an Elven lifetime. Each little step towards the cliff's edge is harmless, except for the last one. And each Elector Count had a lot to gain by convincing themselves that their step was one of the safe ones, and would find themselves in a sea of troubles if they were the first Elector Count in centuries to not give the guilds and nobles what they'd come to see as rightfully theirs." "Couldn't the Elves have done something about it earlier?" "Should they have gone to war the moment the first tree was felled?" She frowns, examining the question for traps. "I suppose not." "Then the second? The fifth? The hundredth? Each time the Eonir complained, and each time the Elector Count said the right things and put a stop to the encroachments, but eventually they'd need a favour from this guild or that noble, or a new Elector Count would come to power, and they'd go around again. By the time the Eonir had recognized the pattern, it had become so established that any military action would be easy to see, and easy to present to the rest of the Empire, as an unprovoked attack. Neither side understood the other to realize the course they were on until they had gone too far along it to turn back." "That's why you're studying them," Eike says. "To stop that from happening." "Yes, that's the practical reason. But also because it can teach so much. When you learn how a completely different culture sees the world, you also learn to see the world in an entirely new way. You renew your appreciation for the good, and learn more of how to avoid the bad." Eike frowns as she considers that. You're not sure how much she's taking on board, but so far the signs look good. Skill acquired: Eonir, Advanced (1/2) [Rolling...] Eike has learned: Diplomacy: Eonir of Laurelorn: A period of immersion in Tor Lithanel during her teenage years gave her a solid understanding of the Eonir. +1 Diplomacy Diplomacy: Politicking 1/3 Tar-Eltharin (Eonir accent) --- In front of your selected group of experts, you sketch out the Waystone runes on a chalkboard. "First off, let's approach the runes as runes," you say to them. "I know my way around Eltharin but I wouldn't lay any claim to be a scholar of the language, so feel free to jump in if you have any further insight. Now, pyramids are a common motif in Eltharin runes - in the rune for 'Asur', of course, and in Avalu, Drome, Keldri, Tavlu, and Varinor, as well as a number of others. But these are all depicted with a flat top, not coming to a point. As for triangles in general, the closest I could find is Sethai, which is the wrong way around and assymetrical to boot. Maybe Ismuir if you lop off the bottom two thirds. The prospects for the diamond are even grimmer." Sarvoi nods. "They're too basic as shapes to encapsulate a rich concept. Combined, it might be a modified Avalu. With the top removed from the pyramid..." He frowns as he considers it. "The power of natural heirarchy?" "Or something along the line of 'Godless strength'," Hatalath muses. "The straight, clean lines rule out Fan-Eltharin or Druchast," you say. "Thorek, do they mean anything to your eye?" "It's similar to a set of runes sometimes used to refer to the fallen Karak Izril," he says dubiously. "Or an inversion of the rune for 'treasure vault', where the treasure is kept atop the mountain peak." "Could it mean something like..." you think for a moment. "Vault for treasure yet unacquired?" He frowns. "It's possible, but I can't see that being arrived at by many Dwarven hands. Treasure is hewn from the stone and delivered to a vault, unacquired treasure above the mountain makes no sense." Maybe it did once to Dwarves who were more willing to work with Elves and with magic, but you don't voice that thought. "Elrisse, what about High Nehekharan?" "A pyramid with nothing inside it isn't a pyramid, it's a thorn, and it means something like 'readiness'," she replies. "Nothing comes to mind for the diamond, though - maybe 'mast' if you really force it, which would give you a meaning of 'built to be ready to defend'." "I think the shapes are basic enough that you could tease a meaning out of them in any runic language," Egrimm says. "The similarities in their meanings are compelling, but all these languages are related, it could simply come from the fact that the root concepts are similar, rather than this specific combination of shapes having a transcendent meaning." You frown, thinking. "Or even that we all live in the same world, so we're drawing from the same set of physical phenomena to find shapes with compelling meanings. Okay, let's consider the shape outside the context of language. Assume the droplet shape is just a droplet shape. What does that represent?" "An imbuement with the properties of water?" Egrimm guesses. "Physical or metaphorical?" Elrisse asks. "Either, I suppose," he replies after a moment of thought. "Water moves downhill whenever it is able," Thorek muses. "At first glance, a good fit for the purpose. But it comes with too much baggage. Water also transforms in response to the environment, which is something we don't really want here." "Don't we?" Sarvoi asks. "There's only one relevant transformation, and so far it seems the network has no problem shifting the result of it." "They're pulling some of it out before it reaches the Vortex, so they have to be preventing that," Hatalath says. "Possibly as simply as just keeping it in tightly-controlled conditions so it never encounters the impetus to transform." You nod as you jot down notes. "And metaphorical?" "Restorative and vital," Tochter suggests. "Water always returns to the ocean," Elrisse points out, "no matter how circuitous the route it takes to get there. Harnessing that pull of inevitability could be very potent." "Would it also be bringing in oceanic qualities?" Egrimm asks. "Not easily," Tochter says after a moment of thought. "It's a single droplet, it's water on a small scale. For ocean, you'd want a wave." "Or wouldn't, for this," Thorek points out. "You want it flowing to the end point, but not gathering there and starting to slosh about and ruining coastlines." "From a Sapherian mindset, we'd be thinking the Inner Sea, not the Great Ocean" Hatalath points out. "That's a much more benign set of associations." "Okay. What about the pyramid?" "The Diamond Throne?" Sarvoi suggests. "Either suggesting the literal Shrine of Asuryan on the Inner Sea to add an additional pull, or putting the entire thing under the authority of Him." "No, this was an entirely Hoethian affair. Asuryan was romping around the place whacking Daemons with a sword at the time," Hatalath says. "The Tower, then. Tavlu," Sarvoi ripostes. "Once again, we reach the problem that Elven pyramids are flat-topped," Hatalath responds patiently. "Could it be as simple as the pyramidion atop the Waystone?" Tochter asks. "Indicating the focal point for Winds absorption?" "If we consider the two runes together, that would make sense," Sarvoi says. "A raindrop falling directly upon the focal point." You frown. "A sympathetic model to be enforced upon itself. It seems too simple, but perhaps we're giving the ancients too much credit. Maybe they had to make it simple to deploy it so widely." "If the hard work is being done from the centre, it could be that all the fripperies of the Waystones themselves are just to help them along," Egrimm suggests. "It would explain how so many unruned Waystones were added to the network in the centuries after the Elves left these shores," Tochter said. "If it is that simple, then it'd be very testable. Hatalath, could you knock together a proof of concept based on this?" "Easily." "I'll ask that you do so, then." --- 'Easily' turns into 'hmm' turns into 'interesting' turns into months passing before Hatalath emerges once more, hauling a series of scale models made of varying materials. You're barely able to delay his expounding for long enough for everyone else to reconvene. "By itself, it just adds a little downwards turbulence to the ambient Winds," he says, pointing at the first, all-stone model. "It's a very minor effect for magical runes, but it's simple enough that it could be done by any competent stoneworker with a grasp of basic magical theory." "Which would have been relatively common for Ulthuan of old," Sarvoi observes. "More so than Archmages. Where it gets interesting is it has a compounding effect with other means of Wind conductivity," he points to the next one, "I used a core of wire to act as the channel, and the Runes alone gets a very steady trickle of ambient Wind movement. If we take as a given that the pyramidion alloy has better Wind-conductive properties than standard modern alloys, then we have a decent magical channel before we even start on the enchantments in the base or the connection to the wider network. The rest is refining the Runes - there's a point of diminishing returns for more potent and valuable materials, but silver seems to be a good middle ground." "It's a centralization of expertise," Elrisse says. "Have the Archmages, or the Smith-Priests of Vaul, or whoever put all their effort into forging the pyramidions, and then you can send them out with masons. I have a feeling that the bases will either be very simple, or will have a component that is very portable. This is how you dot a world with Waystones." You give the silver-runed model a suspicious look, wondering if this is too easy. But what Elrisse says makes sense - these things can be found in just about every corner of the world, they can't all have been hand-crafted by the greatest geniuses of a bygone era. [Waystone component completed: Runes.] - Most of this was written either on a train in the early AMs or in a crowded airport food court, so my apologies for any disjointedness in any of the above.

Turn 40 Results - 2489.5 - Part 3 - The Architecture of Fate

There is, you discover through trial and error, a minimum amount of Vitae required for you to be able to get an adequate 'grip' on the liquid so you can attempt to squeeze it into a power stone. You're uncertain as to whether this is because of the physical properties of the Vitae changing at differing amounts or if it's simply a matter of it needing to be big enough that you can see it clearly. You end up settling on a third of a gallon as a minimum size to achieve adequate control, and after you've grown familiar with the metaphysical weight of the liquid as you enforce your will upon it, you lift it with a gesture into the air, holding it in as perfectly spherical a shape as you can. Every distortion from that perfectly round shape signifies an unevenness in the willpower pressing in on the ball from each side, and having such plainly visible feedback makes it easier to refine your control than your experiments with power stones. You settle in, take a breath, and begin to squeeze. [Squeezing Vitae: Learning, 1+29=30.] For quite some time it remains stubbornly inert, and you have to fight off the worry that Vitae is as incompressible as mundane fluids. But after your attention begins to waver and you turn some of your attention away from the ball of shimmering fluid you drag in your wake so you can see to biological necessities, you notice that as your attention turns elsewhere, the ball grows a small but unmistakable amount. No, not grows - it decompresses. Reassured, you continue your vigil over the fluid and keep pushing in on what only seems to be unable to be pushed any further. With carefully-honed patience you maintain and very gradually increase the even pressure that keeps the shimmering sphere suspended in the air. And it disappears. After a moment of befuddlement and looking around the room in case you'd somehow missed the sudden addition of a great deal of agitated Winds, you scrutinize what you just saw and felt. It's more like it drained away extremely rapidly, the pressure sharply dropping to zero instead of instantly being gone. No, not gone. Growing more distant? But your will still grasps it from every spatial dimension, doesn't it? Well, every mundane spatial dimension. But there is another, isn't there? One you're intimately familiar with. The Vitae burrows into the fabric of reality, flashing and sparking into magic as it begins to transform, but in the instant of its transformation the energies disappear, replaced with an absence of pushback against your will that almost causes you to stumble. In the place of the shimmering ball of Vitae is a hole orthogonal to real and about the size of your hand, a slit carved in the wall that separates life from dream. And as you circle it, you can see the empty space within, a uniform greyness of the inside of the barrier that makes life possible. You've seen that shade once before - in the Grey College, in the room without walls that reveals its existence within a liminal realm. Either you've uncovered a very small liminal realm - about two cubic meters, by your estimation - that just so happened to be where you performed this experiment, or your experiment has created it. You peer through the hole, and begin extending the instruments you always have at hand for these sorts of experiments to gauge what's within. Temperature, normal. Air pressure, normal. Humidity, normal. Everything about the inside of this realm is entirely normal. Of all the various states of being, of the infinite variability of reality the Winds have apparently created new reality that is entirely typical for this place. So what does that indicate? That when forced into the barrier between reality and unreality, Vitae undergoes a transformation into... what, into nothing? No, into empty space where previously there was none. There's nothing there, but there is a there there to contain that nothing, where previously it was not. How? Well, Vitae was the substance of the realm of Aethyr, so transplanted to where there was no realm, it creates some more. But what you're looking it is certainly no Aethyr in miniature, is it? Well, no, you don't know the ground state of the Aethyr, you only know it as it is with the many Gods in residence. It could be that without them, the Aethyr would just be emptiness? But isn't the Aethyr inherently psychoreactive? This little pocket you've created doesn't appear to be. So it's not mimicking the Aethyr, it's instead mimicking reality? Could it have been imbued with... reality-ness from its time as Vitae? Or was this tiny, nascent realm of Chaos overwhelmed by the weight of a much larger reality through the pinhole that the Vitae had escaped through? No. You've tested Vitae in every way imaginable and know that it is unreactive, its nature unchanged from the moment it bled through into reality. This effect must rely on the inherent properties of the Winds it created. But that would mean that when Winds are presented with a blank slate and transform into a realm to fill it, they birth normality. But that makes no sense - the Winds are the energies of Chaos, aren't they? Well, no, not quite, that's why they're legal when Chaos Sorcery very much isn't. The Winds all represent facets of the real - life and death, light and shadow, passion and instinct, solidity and ephemerality. Mainstream theory is that this is the energies of Chaos having the nature of reality imprinted upon it when too far from the attention of the beings that command it. And there is no weight of reality here. Your lab is magically isolated from the outside world, and the Aethyr was forced into a space between realms before it transformed. Placed equidistant between real and unreal and isolated from the pressure of existence to impose a decision upon it, Aethyr still became Winds and the Winds still retained the nature of reality. Which means that the Winds can't be born of the mere inertia of what already is. Reality is being imposed upon Chaos by something other than reality. [Rolling...] "Do you know what tickles me most about all of this?" The thought arrives in your brain packaged and labelled as sound, but never existed as something so ludicrously inefficient as vibrating air. The past was simply changed so that the words had been heard. At the far side of the bubble of new space from the opening into reality, tendrils of magic wriggle through the thinned membrane that separates reality from unreality like maggots through dead flesh, and once they wriggle their way free they dissipate into will made manifest. "It's that every word I say will further excavate a warren of bad decisions that you will have to scurry your way through. Do you tell your little friends that you have thinned the one border of their reclaimed home that they cannot guard themselves? Do you tell them that you have been singled out for special attention by one of the Eyes of Tzeentch, the very one that once ensnared their brothers in the far north and began the twilight of their race?" It took only heartbeats for you to activate the Rune that flushes the magic out of the air, but entire sentences had already manifested themselves. "What about your little magic club? They've already fretted about this very possibility, haven't they? Can they distinguish between a few whispered words and a full ensnaring of a soul? Could they dare to take such a chance that one such as you might already be suborned when you have the trust and ear of so many? Of course not. You already know what their response would be, because you've already delivered it unto another. The blood on your hands matches that on the crown on your friend's head." How do you ignore words you never heard in a present tense? You do your best to focus on the whisking away of magical energies, and note that none are escaping the slit in reality you have created. Of course not. Magic bleed-off is the result of inefficiency in spellcasting, and this being is beyond such limitations. "Do you know how much effort it normally takes to craft a platter of truth and lies that will so haunt a mortal that they will spend the rest of their days trying their best to decorticate it? But you and yours who have so wonderfully usurped the Sword of Tlanxla have so twisted your own minds that I could say anything or nothing and you will dwell obligingly on it forever. If I said 'I like your hat' - and I really, really do - you will wonder, is this an example of the pettiest of statements for you to nevertheless obsess over, to demonstrate that I can command your mind through only your ears? Or am I making a deeper statement about how truly it pleases the Lord of Sorcery for a witch to wear the garb of those that would hunt her? Am I masking truth in lies, or lies in truth? Would it only be a truth if you decide it a lie, or only a lie if you decide it a truth? Or is eternal indecision that which I seek?" Once none remains in the air, the pull of potent runecraft exerts itself on everything within the room, including yourself. It's not exactly painful to have the magical energies that have become so much a part of you drawn forcefully out, but it feels like it should be. "The importance placed upon such pleasure, upon who has delivered them, grows by the hour. The First Betrayer sobs his fury for all to hear, knowing that the time will soon come again when he will crown one that might achieve what he could not and will never. Already the Four tally their joys and prod their servants, willing and not, knowing and not, into greater efforts. And do you know the most delightful part? That of all the promises and threats that have been whispered into the ears of the greatest and most terrible of champions, none have removed so many of their competitors from the greatest of tournaments as you." You stride towards the slit and gather your will and what scraps of Ulgu managed to cling to your soul. "You have heard for yourself how exquisitely cultivated the resentment within Egrimm is, and seen how convincingly soothed his ruffled feathers now appear. You have tasted the millennia of curdled hate of the Briarmaven of Woe, and struck her down when she left her beloved shadows to finally act. You have known how blind Alric is to the unsuitability that all else know and sneer at, and you have thwarted his ambitions and eliminated his last chance to claw his way back into relevancy. You have felt your blade sing as it sliced through the Elector Count that demanded respect for a title when he had no part in the killings that brought it to him, and the knowledge that the one that thwarted him is also the one that has propped up two generations of the dynasty that usurped him will burn within him until the burning is all that remains of him." You reach forward with your soul and bury talons of willpower into the newly-created fabric of reality. "And even now, my siblings bicker over whether you should be given credit that the brood that contained three generations of exquisite warlords that were so cleverly walked onto the precipice of apostasy, are now so utterly defeated that they will shriek and bite at any hand that reaches out for them, instead of allowing themselves to be properly usurped like their allies were." Tendrils of the purest magic burrowing through reality seep into your now magic-starved soul and your grip on reality redoubles and redoubles again. "Should you earn this world through right of conquest, your will here would be paramount. Not because you would be stronger than the Four, but because They want to see what you would do with it. They have worlds without counting where Their will becomes fact, and They have wrung every morsel of enjoyment out of such simple games. If you would take up the crown and with it make yourself the ultimate bulwark against Them, They would whisper and cajole and threaten and offer you every temptation to turn upon your wards, but every 'no' would be a rapturous novelty. All you'd need do to keep this world from their grasp is to stay true to your purpose. And is that not the founding purpose of your order? To be the 'no' in the darkness?" You don't even know where to begin rejecting the strength that even the slightest wisp of the energies of the Changer of Ways has given you, and even if you could, it would render you unable to do that which needs to be done. "Why do you think you were able to pull back so many of the generations born in Chaos from the Desolation Hold? Because the sweetest of victories was not those bludgeoned into submission and dragged off in chains, but those that would forge the chains themselves. A single sentry that walked into the darkness themselves and let the Maidens of Ecstacy have them delights the Four more than ten thousand who fight and bite and scratch and need their souls flayed down to the gristle before they obey." Already chewed through by the tendrils of magic, it takes only a few tugs for your empowered will-claws to force the newly-formed walls of reality to buckle and pucker. "When you can be sure of nothing else, be sure of the boredom of the Four. When they want puppets, they have as many of the likes of me as they could ever want. What they don't have is you. Should you be willing to change that, you could command any price. Every price." Scraps of reality's bloody flesh are pushed towards you by a sudden influx of the energies of the Aethyr, but they cannot flood freely into the world, because their point of ingress is contained within a bubble in the wall, and the only egress is the size of your palm. Like debris in a suddenly-narrowing river, as soon as one part of it snags it causes a pile-up of the rest, and in a moment a portal becomes a scarred pucker, holding fast against all that would press against it. This stops the tendrils, but it cannot stop the last whisper already planted in the past. "You cannot prevent the emergence of a Thirteenth, just as you cannot prevent the existence of Ulgu. All you can do is decide whether such a weapon should be surrendered without a fight to the whims of the vilest."

Turn 40 Results - 2489.5 - Part 4

After minutes that felt like hours crawl by without any indication of any sort of penetration attempt through the puckered wound in reality, you exhale and take a moment to gather your thoughts. Reality, you know, is hardy. If damage inflicted hung around indefinitely, there'd already be nothing left of it. Only the most horrifically grievous of injuries can be kept open indefinitely, and even that with continuous upkeep from one side or another, and without that upkeep or with any lesser injury reality is able to 'heal' over time. In this place, far above the bustle of life that attracts so many Winds and close to the Karak-Waystones that keeps ambient magic levels low, the damage you have inflicted is no worse than might be inflicted by a particularly exuberant miscast, which this structure was specifically placed and built to be able to withstand. So at the very least, you haven't actually blasted a Daemonic breach behind the Karak's defences, no matter what your undesired interlocutor implied. With that matter settled, you self-consciously straighten your hat as you consider the rest of the Daemon's words. That an Everchosen might be on the horizon is certainly alarming, but the Empire has never been safe from the possibility of a new one striding out of the wastes, and those with sense knew from the moment Asavar Kul fell that it was only a matter of time until another arrived. There's already been something of a ramping-up of readiness in response to increased cultist activity. The candidates that were specified... well it comes as no surprise that Alberich Haupt-Anderssen was in the running, and that does add context to his attempt to ingratiate himself to the Chaos Gods with a ritual of dedication, so that can be treated with no more than the regular amount of suspicion any words connected to the Plotter receive. What you know of Drycha does indicate there's little she wouldn't resort to in her insane quest for vengeance. Alric... well, at this point you're almost tempted to say that Chaos is welcome to him, and in any case, his claws are so thoroughly blunted by repeated failures to reburnish his good name that the risk he would pose is not significantly higher than any Black Magister. But Egrimm... You frown and sigh. You're supposed to doubt him, and then wonder if your doubt is what the Daemon actually intended, and then begin to treat Egrimm with an infuriatingly inconsistent mistrust, right? That's how this dance goes, isn't it? Well, nuts to that. If he was on the path to resentment-induced heresy, then the cure is for you to continue treating him as you've already been treating him: as a highly-skilled Wizard deserving of respect and acknowledgement. And if he isn't, then there's no reason to worry about it. And then there's you. Well, you don't particularly feel like being an Everchosen just because a living embodiment of lies and trickery tells you that you could do good with it, especially at the cost of burning every bridge you have and with absolutely no benefits or support up front. Morality aside, that offer is just insulting. Even the Druchii have done better. So though there's a part of your mind that does find the thought experiment intriguing - you flex your fingers and remember how much easier it was to exert your will with just a few ambient wisps of Tzeentchian energies - the feathery buggers are going to have to really up their game if they think they're going to sway you. So if you ignore the names that were so heavily dropped, where does that leave you? You're certainly not going to be able to command any sort of mobilization effort based on 'a Lord of Change told me', but you can add the information in more general form to the greater intelligence apparatus, which will be accumulating bits and pieces like that and will, eventually, reach the point where the omens are unmistakeable and the Empire - hopefully - will get its ducks in a row before half of Kislev is aflame. And if it turns out to be nothing - there's nothing to say that an Everchosen will always attack the Old World, and several theorists in the field believe that Naggaroth and Cathay have received the brunt of at least a couple - then those armies can go and proactively stamp out a few nascent lesser threats. There's always something out there that could use a taste of steel and gunpowder. As for the original experiment, while the objective was failed, and is unlikely to succeed unless you can find a sturdier reality to test it in, the results you did get are intriguing. On a theoretical level, that the Winds will, in as perfect a vacuum as can be devised, create a facsimile of reality blows a gaping hole in what was believed about their fundamental nature. As you were theorizing before you were so rudely interrupted, accepted wisdom says that reality exerts a sort of... reverse taint upon the energies of Chaos, which can be dislodged by extended distortion, reexposure to corruptive energies, or forced blending of different forms of Winds. Under this theory, Vitae that is made to detonate while equidistant to reality and unreality would never have been exposed to the taint of reality and so would form a copy of the Aethyr that birthed them. Or, if reality suffused one side of the barrier while unreality suffused the other... either a regular transformation into Winds, or an immediate curdling into Dhar, you suppose. But such suffusion is unlikely in your labs, isolated from both the density of life and emotion that attracts the Winds, and from the magical energies that bring closer the realm of Chaos. So for the Vitae to become Winds and then for the Winds to become reality means that reality is being imposed upon the Winds by something other than reality. You remember Cython theorizing about the similarity in nature between Gods and Winds, and wonder if it was more correct than it knew. Is this a product of divinity? Do the Gods collectively impose a sort of combined pastiche of their domains onto the world, creating forms of energy not connected with any of them individually but that does uphold the form of life that, in turn, sustains the Gods? Or is there some sort of hidden pantheon of God-Winds that are omnipresent throughout this world, so that the energies of the Aethyr that enter it are as under their command, just as the energies of the Aethyr around the conventional Gods becomes the divine energy with which miracles are worked? Or some other, stranger possibility? As for the results, well, the birthing of a pocket dimension is exciting news, and one thing you look for in a pocket dimension is the clear absence of Daemons, so you've hit a stumbling block right from the gate. But as a pocket of the liminal realm is by definition closer to the Aethyr than reality is, this cannot be a unique problem, and as you spent a decade of your life within a pocket dimension without ever being overrun by Daemons, it's one that must have a solution. Perhaps one not yet known to the Colleges, as Collegiate forays into the field are so far tenuous and prone to spontaneously extruding themselves, but you've always considered Collegiate knowledge more of a starting point than an ending one. Soothed by the comforting familiarity of magical theorizing, you've gathered the willpower to turn to the main topic at hand: disclosure. Though you've determined that you haven't actually exposed the Karak to any more danger than they had accepted when they gave you a home in it, most Dwarves would agree that courtesy dictates that you report the presence of a Greater Daemon inside a Karak, or the wounding of the barrier between said Karak and the realm of Daemons. Likewise, the Grey Order likes to be kept abreast of this sort of thing so they know to be on the lookout for any sudden penchant for feathers and coloured flames. But the price of those admissions would be an erosion of trust and repute that you have spent thirty years building. Perhaps not an irreversible one, but you already have a lot of demands on your time without having to reassure your allies of your reliability, and if your Collegiate and Dwarven contributors to the Waystone Project - currently the staunchest members - were to suddenly have reason to distance themselves, that could bring the entire Project into jeopardy. And as for the 'Everchosen' part... you have no idea what the procedure would be if a Wizard tells their superiors that they're in the running to be the next Asavar Kul. You'd like to think that the words of a Tzeentchian Daemon would be automatically disregarded, but the death or imprisonment of a single Wizard, even a Lady Magister, would be a ludicrously cheap price to pay to avert another Great War. And part of you knows you could do a better job of things than a mere upjumped steppe warlord if you put your mind to it. If it weren't yourself that would be on a chopping block, you're not entirely sure you wouldn't come down on the side of averting the risk. Report to Belegar: [ ] [BELEGAR] Nothing [ ] [BELEGAR] Greater Daemon [ ] [BELEGAR] Weakening of reality [ ] [BELEGAR] Daemon and weakening Report to College: [ ] [COLLEGE] Nothing [ ] [COLLEGE] Incoming Everchosen [ ] [COLLEGE] Everchosen and Greater Daemon [ ] [COLLEGE] Everchosen, Daemon, and Mathilde's candidacy - There will be a two hour moratorium.

Turn 40 Results - 2489.5 - Part 5

Spoiler: Voting results [*] [BELEGAR] Daemon and weakening [*] [COLLEGE] Everchosen and Greater Daemon Tally You'd only gotten partway into your telling of Belegar of your mishap before he'd sent runners to Kragg and Gunnars and had you explain the rest on the way up to your tower, the rest of the Gyrocarriage filled with as many Hammerers as will fit. "The likes of that need only the slightest opening to get their words in, if they put their mind to it," Gunnars explains to Belegar after their first pass over the room. "A resonant dream on the wrong night, a violent death in the wrong place, a malicious phrase of Dark Tongue translated into music and stuck in the wrong head. Or, of course, rogue magical energies in the wrong experiment. The attention of such a being is dangerous, of course, but its words alone have only the power they are allowed to have. It can be dangerous if it reaches the ear of the weak-willed, but if the target was an average Dawi or Undumgi then some counselling and a careful eye would be sufficient. For the likes of a Grey Wizard, the training they give their Magisters is better than that of most Witch Hunters, so there need be no concern at all." "Are you concerned?" Belegar asks you. You give it some thought. "More that I have such a being's attention at all than by that they were able to slip a message through the liminal barrier." "Which is certainly creased," Kragg says as he moves back and forth through the part of the room where the experiment was performed, and you can see the liminal barrier rippling slightly as he passes. "Strength is inconsistent, and overall weaker than it was before. Not enough to be dangerous on its own, but definitely enough that it would be dangerous to use this place for experimentation for at least the next year. I'd give it at least a decade before it's as safe as it was before this happened, but after a year it'd still be safer than anywhere else you might be playing damn-fool games with mystery fluids." "Is this a danger unique to wielders of the Winds?" Belegar asks cautiously. Kragg snorts. "Unfortunately not. There was a time when even the most blockheaded of Apprentices to Thungni's art would know better, but in these modern times it's not unknown for this sort of thing to arise from training or experimentation without proper fundamental education or supervision. If you push hard enough on the energies of Chaos they start pushing back, so every now and then you get some blockhead with more reach than grasp who thinks that whacking the Aethyr hard enough to draw the wrong sort of attention makes things safer. Older than her have managed worse for stupider reasons." Belegar stares hard at the spot in the air where the Vitae penetrated, as if trying to manifest Magesight by sheer stubbornness. "What's the worst case scenario if something did punch all the way through?" "Up here is isolated enough from magical energies that whatever came through would only have what was being experimented on to sustain itself," Kragg says. "Minus whatever was lost to actually making the breach in the first place. It could bring energies through with it, of course, but it's zero sum, it's either a larger force coming through or a smaller force that can last longer. There are other magical energies in the other towers, of course, but we knew they would be around Zhufokri experiments, so we built them sturdy. Unless they knew exactly how they were made - and they don't - it would take more effort to get at those energies than they'd gain by doing so." "And it's likewise isolated from any other potential victims," Gunnars says. "Besides which, the Undumgi are militarized enough that they'd respond quickly to an attack even from an unexpected direction. Unless bolstered by the emergence of a Cult to support it - and we are watching out for that sort of thing - whatever comes through would only manage limited damage before evaporating or being fended off." "The limiting factor for that lot isn't the amount of strength they can bring to bear, it's how much they can maintain in reality," Kragg agrees. "And keeping that low is the whole purpose of the Waystone Network, of which the Karak itself is a part. A lot would have to go very wrong over a long period of time for there to be enough ambient energy anywhere in the Karak to maintain a meaningful invasion force." Belegar nods as he digests that. "So it's not so much the experimental mishap that made this so alarming, but that it was compounded by the eye of such a being being turned this way in the first case." He gets a series of nods in response. "Which is likely because the retrieval of Karak Vlag spoked their wheel." "It seems that way," you say. The being could easily have been lying about that, but you've only locked blades with the forces of Chaos a handful of times and that was the most dramatic encounter you've had. Belegar nods again and relaxes slightly. "I do appreciate you bringing this to my attention, and expect you to do so again if things escalate further, but for now I'm happy to consider this Zhufokri business that was handled by Zhufokri, same as the occasional explosion atop Karag Lhune. Just make sure it stays handled." You exhale in relief. "Thank you for your trust." --- As you explain matters to Algard, he starts to rummage through his paperwork subdimensions for specific reports, and by the time you're wrapping up most of the surface of his usually-clear desk is covered. "Everchosen, Everchosen," he says to himself. "You know, before Asavar Kul there wasn't even widespread consensus that it was even a meaningful title, just a way for Norscan Champions to steal a bit of legitimacy from Morkar the Uniter, the closest they've ever come to a Sigmar. But a Kurgan claiming the title of Twelfth Everchosen and having the Norscans fall in line without any friction put paid to that. Ever since there's been a constant clamour over trying to fill out the roster, and of course everyone claims that the Chaos Champion that their province or country or Cult can take credit for slaying is definitely an Everchosen. Bretonnia says Kharan, Ostermark says the Dark Master of Mordheim, Hochland says Gorthor, all three provinces that had forces at Ostwald Moor say Harald the Hammer, Remas says Erghal Bloodhard. Walther says that there's a Druchii legend that Malekith recruited or enslaved one, Lady Magister Grey says that the Chaos Dwarves like to boast that they manipulated one into clearing a bunch of competition out of the Dark Lands, and even the undead Priest-King of Khemri claims to have killed one. All in all, there's at least three times as many candidates as there's been actual Everchosen, and that's not counting however many we might never have heard of. In any case, if it's time for a Thirteenth to rise, that would explain some of the infighting we've seen among Chaos cults recently. At first we thought it was knock-on effects from the Karak Vlag business, actually." "How so?" "Just as the Aethyr reflects reality, so too can the politics of the Chaos Cults reflect the Aethyr. If Higher Daemons start fighting, so too do Cults aligned with them. At the same time that you were yanking Karak Vlag back into the mountains, the Six-Cult of the Soulflayer and the Nine-Cult of the Eldritch Watcher went to war with each other, detonating decades of secrecy and careful recruitment in the process as Witch Hunters waded in and finished off the survivors." "Well, at least I can put a Use-Name to the voice," you say, with forced lightness. Not a True Name, of course. That would be too easy. "Since then there's been clashes between Norscan Reavers and Fimir in the Wasteland, and clashes at sea between other Norscans and a Plague-Fleet, and some sort of surreptitious war in Bretonnia between an undead host headed by a skeletal Chaos Lord and the Duke behind the False Grail business. You're not the first to mention competing for Everchosen as a possibility." He rearranges some of the papers and sighs. "We'll keep an eye on the situation, of course, but even if we knew for sure that it was happening, it's hard to convince anyone to mobilize until the forces of the enemy start doing the same. I do hope it takes its time and the Gods smile on the coming generation. Luitpold is no Magnus, and Vladimir is definitely no Alexis." "Any advice for dealing with the Daemon itself?" you prod. "Eventually we all pick up the kind of enemy that can't be solved with a knife," he says. "The danger of such beings shouldn't be underestimated, but can be overstated. It plots and it plans, of course, but remember that it's still a Daemon. Sometimes they'll rattle your cage just to see you bounce off the walls. And, of course, the 'conspicuously pay attention to someone to cause them to be distrusted by others' caper is one of the oldest ones in the book. If you gather some actual evidence of what it's up to, if it's up to anything at all instead of just claiming victory through a mouthful of blood, we can start moving to counter it. But until then, be alert but not rattled. If you start spending several times more effort trying to unravel its words than it spent speaking them, you begin a game you can never win." "What if that's what it's counting on?" "What if you getting out of bed in the morning is what it's counting on? Better people than either of us have driven themselves mad that way. No, unless it's levelled more than the usual volley of smug insinuations your way, there's not much more to be done." You very carefully react as though there was nothing more than that. "Thank you for your time, Magister Patriarch," you say, and rise and begin to leave the office. "Oh, and Lady Magister?" You turn, and are barely able to catch the glowing orb and its payload of Hysh as it hurtles towards you, and frown at its scrutiny and subsequent inactivity. "Why couldn't you just hand it to me?" "I could say it's so you let your guard down, but honestly it's because if it does its work on someone sitting right across from me, it messes with my paperwork enchantments." - May everyone enjoy any holidays they might be celebrating this time of year without worry about Daemonic disclosure hanging over their head.

Turn 40 Results - 2489.5 - Part 7

To prepare for your search for the missing nexus of Reikland, you stretched out a large map of the province on a table in a study of the former House Elwyn estate. "For Axe Bite Pass," you said to Johann, Max and Egrimm, "we're looking at the Counties of Bögenhafen and Osburg, and the Barony of Ussingen. And the March of Helmgart itself, of course." With a gesture, you mark the area with Aethyric colour. "For Grey Lady Pass, it's either Ubersreik, Auerswald, or Stimmigen - Wittgendorf is on the wrong side of the line between Nuln and Altdorf. So it's mostly going to be the Vorbergland, the fertile foothills between the Grey Mountains and the Reikwald. This is the breadbasket of the Reikland, and some of the most heavily populated lands in the Empire outside of its cities, so it's either going to already be a landmark or tucked away really well." Then the four of you descended upon the Library of Mournings to search through their records of Elven settlements in those areas to narrow down the possibilities. Considering the Library is named that because it holds the administrative records from when all of those were the constituent parts of the nascent Kingdom of Elthin Arvan, you're reasonably certain they'll have what you're looking for. Once you've marked the map with every record of Elves building so much as a lean-to, you transplant your search to Altdorf and compare your map against the hall of records in the Palace of Retribution, which is known more officially as the Imperial Courthouse, and to search for anything odd that might be traces of ancient construction left off the official maps. The room you commandeered descends into studious silence, only occasionally broken by someone voicing their discoveries. "The Hägercrybs are dotted with ancient cairns attributed to the Unberogens, and the Hill Dwarves used to have mines in the area. The northern stretch would be in the right area, though it's more east than I think is likely." "It looks like there was an Elven trade outpost around where Bögenhafen is now. The Unberogens fortified the ruins around -400 IC and called it Boigenfastis, but it was levelled by greenskins about -200 and wasn't rebuilt until after Black Fire Pass. It could be that the nexus was there, and it was destroyed or buried in rubble then." "Sigmar is said to have had a magical tomb built near Grey Lady Pass to contain the body of a Chaos Champion that had been raised by Nagash, and continued to harry the tribes after Nagash was defeated. His shamans might have recognized the power of a nexus and used its power for it." "I suppose Ubersreik is out, if there was anything significant in its catacombs it would have been discovered while the Skaven were being expelled from under it." "Maybe so, but the fortress of Black Rock is outside its walls. Maybe it was named for the presence of a literal, and particularly impressive, black rock?" "Tor Fanloc, which was in the Seifenhügel, looks very close to where Midfurt is now." "No, Midfurt's on the Blut, it couldn't be the location of an outpost in the Seifenhügel." "I know you said west of the Nuln-Altdorf line, but there's a rather strange clock tower in Kemperbad that drove mad the one who made it. A Magicker experimenting on a Waystone, perhaps?" "Apparently there's a Waystone in Grünburg that a local noble wants to turn into a statue of himself? Probably not what we're looking for, but I'll make sure someone has a stern word with him." "It's a bit far north, but there's a castle in the southern Skaag Hills that's just called 'The Horn', and I can't find any record as to why. Could be it was built on something horn-shaped." "There's a castle called Stychelschloss but I can't find any records of a Stychel dynasty, and it's only accessible by a roadside inn with a ferry that's called 'The Nobody Knows'." "The 'stychel' could have been taken from the Bretonnian for 'stylus', that would make sense if it was an Elven research outpost at one point." "Paranoth apparently has a tower near Eilhart? I don't think that would be it, but I'll ask the Jades to be sure." "It's a ruin nowadays, but Taal's Horn Keep near Helmgart supposedly had a Waystone inside it." "Reikland," you say with a sigh after the possibilities keep accumulating, "has too much unexplained oddities tucked away in its nooks and crannies. How are there this many unanswered questions this close to Altdorf?" "There's always something more pressing that needs attention," Max says. "If a weird castle or a ruined temple isn't actively spitting out monsters, then it gets ignored in favour of dealing with the ones that are." The four of you spend a while sorting the possibilities in order of how promising you find them and sorting out the path you'll take to investigate them, glad to have a Gyrocarriage at your disposal instead of having to slow yourself to the pace of Max on Shadowhorseback. --- Two weeks pass in a haze of Gyrocarriage flights, mediocre taverns, and souvenirs that Max insists on accumulating from some of Reikland's most milquetoast landmarks, until you find yourself somewhere north of a nowhere town allegedly famous for its red cheeses, chasing a faded mark on an Elven map of questionable significance, with Egrimm having accumulated more and more reasons to be elsewhere as the stretch of unremarkable villages grew longer and longer. "I still think that it's just a label for this part of the Reikwald," Max says, lagging severely behind you and Johann as the two of you stride tirelessly through thick undergrowth. "It was just the word 'Athel', like on the other maps, and I don't think that smudge was enough to be the remnants of a whole other word." "Best to be sure," you respond shortly. "It was the same plain handwriting that they used for places like Tor Fanloc and Tor Yvanithress. Elven cartography usually gets really fancy when a forest needs labelling. Besides, after two weeks of looking at thoroughly unimpressive rocks in thoroughly unimpressive villages, we could use a change of scenery," you respond, Branulhune appearing in your hand to hack through a particularly thick tangle of lianas. "Does the body good to get a bit of fresh air," Johann agrees, casually backhanding a probing Bloodsedge branch that had taken an interest in him. "Maybe your bodies," Max grumbles back, trying to untangle his boot from a briar. "Mine is quite happy in civilization." But Max's intermittent chorus of grumbling is eventually silenced when the steepening terrain funnels you down a narrow pass almost entirely clogged with hanging vines that need hacking through, and the first indication you have that you've found something is when Branulhune gives a judder of increased force as it finds itself impacting stone instead of wood, and it shears through the stubby pillar that had once been half of an archway. You and Johann, and Max when he catches up, look down at freshly-exposed white stone that contrasts starkly with the brownish-green of moss covering the exterior. Soon after that the corridor of stone opens up into a dense forest of trees and pillars, both identically overgrown with moss, and then leading into a maze of likewise identically overgrown cliff faces and stone walls. "Huh," you say. --- As the three of you poke through the ruins, you revise your estimate up from outpost to full-blown settlement, but at no point do you find anything that sheds any light as to its purpose. Though by all appearances it's been at least centuries since the last time these ruins had visitors, the last people here certainly were not Elves, as the place has been thoroughly picked clean of anything not nailed down. That plants the seed of a suspicion that the people of the Empire were not to blame - not because they're too noble to loot ancient ruins, but because if it was them they'd have quarried the ruins for stone as well - and that suspicion is proven quite correct when you start to recognize that among and sometimes atop the elegant lines of Eltharin is the cruder but still flowing curls of Belthani ideograms. When the scale of the place sinks in, you search for a place flat enough to land a Gyrocarriage, then you and Max begin to set up camp while Johann makes his way back to civilization to fetch Adela and start ferrying supplies in. "This doesn't fit with all the other nexus locations," Max says to you as you clear the landing area of debris. "It's isolated and defensible and far from trade routes. Even going from Altdorf to Helmgart bypasses it." "It might have been built as the Elven equivalent of Karak Norn," you say. "We know that getting over or through the mountains was tricky for the network, so it might be it needs to be tucked right up against the foothills instead of being able to thread the needle of the pass." "If it was the same as Karak Norn, it'd be at Helmgart, or at least closer to it" he replies. "Maybe in that Waystone at Taal's Horn Keep." "Once Johann gets back we'll scout the entire place and settle it one way or the other," you say with a shrug. "It's the Belthani graffiti that interests me. Maybe they learned how to make nexuses here, if they didn't know it already." "Or they might have just picked it clean. According to some histories, they didn't even have bronze before the arrival of the Imperial tribes. Upgrading from soft native metals to Elven steel would be an incredibly big deal for them." It doesn't take too long for the Gyrocarriage to arrive - unlike you, Johann is capable of almost his full speed in dense forests - and the three of you begin a thorough and systematic sweep of the ruins. To your mild surprise, at no point are the three of you ambushed by anything more threatening than strangler vines and some kind of corvid defending its nest. Truly uninhabited ruins are very much a rarity in the Empire, and you suspect that these will not remain uninhabited for long now that you've reopened the overgrown entrance to it. Your search eventually terminates at the central building, a large, domed building topped with the jagged remains of what had once been spires. "A temple?" Max guesses. "Not with that much energy pouring out of it," Johann replies. "There's definitely no leylines coming into here, right?" "Unless it's coming deep underground and from the west, no," you say firmly. "So where's the energy coming from?" "And why is it mostly Ghyran?" Johann asks. "Didn't you say that a leyline outflow would necessarily have a core of Dhar?" "Ones from Waystones would be. I haven't made a study of Nexuses yet, I'd assumed they just scaled up the workings of Waystones." The three of you cautiously make your way up the ruined entranceway, framed by ruined arches, and into the building proper. The interior is a single immense room extending several meters below ground level and topped by the dome, dominated by a massive, floating shape of marble fringed with gold, at least twenty meters tall and shaped like an angular plumb bob with concave faces. It floats on a point of crystal several meters above an identical crystal inset into the floor at the centre of what looks to you to be a much larger version of a Waystone base. The room is ringed by a walkway at the level of the object's crystal, and extending out over the floor below are what look like three control platforms, each with a control object of marble and crystal embedded at their points. "I retract my argument that this isn't likely to be the nexus," Max says after a long silence. "Definitely looks the part, doesn't it?" you say. "But while we've already ruled out it doing nexus things, it's definitely doing something." "It's fountaining Ghyran into the air, is what it's doing," Johann says. "That might explain why the Vorbergland is so fertile." "Ghyran doesn't just come from nowhere," you say. "And it can't be a portal like the Tarn of Tears unless it's dumping the other seven-eighths of the outflow elsewhere." "Well, if it's not coming from a leyline and it's not coming from the Aethyr, what else is left?" Max asks. "The Reikwald's Dreaming Wood? It can't be, Cadaeth told me that it's dormant," you reply. "Did she say why?" Max pushes. You search your memory. "'The magic that once sustained it disappeared'," you reply slowly. "Well. I guess we found where it went." Johann looks the nexus up and down. "They turned a Nexus into a massive Aethyric shunt draining the magic out of the Dreaming Wood?" "Taking magic that would make the Reikwald a lot livelier than it is, and instead using it as a sort of magical fertilizer," you say. "I wonder if it was the Elves or the Belthani that did it." "Even if it was the Elves, then the Belthani left it be," Max says, looking at the densely-scrawled graffiti covering the walls. Perhaps you're just projecting, but here it looks a lot more like research notes than the incidental street graffiti you'd imagined the runes outside to be. "I thought they were all about living in harmony with the natural world." "It's a lot easier to live in harmony with a dog than a wolf," Johann says. "A lot of people would consider trading a magical and unruly forest for turning otherwise marginal foothills into a breadbasket to be an absolute steal," you say. "Including, I'd guess, the current nobility of the Reikland. This complicates things. I was hoping it was just a matter of finding a dormant Nexus and turning it on." "Well, not really," Johann says. "If Marienburg's nexus is blocked or destroyed and there's no other way to reconnect the leylines, then turning this back into its original purpose - which I think would just be a matter of rotating it from the Aethyric back to the spatial - would be much better than letting everything east of the Grey Mountains turn into wasteland." "That's true," you say, brightening up. "And at least now we know to protect it - Gods know what troubles the Skaven or Beastmen could cause with this place if they found it first. Or just someone that'd want to knock it over so they can strip the gold off of it. And you know what? Since this is what makes the Vorbergland's grains and vines so profitable, it would be easier to justify a tax or a corvée on it to see to its proper defence." "A fort, or a chapterhouse, maybe," Max says. "Does Rhya have any Knightly Orders?" "They've got a few heavily-armed monasteries, that would work. Or the Jades might want to set up a branch here," you say. "Well, this much marble would probably pay for a fair bit of it," Johann says. "Tor Lithanel might even be wanting to buy it." "There are a few interesting possibilities," you muse, brightening. "That does seem like it would make for some interesting debates." --- While the Library-We is coming along quite well in terms of organizing and maintaining the library itself, they're still very resistant to the idea of complete strangers coming into their home and endangering their books with their presence, and have a tendency to lurk alarmingly around anyone they're particularly suspicious of the intentions of. Some might say that this is an inherent downside of the We as librarians, but in your experience, a significant amount of human librarians have the exact same attitude towards visitors. And if you were completely honest, you're not entirely opposed to having a constant guard making sure your rarer volumes aren't being mistreated. So you're happy to consider the education of the Library-We to be entirely on course. But while the role of librarians plays to a number of the strengths of the We, the same could not be said of them as a scribe, as it is a necessarily nomadic role. To regularly uproot a We from its webs and expose its Egglayers to danger as it travels en masse to a new job site would be very distressing to them, and likely equally distressing to whoever it is you ask to host a colony of giant spiders. No, unless you can think of something particularly novel, your scribes would have to be rather more prosaic than your librarians. There's three basic approaches that come to mind: you could commission the efforts of an established organizations who are already extremely capable of performing this role, such as the Cult of Scripsisti or Clio or the Runescribes Guild, giving you a ready-made workforce that is ready to go from day one and willing to expand their capabilities if needed. You could seek out individuals with the necessary skillset on a per-job basis, either spreading the net of the EIC to seek out those with that skillset or just going directly to the universities to offer work to their students, giving you as much flexibility as possible to scale up or down the workforce as needed. Or you could hire on a full-time staff on a permanent retainer and train them up more or less from scratch, drawing from either the local population or from the orphanages of the Old World, tailoring them to your needs and guaranteeing their loyalty. From where will Mathilde recruit an army of scribes for the Library of Kron-Azril-Ungol? Outsourced: [ ] [SCRIBE] Cult of Scripsisti Dedicated to the Goddess of Writing, considers the creation of accurate copies to be their religious duty. Will build ties to the Cult of Verena. Reikspiel, Tilean, Old Reikspiel, Classical. [ ] [SCRIBE] Cult of Clio Dedicated to the Goddess of History, considers the preservation of historical documents to be their religious duty. Will build ties to the Cult of Verena. Reikspiel, Tilean, Old Reikspiel, Classical. [ ] [SCRIBE] Runescribes Guild Highly-skilled, diligent, and extremely reliable. Reikspiel, Khazalid. Gig work: [ ] [SCRIBE] Empire Skim from literate citizens willing to travel for work everywhere the EIC has a presence. Reikspiel, Kislevarin, more languages as EIC expands. [ ] [SCRIBE] Universities Take students from the universities of the Empire who are looking for work to fund either their education or their drinking habits. Wide range of languages, but can tend to be a bit unruly. Reikspiel, Tilean, Estalian, Kislevarin, Old Reikspiel, Classical. Permanent employees: [ ] [SCRIBE] Locals Will demonstrate the value of literacy to the local population, and will be reasonably loyal and self-sufficient. Reikspiel, Tilean. [ ] [SCRIBE] Orphans You can take your pick of literate orphans from throughout the Old World, and train them up from scratch to guarantee their loyalty. Reikspiel, Tilean, Estalian, Kislevarin. Thus concludes the work Mathilde performed these past months, but not every waking moment was filled with work. With whom did she spend her free time? The five with the most votes will be chosen, not counting those locked in. [+] Social interaction initiated by someone else (locked in) Laurelorn [ ] Max The entire time you've known Maximilian, he has been pursuing his own goal of true transmutation via magically-enhanced blacksmithing. Check in to see how he's going with that. [ ] Thorek See what inroads Thorek has made with the Major Houses of Tor Lithanel. Karak Eight Peaks [ ] Panoramia In the wake of an apparently quite controversial paper, Panoramia is finally taking her Magisterial exams. Be there to observe the fallout and offer moral support. [ ] Gretel She's apparently getting involved in the Karaz Ankor's ambitions in the Border Princes. [ ] Okri You've met Loremaster Okri of Karak Eight Peaks once before. Pay him a visit and see how his great ambitions for heavily-armed Ironbreakers delivered by Gyrocarriage are going. Foreign Relations [ ] Sylvania Meet this would-be Markgraf Nyklaus for yourself. [ ] Middenland See how the Ulricans are going with their new Eonir coreligionists. [ ] The Black Water Canal Pay another visit to the canal project, and see if there's any further signs of sabotage. [ ] Druchii Diplomats Check in on these unexpected visitors to Tor Lithanel. Friends Abroad Following Up [ ] Brief the Emperor Though the Waystone Project is in early days, you've had a few early wins and have uncovered some important information about the Waystone Network as it relates to the Empire's security. [ ] Amber College Check in on the salamanders. [ ] Gold College See what's become of their research into Skaven technology. [ ] Skull River Ambush Look into the investigation of the mining of the Skull River, and any consequences of it. - There will be a five hour moratorium. - As always, feel free to suggest ideas for social actions, especially ones I've okayed and then forgotten about. I feel like there's at least one or two of those. - Egrimm is missing from the latter part of this turn because, erm, I forgot he was along for this task. There's no concrete results he could have delivered above and beyond what you got if present though, you only lost out on the pleasure of his company.

Turn 40 Social - 2489.5 - Part 1

Spoiler: Voting results [*] Panoramia [*] Brief the Emperor [*] Sylvania [*] Thorek [*] Max [*] [SCRIBE] Locals Tally "Your Majesty," you say with a bow, as Emperor Luitpold enters the Mappa Mundi room of the Imperial Palace, where an immense mosaic map of the Empire covers the floor. "Lady Magister," he responds with a nod, and gestures to the man following him in. "This is Graf Otto von Bitternach, Chamberlain of the Seal." "We've met," you say as you shake the Graf's hand. "Her advice was quite helpful during Marienburg's talk of barring the First Fleet from the Sea of Claws," he agrees. "Dragomas said you had news regarding your project with the Elves of Laurelorn," the Emperor prompts. "I do, with several facets to it. What do you know of the Waystones that dot your realm, your Majesty?" "They're ancient Elven artefacts that ward off dark magics, I believe." You consider this. Whoever came up with that layman's explanation was quite clever: it explains what they need to know and minimizes the chances they'd get it in their head to mess with them, either out of fear or ambition. "In effect that's true, but their actual mechanism is rather more involved. You see, when magic first entered the world, it accumulated over centuries until it became thick enough to sustain entire armies of Daemons, who went on to rampage through the continents and besiege the isle of Ulthuan. In response, the Asur created the Great Vortex to drain away excess magical energy, allowing them to break the siege and banish the Daemonic armies. In the centuries that followed they met and entered into an alliance with the Dwarves, and together they built the Waystone Network across the world." You wave your hand and glowing streams of light spread across the floor, forming themselves into the pattern of Nexuses and leylines as they were in the time before the War of the Ancients. "They achieved equilibrium, with the magic flowing in from the Northern Wastes being balanced out by the magic flowing out through the leylines. But the War of the Ancients turned the Elves and Dwarves against each other, and in the end the Elves of Ulthuan abandoned the Old World, save for a couple of holdout colonies that refused to leave. Our ancestors filled the vacuum, building our own cities upon the ruins of the Elves and, either knowingly or not, protecting most of the most important Waystones. But not all." You point to Ostland, and three points of light go dark. "The Brass Keep, the Blood Fane, and the Tower of Melkhior are all now held by dark forces, making the Forest of Shadows that much darker." You point again, this time to Ostermark. "Mordheim was destroyed, and it's no coincidence that the Vampire Wars began soon after." You point to Westerland. "Almshoven was destroyed by a Plague Fleet during the Great War." You clench your fist, and all the streams of light flicker and disappear. "We teetered on the edge of oblivion and didn't even realize it. But Fort Solace was established soon after with an Asur-supplied monolith at the core of its lighthouse." You wave your hand and the light reappears, rerouted through this new junction. "To get to the Great Vortex, the leylines have to get past the mountains. And currently, the only place they can do that is through Marienburg and its holdings, the maintenance of which is dependent on the largesse of the Asur. Which, I feel, adds an uncomfortable factor to the rather strained state of relations between them and us." "Would they go so far as to hold it hostage?" Emperor Luitpold asks, his eyes turning to the Chamberlain of the Seal. "Hard to say," Graf Otto replies after a moment of thought. "I doubt Ulthuan would actually follow through on any veiled threats - that sort of thing would be ruinous for their reputation in the Old World - but if Marienburg wasn't in the habit of slipping leashes they'd still be a province." "There has been suspicion that the mining on the Skull River was the work of rogue elements within Marienburg," you mention. "And my contacts within Tor Lithanel suggest that Ulthuan would have a limited ability to replace destroyed Waystones." "So some rogue brinksmanship could end up flinging us right over the edge, even if most of Marienburg doesn't want it," the Emperor muses. "Why did the Elves build this with a single point of failure in the first place?" "Good question, one I've been digging into myself. And what I've found is that they didn't." You point to Wissenland. "Bugman's Brewery, built on the site of the Dwarven settlement of Kazad Thar by members of Karak Norn's royal family. My suspicion is that this was once part of an alternate route for magic to flow, from there to Karak Norn to the Elven settlement within Athel Loren. But the reputation of the Asrai in this modern era suggests they are no longer the sort to leave immense magical power untouched. So feeding them the magical runoff from most of a continent could be... problematic." There's murmurs of agreement from your audience. "For this reason, I suspect the Dwarves of Karak Norn might have removed this possibility millennia ago, most likely during the War of the Ancients." "You haven't asked them?" the Emperor asks. "Not yet," you reply. "It's a minefield of taboo subjects, so should only be approached with great forethought and delicacy." "And Karak Norn are an odd bunch, even by Dwarven standards," Graf Otto adds. You point to Reikland, and an isolated point of light appears up against the mountains. "And then there's my most recent discovery: Athel Yenlui, hidden in the foothills north of Helmgart. And I do mean hidden, if I didn't have a map from the Eonir pointing me straight to it I doubt I would have found it at all. Once a Waystone allowing magic to flow from Altdorf to Castle Parravon, but since adapted into what we're calling an Aethyric Shunt. The purpose it now serves is twofold: it is why the Reikwald is so much milder than the Drakwald or the Great Forest, and it is why the Vorbergland is so fertile." The Emperor frowns. "I take it that it can't continue doing that while serving this Waystone Network of yours?" "I'm afraid not." "Well, at least it defangs the hostage scenario. They'd be able to confirm the existence of this Athel with their contacts in Ulthuan, and that would dissuade them from following through, since it would unite the Old World against them without actually putting overwhelming pressure on the Empire. Speaking of Ulthuan, any sign of them sniffing around Tor Lithanel?" "Not yet, though the Naggarothi are making overtures." "Won't be long until Ulthuan arrives then, mark my words," Graf Otto says. "But if we're going to make use of it," the Emperor says, "we need to make sure we keep a hold of it. Especially if it's currently responsible for the relative bounty of the Reikland." He walks over the map, gingerly stepping over the magical light signifying the leylines, and leans over to consider the position of Athel Yenlui. "It had to be there. The Margrave of Helmgart might be able to afford the cost of garrisoning it, but that would get the Graf of Eilhart and the Baron of Ussingen up in arms, even though neither of them can afford it. Might even be easier to foist it off onto the Graf of Schilderheim since it's accessible via the Schilder, but then the Graf of Holthusen would oppose it. No, it'll have to be someone else." He pauses, his frown deepening. "Would the Elves try to claim it?" "No," you say confidently, "the revanchist faction going extinct is what allowed them to reach out to us in the first place. Besides, they're as bad as Altdorfers about how insistent they are that their city is the best place to live." "One of the Cults, maybe, or the Jades or Ambers. We'll see. What of the Project itself?" "Investigation of the medium-sized Waystones is ongoing, but we've managed to recreate the smaller, supplemental ones using a few different magical paradigms. Actually implementing them would be long-term projects - my best estimate is that a team of four magic-users could meet the needs of a province within a decade - but if they are put into place, then the benefits of reducing the amount of stagnant magic would be widespread. Citizens will be healthier and saner, there'll be less mutants and Beastmen born, storms of magic will be rarer, there'll be less mayhem on Geheimnisnacht and Hexensnacht, and less power available to Necromancers and Sorcerers." "Shouldn't be that hard a sell to at least set it up around the cities and larger towns. What do you mean by 'magical paradigms'?" "There's a Jade Order ritual that requires interfacing with an established forest. I'm not sure if Reikland would qualify because of the effects of the Aethyric Shunt, but that should work fine for Talabecland." He nods, and you continue. "There's a Kislevite Hag Witch ritual that uses a water spirit to establish them, that would be suited for the southern provinces and Reikland." "What's the legal status of the Hag Witches?" "They don't perform magic directly, they wrangle various kinds of spirits to get things done. According to mainstream doctrine in the Empire, that would make them closer to Priests than Wizards. Besides that, the ritual can be performed by our own Wizards as long as they can secure the cooperation of a water spirit." He nods. "Finally, there's a ritual dedicated to a minor Goddess worshipped within the Forest of Shadows called Halétha. This one seems to me the most flexible as it can be performed anywhere as long as it's done by a member of their priesthood, but legally it's tricky. They're associated with the northern branches of the Hedgewise, a rural magical tradition that's as old as the Empire, but has splintered over the years into a number of different belief systems. The Grey Order has been working on bringing some of their branches into the fold, and their involvement in this project is a part of that, but the efforts of the Templars to stamp them out has made them slow to trust." He nods. "Dragomas and Yorri clash often on the topic." "A question, if I may," Graf Otto says, and the Emperor nods his assent. "You say this magic flows through Bretonnia to reach Ulthuan. Does this mean that there are more vulnerable bottlenecks within its borders?" "I've attempted to secure Bretonnia's involvement, but they seem to feel snubbed by their not being host to the Project, so I can only speculate, but the geography of the Tilean-Estalian border suggests it might be a point of vulnerability, and the dire state of Mousillon suggests that Gisoreux would now be another. The only point I've confirmed as an exit point for magic on the Old World is Los Cabos in Estalia, though Castle Lyonesse may be one as well." "Are you suggesting," the Emperor says slowly, "that the entire Empire might be lost to the Chaos Wastes if a single Estalian city-port were to fall?" "I don't think it would come to that, your Majesty. Ulthuan appears to be keeping a close eye on Los Cabos, and should it be endangered I believe it likely that they would either defend or replace it, as they did to Almshoven. I suspect that they have come to rely on a constant influx of magic to maintain their realm." "Disquieting nevertheless. Thank you for your work in this endeavour, Lady Magister, and I task you with continuing it. The benefits you describe are worthwhile, and though I do not like to hear of these hitherto unknown vulnerabilities, I'd much rather know about them now than when the razing of some southern village dooms the continent." "It is an honour to serve, your Majesty. I will pass word of any further developments via the Supreme Patriarch." --- Markgraf Nyklaus Schurz, as it turns out, is Markgraf twice over. First, as one of many sons of the Markgravine of Essen and therefore, as Markgraf is an inherently militant title, automatically entitled to call himself by the title he must be ready to inherit should his mother and many older brothers be slain at that frontier of the Empire. And now, though not yet announced to the Empire at large, soon to be the warden of the much greater march of Eastern Stirland. The man himself is an alarmingly intense man a few years your junior, wearing the extravagant twin-tailed hat of a seaborn officer and has a goatee that juts alarmingly out from his chin. "Do you know what a caul is?" he asks you abruptly after introductions are exchanged. You look at him quizzically. "The headdress?" "Haha, in a sense. Very rarely a child is born with part of the sac that contained them still clinging to their scalp. Among certain sects of the Morrites, including my own family, it is considered a sign that the one that bears it is to become the next Andanti, the Morr-blessed slayer of Vampires, that my family believed itself part of the bloodline of. Incorrectly, as it turned out. So very many years trained in a form of combat senseless to merely mortal men, and a jaunt into Sylvania to awaken what was thought to be my birthright. It was, in all respects, an utter farce. One that in all likelihood would have killed me, were it not for your very self, and your Grace, carving a bloody swathe across it and distracting all the worst horrors that dwell in its shadows. Instead it scarred me, and killed my handlers, and gave me opportunity to leave for the other fraternity that considers the caul to be a mark of greatness: sailors. A less glorious brotherhood, perhaps, but one that manages to produce more than one worthy a generation. "It was, I can now admit, a youthful tantrum, but one I will never regret, as it taught me the measure of myself, and over the years earned me glory enough that I could return to my disgraced family and snatch back the petty titles that was all they could truly pass down. Now I return to the place that made a lie of everything I thought I was, and the place that I will teach the lie of what it thinks itself to be. Sylvania has not existed for centuries, not since the Von Draks went extinct in the maw of the Vampire. It is now, and will never be more than, Eastern Stirland. I will spill the blood of those that found it comfortable to pay their taxes in the blood of others, and I will allow all the others the gentle mercy of taxes in unsanguine kind. It will be as blissfully moral a task as the pursuit of the fanged ones, as those that resist deserve all the evils that I will pay unto them, and all that welcome me will deserve all the mercies that they will learn to be normal in every other corner of our realm." You take a moment to take in his slightly manic speech. "Your ambitions, at least, are the equal of the task before you." "And am I? After all, is that not why you are here? To pass judgement on the man that will finish the job that your younger self began?" You return the man's frankly evaluating look with one of your own. "I'm mostly here to make sure you're not actually a Vampire. The rest is curiosity." "Can you actually spot that?" "In my experience, yes. I suspect that there are some who may be able to make their soul look like that of a regular human, but it would take constant concentration and an extremely deft hand to be able to make ambient Winds react normally to it, and that's only if they knew they needed to do so." "Fascinating. Is whatever you're currently doing more important than Sylvania?" "Funny you should ask, it might actually be better for Sylvania..." A long and detailed conversation about Sylvania and the many different possible approaches to taming its horrors, you part ways a lot less unsure about leaving Sylvania in his hands. He's clearly out of his depth, but aware of it and willing to keep digging as far down as it takes to entrench himself. Short of doing the job yourself, that may be the best you can ask for. He's also a touch on the overly energetic side, but that's far from the worst of character quirks that might be expected of the sort of person willing to take this job. That's not to say you won't turn a careful eye in his direction from time to time, but you might not need to have a blade ready every time you do so. - Happy fifth birthday to the quest.